<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Going beyond the known</title>
    <description>A travel blog by Monika Suchoszek.</description>
    <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 11:52:25 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 11:52:25 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Coastal city Platja de Gandia, great destination for holidays with kids</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to combine relaxation on the beach with some city exploration, a stay in Platja de Gandia paired with a trip to 
Valencia is a perfect choice. It’s just a quick 1-hour and 15-minute train ride from Valencia’s city center to reach the 
charming seaside town of Platja de Gandia. During our trip, we also ventured to Cullera, another coastal gem, and explored the 
fascinating Oceanogràfic, situated within the stunning Gardens of Turia in Valencia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Platja de Gandia truly surprised us! With its 3-kilometer-long promenade, this beach was more than we expected. Our apartment 
was conveniently located just a street away, right next door to a cozy fruit shop, a small local bakery, and a spot offering coffee, 
warm chocolate, and freshly made churros (churreria). The beach itself is expansive, with soft, fine sand and wooden walkways that make 
access to the shore easy, especially for families with strollers or those with limited mobility. The beach is well-equipped 
with free restrooms, plenty of space for sunbathing, and most importantly, it was never overly crowded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_194625_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights of Platja de Gandia is its lively promenade, which comes alive in the evenings. It’s lined with shops, restaurants, 
and cafes, making it the perfect place for an evening stroll. Street vendors add to the vibrant atmosphere, selling handmade 
jewellery, sunglasses, football shirts, and plenty of souvenir trinkets. You’ll even find people offering henna tattoos or 
creating colorful braids for children. The promenade is wide, allowing sufficient space for pedestrians, cyclists, and scooters, 
though shade can be a bit hard to come by.One thing to note: the local council has banned 
dogs on the beach, so if you’re traveling with pets, you’ll need to make alternative plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Platja de Gandia is relatively unknown to international tourists. With most visitors being Spanish, English 
isn’t as common as one might assume and therefore, so we did encounter few issues in the restaurants when trying to find a 
table or make a reservation. Though knowledge of a few basic words in Spanish goes a long way!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/P8243643.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240824_125726_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240824_193443_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/IMG-20240829-WA0030_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights of our time at Gandia’s beach was the dedicated kite-flying area. Every afternoon around 5 PM, the 
local kite-club would gather to set up an array of colorful kites right on the beach, almost directly in front of our favorite 
ice cream spot, Cognigni. This group, known as “Cometas Gandia,” brings a playful, lively energy to the beach with their 
kites, many featuring fun characters like Tom and Jerry—an absolute hit with the kids! You can even follow them on Instagram 
for updates on their kite displays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_185700.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_185216.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a refreshing break from the beach, we did a day trip to Cullera by train, to visit the impressive Cullera Castle. The castle, 
built in the 10th century, sits atop a hill and offers stunning panoramic views of the city, the Mediterranean Sea, and 
the surrounding coastal area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The well-preserved fortress is a beautiful blend of Moorish, Gothic, and Romanesque architectural styles, showcasing its 
historical evolution over the centuries. Originally, the castle had several towers and walls, many of which have been restored, 
allowing visitors to experience its grandeur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most notable feature is the Torre del Racó de Sant Antoni, a tower that rewards you with breathtaking views of the 
landscape. Attached to the castle is the Sanctuary of the Virgen del Castillo, a quaint Gothic-style chapel built in the 
19th century. Inside the castle, there’s also a small museum with exhibits that highlight the history of the fortress and 
the region. You can explore ancient artifacts, including weapons, pottery, and medieval tools, giving you a fascinating 
glimpse into life during the castle’s active years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_104252.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_111407.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_111356.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_114637_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_115355.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After visiting the castle, we walked back down to the city and had a delicious lunch in 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/HaTVLGfD6GLiKt8J7&quot;&gt;Aroma de Grecia&lt;/a&gt;. There was also a lovely &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/ZhDGhQPShJEZgABs9&quot;&gt;bakery La Delicia&lt;/a&gt;
that served the most amazing savory spinach dumplings—definitely worth a try! We didn’t have time to follow the shore and
check the resto of the city and just had a break on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/9amFPqWC5wau2kJp9&quot;&gt;playground&lt;/a&gt; near the beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the city is a hidden gem, perfect for a family-friendly escape. An ideal spot to unwind, enjoy the sun, and 
soak up the local atmosphere! For an exciting day trip, hop on a train to nearby Cullera or Valencia or take a bus from nearby
Gandia to Alicante (buses leaving from Gania bus station, back side of the train station). In our opinion, wonderful alternative 
to tourist-heavy beach destinations—perfect for families looking to relax and experience something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re arriving at Valencia’s Airport (Aeroport), it’s an easy trip to the city center. Metro lines 3 and 5 will take 
you from Aeroport to North Station (Xàtiva) in just 21 minutes, covering Zone AB+. The fare is €5.80 per person.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From Valencia North Station, catch the C1 train to Gandia. Trains run every 30 to 60 minutes, and the journey takes 
about 1 hour and 15 minutes. A one-way ticket costs €6.30, but you can save €0.50 per trip by recharging your ticket, 
reducing the cost to €5.80. While most trains stop at Gandia, only a few continue on to Platja de Gandia. If your train 
terminates at Gandia, you can take bus L2 to the beach. The bus runs every 20 minutes and costs €1.60 (or €1.70 on Sundays). 
Tickets can be purchased directly from the driver.
The Platja de Gandia train station is quite basic, with just one platform and a ticket machine. However, the machine’s 
translations can be confusing for non-Spanish speakers, as not all options are fully translated. After purchasing your 
ticket, remember to validate it at a separate area on the platform before boarding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The beach near Platja de Gandia is well-equipped, offering public bathrooms every few meters, beach bars, and recycling 
bins to keep the area clean. There are also opportunities for sports like football and volleyball, plus exercise stations 
along the promenade. The beach is spotless, with public showers, toilets, and a first aid station available, making it 
family-friendly. Lifeguards and police on quads keep an eye on the beach, adding to the sense of security.
One thoughtful touch: beside each wooden walkway leading to the beach, there’s an information board with a map clearly 
marking all the nearby amenities.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240829_130608.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_192333_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/P8233575.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240824_094550_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_194758_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our favourites places to eat are listed below with amazing ice cream place that was our place to be every afternoon!
Note that most restaurants are closing in the early afternoon and reopening around 8pm where the whole city comes alive.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/2zBJ8acASm4TmJSK8&quot;&gt;Cognigni&lt;/a&gt;: Amazing Argentinean icecream&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/MqcaPoHHPfbn2Lqd7&quot;&gt;INDIAN RASOI&lt;/a&gt;: Indian Food - Try the Goan Chicken !&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/ixtKCKtX8iJ115bXA&quot;&gt;Restaurante Boga&lt;/a&gt;: Local project to provide jobs to people with intellectual disabilities and promote social integration - Menu changes daily&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/sesQQSkJVCbdM6NeA&quot;&gt;Restaurante Casa José&lt;/a&gt;: A wide variety of sea-food and local dishes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240826_153143_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240826_180430_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cullera &lt;a href=&quot;https://visit-cullera.es/guia/castillo-de-cullera/&quot;&gt;Castle&lt;/a&gt;, is a great spot for a family outing, with entry
tickets priced at just €3 for adults, and kids seem to 
get in for free (at least we weren’t asked to pay for our toddlers). While none of the towers or the different sections 
of walls surrounding the castle were open during our visit, the overall experience was still worth it because of the views.
You can either drive right up to the castle and park there or walk from the Mercat de Cullera (which also has public 
toilets). There seems to be some confusion in reviews about an elevator to the castle—just to clarify, the lift only 
takes you from the parking area to the castle entrance, which is just a few meters up, and there’s another one after 
the ticket office to the main entrance.
Since we arrived by train and had our prams with us, we decided to start our ascent by foot from the market. If you’re 
walking with strollers, we recommend taking Carrer del Calvari to avoid any stairs. Our stroll through the picturesque 
Barri del Pou area wasn’t too difficult, with only a few steps here and there. It was absolutely worth it though—the 
charming white stairways, stone walls, and lush plants growing along the narrow, clean streets made the walk feel magical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_105123.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_114809.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/10/Gandia_Cullera/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/10/Gandia_Cullera/</guid>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Valencia</category>
        
        <category>Gandia</category>
        
        <category>Cullera</category>
        
        <category>castle</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Odkrywanie tajemnic holenderskich tulipanów</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;W Holandii kwiecień jest najlepszym miesiącem na podziwianie pięknych tulipanów. Zaplanowaliśmy wycieczkę do Keukenhof, 
przejażdżkę rowerową przez pola tulipanów oraz obchody Dnia Króla, a wszystko to podczas długiego weekendu. W dalszej części 
tekstu, dowiesz się kilku ciekawych szczegółów o tych słynnych kwiatach!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tulipany pochodzą z północnych regionów Himalajów, z Azji Centralnej, i były po raz pierwszy uprawiane w starożytnej Persji 
już w X wieku jako symbol wdzięku i piękna. Stamtąd tulipany rozprzestrzeniły się na zachód, docierając w końcu do Stambułu, 
co otworzyło im drzwi do Europy. W drugiej połowie XVI wieku podróżnicy przywieźli cebulki i kwiaty do różnych krajów, znajdując 
szczególnie entuzjastyczną publiczność w Holandii. To zapoczątkowało holenderską uprawę tulipanów, a ważne odmiany pojawiły 
się zaledwie kilka dekad później, na zawsze kształtując historię tego pięknego kwiatu. Nasz plan podróży obejmował wizytę na 
farmie tulipanów, przejażdżkę rowerową wzdłuż pól tulipanowych oraz zwiedzanie słynnych ogrodów Keukenhof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_170101.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naszą przygodę rozpoczęliśmy od przejażdżki rowerowej przez pola tulipanów, tworząc pętlę z Leiden do Sassenheim, Hillegom, 
Lisse, Voorhout i z powrotem do Leiden, pokonując prawie 50 km pierwszego dnia (szczegółowa mapa trasy na samym końcu postu). 
Wyposażeni w uchwyty na telefon na naszych rowerach i dobrze oznakowaną trasę na Google Maps, bez trudu odnajdywaliśmy się
w terenie i nasza przejażdżka była czystą przyjemnością (pomijając przelotne opady deszczu). Holenderskie ścieżki rowerowe są 
niesamowicie intuicyjne i świetnie oznaczone. Nasza wycieczka zbiegła się z Dniem Króla, narodowym świętem przypadającym na 26 kwietnia, 
kiedy każde małe miasto ożywa dzięki ulicznym imprezom, a ludzie ubrani w jaskrawe odcienie koloru pomarańczowego, świętują urodziny króla. 
Ku naszemu wielkiemu zaskoczeniu, większość pól tulipanowych została już ścięta, co – jak później się dowiedzieliśmy – miało miejsce 
w tym roku dwa tygodnie wcześniej niż zazwyczaj. Pomimo to, bardzo podobała nam się nasza wycieczka, to mogliśmy sobie tylko wyobrazić,
jak cudownie muszą wyglądać te pola w pełnym rozkwicie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_160322.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC07901.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_175205.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_162953.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_165150.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W okolicy tej znajduje się sporo farm, na których można obejrzeć male pola pokazowe wielu gatunków tulipanów,&lt;br /&gt;
z konkretnymi nazwami i numerami, których cebulki można potem zamówić online. Jest to świetna okazja, aby zobaczyć różne 
odmiany i wybrać te, które najlepiej będą pasować do Naszego ogrodu!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_175129.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_170210.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC07868.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_150613.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farma Tulipanów “De Tulperij” to uroczy, rodzinny biznes, który rozpoczął działalność w 1927 roku. Syn właściciela postanowił 
przejąć farmę i wkrótce rozpocznie nią zarządzać jako już czwarte pokolenie tej rodziny. Farma znajduje się w pobliżu ogrodów 
Keukenhof i jest otwarta w tym samym czasie, co ogrody. Goście, którzy zapisali się na specjalne zwiedzanie farmy, są 
osobiście witani przez właściciela i jego żonę.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_150031.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134648.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_142701.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ponieważ dołączyliśmy do takiej wycieczki z przewodnikiem, otrzymaliśmy kilka bezcennych wskazówek o tym, jak skuteczniej 
uprawiać tulipany w naszych własnych ogrodach. Jedną z kluczowych decyzji jest sadzenie tulipanów w piaszczystej glebie z 
wysokim poziomem wód gruntowych. Na ten farmie woda gruntowa znajduje się zaledwie 65 cm poniżej powierzchni, co eliminuje 
potrzebę dodatkowego nawadniania, a potencjalny nadmiar wody jest kierowany do systemów odprowadzających wodę. Dowiedzieliśmy się 
również, jak ważne jest rotowanie cebulek tulipanów w różnych miejscach ogrodu każdego roku, aby zapobiec rozwojowi 
chorób bakteryjnych i wirusowych wokół cebulek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otrzymaliśmy również szczegółowe wyjaśnienie procesu uprawy tulipanów krok po kroku. “De Tulperij” to farma zajmująca się 
uprawą cebulek, w przeciwieństwie do farm zajmujących się uprawą kwiatów, co oznacza, że nie uprawiają tulipanów przez 
cały rok. Natomiast inne farmy uprawiają tulipany nieprzerwanie, zimą jedynie w szklarniach. Co ciekawe, 80% tulipanów produkowanych w 
Holandii pozostaje w kraju, a jedynie 20% jest eksportowanych.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W “De Tulperij” cała praca rozpoczyna się między październikiem a grudniem, kiedy cebulki tulipanów są sadzone i ochraniane 
sianem przed mrozem. Potrzebują one niższych temperatur przez kilka miesięcy, aby zakwitnąć na wiosnę, najlepiej około 9°C. 
Gdy nadchodzi wiosna i tulipany zaczynają kwitnąć, hodowcy starannie sprawdzają, czy wirusy nie zaatakowały ich upraw, 
usuwając wszelkie pojedyńcze rośliny, które odstają swoim wyglądem od pozostałych, czy to innym ubarwieniem płatków lub brakiem
części liści.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dowiedzieliśmy się, że moment ścinania kwiatów, który zazwyczaj ma miejsce w pierwszej połowie maja, w tym roku 
miał miejsce 2 tygodnie wcześniej. Ścinanie kwiatów pomaga zmniejszyć aktywność owadów wokół tulipanów i zapewnia, że energia 
z rośliny jest kierowana na rozwój cebulek, a nie na utrzymanie kwiatów i dalszą produkcję nasion. Po ścięciu kwiatów cebulki pozostają w ziemi przez kolejne 
6-8 tygodni, aż liście zżółkną. Następnie cebulki są zbierane, ręcznie czyszczone (proces zwany “obieraniem”), suszone i 
przechowywane w ciemnym, wentylowanym miejscu do następnego sezonu kiedy ich sadzenie zacznie się od nowa. Z jednej cebulki 
matecznej można spodziewać się do pięciu małych cebulek potomnych.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niewielka część cebulek jest nadal sprzedawana na aukcjach. Duże cebulki przeznaczone na rynki międzynarodowe są dokładnie myte, 
aby wyeliminować wszelkie bakterie lub grzyby. Mniejsze cebulki są przechowywane i ponownie sadzone jesienią. Cebulki 
potomne potrzebują dwóch do trzech lat, aby urosnąć na tyle, by można je było przeznaczyć na sprzedaż.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NFarma De Tulperij od 2001 roku posiada nowy kolor tulipanów, pomarańczowy, który jest naprawdę rzadki i kosztuje o 30% 
więcej niż czerwone tulipany. Najbardziej powszechnymi kolorami są czerwone, żółte i fioletowe tulipany a wprowadzenie 
nowej odmiany na rynek zajmuje średnio 20 lat. Te nowe odmiany mogą powstawać przypadkowo poprzez losowe mutacje, jak 
miało to miejsce w przypadku pomarańczowego tulipana na tej farmie, lub poprzez celowe krzyżowanie. Hodowcy starannie 
izolują cebulki o niezwykłych kolorach, a kiedy w następnym roku zakwitną one w takim samym kolorze, to wiedzą, że jest 
to stała mutacja i wtedy mogą zacząć powiększać liczbę cebulek, aby w końcu móc zacząć je sprzedawać co jest wieloletnim procesem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134800.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134734.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Każda nowa odmiana tulipanów otrzymuje certyfikat od Banku Genów, świadczący o jej wyjątkowości i tożsamości. Od samego 
początku tulipany były nazywane imionami znanych osobistości lub hodowców. Najbardziej znany z tulipanów to “Semper Augustus”, 
nazwany na cześć cesarza rzymskiego Augusta w XVI wieku.
Jedną z ciekawostek, której nauczyliśmy się od rolnika z De Tulperij, był unikalny proces uprawy hiacyntów. W przeciwieństwie 
do tulipanów przy ich uprawie używa się specjalnej techniki, w której rolnicy ręcznie uszkadzają dolną część cebulek. Ten 
zaskakujący etap powoduje szybkie ich ponowne namnażanie się, produkcję 20-30 nowych cebulek w zaledwie 2-3 miesiące. 
Następnie każda nowa cebulka jest starannie oddzielana ręcznie i musi rosnąć przez trzy lata, zanim będzie wystarczająco 
duża, by wydać kwiaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ostatni nas dzień poświęciliśmy wizycie w słynnym Keukenhof, który został założony w 1949 roku (dokładnie 75 lat temu!). Na 
zdjęciu poniżej widać dawne wejście do parku, które nadal jest jedną z jego cech charakterystycznych. Ogród 
początkowo został otwarty, aby pokazać najlepsze cebulki kwiatów, jakie holenderski przemysł kwiatowy miał do zaoferowania
w tamtych czasach, i od tego momentu stał się jednym z największych i najbardziej znanych ogrodów kwiatowych na świecie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_101110.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_101832.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_102448.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090529.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jedną z głównych atrakcyjnych Keukenhof jest jego uroczy wiatrak, pierwotnie wyprodukowany w Groningen w 1892 
roku i ofiarowany przez firmę żeglugową. Z platformy na szczycie wiatraka zazwyczaj można podziwiać zapierające dech w 
piersiach widok na kolorowe póla tulipanów, gdy są one w pełnym rozkwicie. Jednak podczas naszej wizyty otaczające pola 
pozbawione już były kwiatów.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 milionów cebulkowych roślin wiosennych, tworzy żywy katalog aż 100 prezentujących swoje odmiany hodowców oraz firm na ponad 
20 wystawach kwiatowych na terenie tego ogrodu. Na początku sezonu można podziwiać w pełnym rozkwicie krokusy, żonkile, 
hiacynty oraz wczesne tulipany. W miarę postępu sezonu ogród przekształca się, pojawiają się coraz większe tulipany i 
inne kwiaty. Osoby sadzące i projektujące ten ogród dbają o to, aby każdego tygodnia kwitły inne rośliny, co daje nam gwarancję, 
że będzie tam zawsze pięknie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keukenhof to obowiązkowe miejsce dla każdego miłośnika kwiatów, zapewniające spektakularne widowisko piękna 
natury. Warto jednak zauważyć, że park może być dość zatłoczony, nawet w poniedziałkowe poranki. Choć doświadczenie jest 
niewątpliwie magiczne, nie jest to coś, co chciałbym powtarzać co roku ze względu na ogromną liczbę odwiedzających. Niemniej 
jednak Keukenhof pozostaje rajem dla miłośników kwiatów, który należy zobaczyć przynajmniej raz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090751.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08099.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08066.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08102.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.easyfiets.nl/en/&quot;&gt;Easy Fiets in Leiden&lt;/a&gt; Personel był bardzo miły, a nawet mogliśmy oddać rowery po godzinach otwarcia, 
jednak rowery były dość małe, a jazda nimi przez 50 km nie była łatwa.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/Screenshot 2024-05-02 223301.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tulipstore.eu/nl/service/tulip-store-showtuin/&quot;&gt;Tulip Store Showgarden&lt;/a&gt; 
To ogród pokazowy tulipanów z dużymi polami tulipanów, do które można wejść bez opłaty. Inne miejsce z pięknymi 
polami znajdowało się obok firmy Vernooij VOF, nie będącej farmą tulipanów, ale mającą piękne pola które były także łatwo dostępne.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Podczas naszej wycieczki rowerowej, podążaliśmy głównie trasą rowerową wyznaczoną na stronie &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/cxvXKUircv5tzJJw6?g_st=aw&quot;&gt;Flowermap.nl&lt;/a&gt;.
Można ją otworzyć i zostanie się natychmiast przekierowany do Google Maps, co sprawia, że korzystanie z tej mapy jest bardzo 
łatwe. Następnie wystarczy śledzić znaczniki na mapie. Pominęliśmy jedną pętlę, która prowadzi nad morze, ponieważ 
pogoda była niestabilna, a my nadal musieliśmy wrócić do Leiden. Nasze koleżanki pokonały ten fragment i potwierdziły, 
że krajobraz zmienia się drastycznie, a wydmy prezentują się zachwycająco nawet przy wietrznej i burzowej pogodzie.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tulip Farm &lt;a href=&quot;https://detulperij.nl/&quot;&gt;De Tulperij&lt;/a&gt; w Voorhout - można dołączyć do wycieczki po polach tulipanów
(3 wycieczki każdego dnia, po angielsku i niderlandzku). Jest także szklarnia kwiatowa z kawą, herbatą i holenderskim 
goframi, pięknie udekorowana. Można również kupić wiele pamiątek związanych z tulipanami oraz słynną porcelaną z Delft. Podczas naszej 
wizyty nie było możliwe zakupienie żadnych cebulek, ale można je wybrać online i zostaną wysłane później pod wskazany adres. 
Jeśli kiedykolwiek znajdziesz 
się w pobliżu Ogrodów Keukenhof, wizyta w De Tulperij to konieczność dla każdego miłośnika kwiatów! Wizyta trwała 
prawie godzinę i obejmowała 20-minutowy film oraz czas na zdjęcia na polach, które nie są dostępne dla każdego 
odwiedzającego. Na tej farmie można również zobaczyć dalie – od początku sierpnia do początku października, kiedy farma 
ponownie jest otwarta dla zwiedzających. Należy jednak zauważyć, że choć każdy może zobaczyć ogród pokazowy tulipanów, 
aby robić zdjęcia na polach, należy zarezerwować wizytę z przewodnikiem.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134831.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://keukenhof.nl/nl/&quot;&gt;Keukenhof&lt;/a&gt; To prawdopodobnie najczęściej odwiedzane miejsce w Holandii podczas tych kilku tygodni, gdy jest 
otwarte. Liczba dużych autokarów turystycznych na parkingach, które mijaliśmy w sobotę podczas jazdy na rowerze, była 
oszałamiająca, nie wspominając już o liczbie samochodów zaparkowanych na różnych parkingach wokół słynnych ogrodów. 
Byliśmy zadowoleni, że zarezerwowaliśmy bilety na poniedziałkowe przedpołudnie o 8:30 rano. Jedynym problemem, z którym 
się zetknęliśmy, to znalezienie właściwego parkingu. Wszędzie było tak pusto rano, że nie byliśmy pewni, gdzie się udać. Skończyło się na tym, 
że pojechaliśmy na dwa różne parkingi, zanim ktoś w końcu nas skierował do właściwego, tracąc prawie 20 minut. Wydaje się, 
że wyznaczony parking zmienia się w ciągu dnia, więc jeśli przyjeżdża się z samego rana, to zdecydowanie trzeba udać się na główny parking 
(współrzędne: 52.268923, 4.551555). To ten sam parking, gdzie można wynająć rowery.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do godziny 11:00 rano liczba odwiedzających w parku była rozsądna. Po tej godzinie zaczęło się robić naprawdę tłoczno. 
Zauważyliśmy coraz więcej dużych grup, co utrudniało poruszanie się po niektórych obszarach. Ponieważ odwiedzaliśmy 
park po ścięciu pól tulipanów, nie warto było spieszyć się do wiatraka, ponieważ widok nie był już tak spektakularny bez kolorowych 
pól otaczających to miejsce. Zamiast tego polecamy udać się do Ogrodu Historycznego, który jest popularnym miejscem do robienia zdjęć selfie, 
jak później zauważyliśmy. Po zwiedzeniu parku udało nam się jeszcze przejść do centrum miasta Lisse na lunch 
(mniej niż 20 minut pieszo) i potem wróciliśmy na parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090553.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2024/05/Lisse-Tulipany/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2024/05/Lisse-Tulipany/</guid>
        
        <category>Holandia</category>
        
        <category>Keukenhof</category>
        
        <category>rower</category>
        
        <category>tulipany</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discovering the secrets of tulips in the Netherlands</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, April is the best month to view Holland’s beautiful tulips. We packed a trip to Keukenhof, cycling 
through tulip fields, and King’s Day celebrations into a single long weekend. Read on to discover what we learned about 
these iconic flowers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tulips originated north of the Himalayas, in Central Asia, and were first cultivated in ancient Persia as early as the 
10th century as a symbol of grace and beauty. From there, tulips spread westward, eventually reaching Istanbul, which 
opened the door to Europe. By the second half of the 16th century, travellers had brought bulbs and flowers to various 
countries, finding a particularly enthusiastic audience in the Netherlands. This marked the beginning of Dutch tulip 
cultivation, with important varieties emerging just a few decades later, forever shaping the history of this beautiful bloom. 
We started our weekend trip with the main goal of understanding tulip cultivation better and admiring the stunning 
variations growing in the fields around Lisse. Our travel schedule included visiting a tulip farm, cycling along tulip 
fields, and exploring the famed Keukenhof gardens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_170101.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started our adventure by cycling through the tulip fields, creating a loop from Leiden to Sassenheim, Hillegom, Lisse, 
Voorhout, and back to Leiden, covering nearly 50 km on the first day (detailed map in practical info section). Equipped 
with phone holders on our bikes and a 
well-marked route on Google Maps, navigation was a breeze. Dutch cycling paths are incredibly intuitive, and we didn’t 
get lost once. Coinciding with our trip was King’s Day, a national celebration on April 26th, where every small city 
burst into street parties with people dressed in vibrant orange, celebrating the King’s birthday. To our surprise, most 
of the tulip fields had already been cut, which we later learned happened two weeks earlier than usual this year. Despite 
this, we thoroughly enjoyed our tour and couldn’t help but imagine the sheer beauty of the fields in full bloom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_160322.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC07901.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_175205.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_162953.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_165150.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We passed few tulip farms where we could see small show gardens with many types of tulips with specific names 
and numbers to make it very easy to order them online. A great chance to see different types and choose the one that 
will fit your garden best!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_175129.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_170210.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC07868.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_150613.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tulip Farm De Tulperij is a charming family-run business that started in 1927. The son of the owner decided to take over 
the farm and will start the 4th generation in the near future. Visitors are welcomed personally by the owners, the farmer, 
and his wife. It’s located near Keukenhof Gardens and is open during the same time as the gardens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_150031.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134648.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_142701.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we joined a guided tour, the owner generously shared invaluable tips on how to grow tulips more effectively in our 
gardens. One key takeaway was to plant tulips in sandy soil with a high level of groundwater. On their farm, the groundwater 
sits just 65 cm below the surface, eliminating the need for additional watering as any excess is channelled into irrigation 
systems. We also learned the importance of rotating tulip bulbs to different spots each year to prevent bacterial and 
viral diseases that can develop around the bulbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also received a step-by-step explanation of the tulip cultivation process. De Tulperij is a bulb grower’s farm, unlike 
flower growers’ farms, meaning they don’t grow tulips year-round. In contrast, other farms cultivate tulips continuously 
in greenhouses. Remarkably, 80% of tulips produced in the Netherlands remain in the country, with only 20% being exported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tulip cycle at De Tulperij begins between October and December, when bulbs are planted and protected with hay. They 
require lower temperatures for a few months to bloom in spring, ideally around 9°C. As spring arrives and tulips start to 
emerge, the grower meticulously checks for viruses, removing any plants that look different, such as those lacking leaves 
or displaying a mosaic pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned that the timing of flower cutting, which typically occurs during the first two weeks of May, happened 2 weeks 
earlier this year. Cutting the flowers helps reduce insect activity around the tulips and ensures that energy is directed 
toward bulb development rather than seed production. After cutting, the bulbs remain in the ground for another 6-8 weeks 
until the leaves turn yellow. Then, the bulbs are harvested, cleaned by hand (process is called “peeling”), dried, and 
stored in a dark, ventilated place until the next planting season. Up to five small bulbs can be expected to grow out 
of the mother bulb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small part of the bulbs is still sold at auctions. Large bulbs destined for international markets are washed to eliminate 
any bacteria or fungi. The smaller bulbs are stored and replanted in the autumn, with bulblets taking two to three years 
to grow large enough to sell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De Tulperij farm has a new tulip color from 2001, orange, which is really rare and costs 30% more than red tulips. While 
red, yellow, and purple tulips are most prevalent, it takes, on average, 20 years to introduce a new variety to the market. 
These new varieties can emerge by chance through random mutations, as was the case with the orange tulip, or through 
intentional crossbreeding.
The orange tulip at De Tulperij was a lucky find, emerging from a random mutation. The growers carefully isolated the bulb, 
and when it bloomed the same vibrant color the following year, they knew they had something special. This permanent mutation 
marked the start of their efforts to cultivate and increase the number of these unique orange bulbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134800.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134734.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right next door to De Tulperij, there’s a neighbor with an impressive collection of 7,000 different tulip types, including 
virus-resistant varieties. Each new tulip variety receives a certificate from the Gene Bank, a testament to its uniqueness 
and identity.  From the beginning, tulips were named after famous personalities or breeders. The most famous one is 
“Semper Augustus,” named after Roman Emperor Augustus in the 16th. century.
One fun fact we learned from the farmer at De Tulperij was about the unique process of growing hyacinths. Unlike tulips, 
the cultivation of hyacinths involves a deliberate technique where farmers manually damage the bottom of the bulbs. This 
surprising method causes the bulbs to multiply rapidly, producing 20-30 new bulbs within just 2-3 months. Afterward, each 
new bulb is carefully separated by hand and then needs to grow for three years before it’s large enough to produce flower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last day was dedicated to visit famous Keukenhof that wes established in 1949 (exactly 75 years ago!). On the photo below you can see the former 
entrance to the park that is still one of the features of the park. The garden was initially opened to showcase the best 
flower bulbs the Dutch floricultural industry has to offer, and it has since become one of the largest and most well-known 
flower gardens in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_101110.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_101832.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_102448.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090529.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights of Keukenhof is its charming windmill, originally produced in Groningen in 1892 and donated by a 
cruise company. From the platform at the top of the windmill, you can usually admire breathtaking views of the colorful 
tulip fields at the peak of the season. However, during our visit, the surrounding fields had already been cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keukenhof’s main attraction is its focus on the 7 million spring-flowering bulbs, showcasing a living catalog for the 
100 participating companies. Over 500 flower growers present an impressive variety of cut flowers and pot plants at more 
than 20 flower shows. Early in the season, you can enjoy crocuses, daffodils, hyacinths, and early tulips in full bloom. 
As the season progresses, the garden transforms with larger tulips and other flowers making their appearance. Keukenhof 
is a must-visit destination for any flower enthusiast, providing a spectacular display of nature’s beauty. However, it’s 
worth noting that the park can get quite crowded, even on a Monday morning. While the experience is undoubtedly magical, 
it’s not something I would repeat annually due to the sheer volume of visitors. Nonetheless, Keukenhof remains a floral 
paradise that should be experienced at least once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090751.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08099.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08066.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08102.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.easyfiets.nl/en/&quot;&gt;Easy Fiets in Leiden&lt;/a&gt; Very friendly stuff, and we could give them back even after 
opening hours, but the bikes were quite small and cycling 50 km with these, was not idle. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/Screenshot 2024-05-02 223301.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tulipstore.eu/nl/service/tulip-store-showtuin/&quot;&gt;Tulip Store Showgarden&lt;/a&gt; is a tulip show garden with big fields with tulips that you can enter without 
a fee. Another spot with beautiful fields was next to Vernooij VOF, not a tulip farm but nice fields with easy access.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During our bike ride, we mostly followed the route outlined on &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/cxvXKUircv5tzJJw6?g_st=aw&quot;&gt;Flowermap.nl&lt;/a&gt; 
You can open it, and it will redirect you immediately to Google Maps, making it very easy to use. Then you can just follow 
the marks on the map. We skipped one loop that goes to the sea because the weather was unstable, and we still had to 
get back to Leiden. Our colleagues did this part, and they confirmed that the landscape changes dramatically, with 
the dunes looking stunning even in windy and stormy weather.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tulip Farm &lt;a href=&quot;https://detulperij.nl/&quot;&gt;De Tulperij&lt;/a&gt; in Voorhout - you can get a guided tour through the tulip fields (3 tours every day, English 
and Dutch). There is also flower greenhouse with a coffee, tea and a Dutch waffle, beautifully decorated. You can also 
buy many tulip and Delftware related souvenirs. During our visit, it was not possible to buy any bulbs but these can be
purchased online and shipped later to your home address. It’s incredible to see the dedication and time that goes into 
growing bulbs. If you ever find yourself near Keukenhof Gardens, a trip to De Tulperij is a must for any flower lover! 
The visit lasted almost one hour and included a 20-minute movie and free time for pictures in the fields that are normally 
not open to every visitor. On this farm, you can also see dahlias – beginning of August to beginning of October when farm is 
open for visitors again. Note that while everyone can see the tulip show garden, to take photos on the fields, you 
need to book guided tour.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134831.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://keukenhof.nl/nl/&quot;&gt;Keukenhof&lt;/a&gt; is probably the most visited place in the Netherlands during the few 
weeks it’s open. The number of large tourist buses in the parking lots we passed on Saturday while cycling was astounding, 
not to mention the number of cars parked in various lots around the famous gardens. We were glad to have booked our ticket 
for Monday morning at 8:30 am. The only issue we encountered was that the parking lots were so empty in the morning that 
we weren’t sure where to go. We ended up driving to two different lots before someone finally directed us to the correct 
one, wasting almost 20 minutes. It seems the designated parking lot changes during the day, so if you arrive in the morning, 
definitely head to the main parking lot (coordinates: 52.268923, 4.551555). It’s also the same lot where you can rent a bike.
We approached Keukenhof from another direction, so look for temporary signs on the roundabout that indicate where to turn. 
The sign simply said “Keukenhof,” which was confusing. It would be more helpful if it included the word “open” and a 
parking pictogram as well.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until 11:00 am, the number of visitors in the park was reasonable. After that time, it started to get really crowded. 
We noticed more and more large groups, making it difficult to navigate some areas. Because we visited after the tulip 
fields had already been cut, it wasn’t worth rushing to the windmill first since the view wasn’t spectacular without 
the colorful fields. Instead, we recommend heading to the Historical Garden, which is great for selfies and, as we noticed 
later, a popular spot in the park. After visiting the park, we had a walk to city center of Lisse for a lunch
(less than 20min walk) and then came back to the car parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090553.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/05/Lisse-Netherlands/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/05/Lisse-Netherlands/</guid>
        
        <category>Netherlands</category>
        
        <category>Keukenhof</category>
        
        <category>cycling</category>
        
        <category>tulips</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weekend w Marsyli, najstarszym mieście Francji.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mały park z pozostałościami archeologicznymi obok Muzeum Historii Marsylii to miejsce, gdzie rozpoczęła się historia tego miasta. 
To właśnie tutaj, w tym konkretnym miejscu, pierwsi greccy osadnicy z Focji tchnęli życie w to miasto około 600 roku p.n.e., 
zakładając podwaliny pod to, co miało stać się tętniącym życiem portem Marsylii. Nadal można tam zobaczyć łódź w rzeczywistym 
rozmiarze, używaną przez Greków do żeglugi po wzburzonym Morzu Śródziemnym, aby dotrzeć do tej naturalnie spokojnej zatoki, 
doskonale chroniącej przed wiatrem i oferującej schronienie przybyszom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_112904.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niedaleko stąd, nowoczesny port tętni życiem. Widoczny z punktu widokowego “Mirador de Saint-Jean”, znajdującego się blisko 
fortyfikacji miasta, która prowadzi statki do wejścia do portu. Na końcu portu, nabrzeże Quai des Belges ożywa każdego poranka, 
gdy rybacy oferują tu swoje najświeższe połowy. W tym miejscu znajduje się również tablica upamiętniająca pierwszych przybyszów z Grecji.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103113.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103082.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103080.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103077.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dzielnica „Le Panier” znajdowała się w bezpośrednim sąsiedztwie naszego apartamentu, więc kilkakrotnie przechodziliśmy 
obok tego miejsca i zawsze gubiliśmy się w wąskich uliczkach, odkrywając nowe graffiti, kolorowe alejki i urocze butiki z 
mydłem marsylskim. W rzeczywistości oryginalne mydło marsylskie wygląda dość niepozornie, jest to po prostu duża kostka (300g) 
zielonkawego mydła o subtelnej woni. Jednakże tego właśnie potrzebuje twoja skóra, 72% oliwy z oliwek z pewnością 
odpowiednio ją nawilży oraz ukoi. Nie daj się zwieść wszystkim pięknym mydłom pełnym 
barwników, perfum czy syntetycznych dodatków. Oprócz uroczych małych sklepów, można w tej dzielnicy znaleźć rowniez małe galerie i 
interesujące kawiarnie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103093.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_125351.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103108.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_172204.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Przestrzeń przed Centrum Charytatywnym, opustoszała w listopadowym chłodzie, według naszego przewodnika, w miesiącach 
szczytu sezonu byłaby trudna do przejścia, gdy wszystkie restauracje i kawiarnie wystawiają tutaj swoje stoliki. Pod 
koniec jesieni, podobnie jak reszta dzielnicy La Panier, ten obszar pustoszeje, sklepy zamykają się a okolica ucicha, 
oczekując na wiosne po ktorej następi kilka pracowitych miesięcy. Jeszcze kilka lat temu można było w tej dzielnicy mieszkać, 
podpisując długoterminową umowę najmu, ale teraz większość domów jest oferowana tylko na Airbnb. Wynajem krótkoterminowy, nawet 
tylko pzrez kilka miesięcy, okazuje się znacznie bardziej opłacalny. Zauważyliśmy często na murach budynkow napis 
“Airbnb dehors”, co oznacza “precz z Airbnb”. Jasno podkreśla to, że lokalni mieszkańcy nie są zadowoleni ze zmian zachodzących 
w tej dzielnicy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103136.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103135.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ta wspaniała bazylika, Katedra La Major, została zbudowana w XIX wieku blisko fundamentów oryginalnego portu Marsylii. 
Kolory ścian są oszałamiające, szczególnie gdy podkreślone światłem zachodzącego słońca, które akcentuje różne kamienie 
żyte podczas budowy, która trwała ponad 40 lat. Nasz apartament znajdował się zaledwie kilkaset metrów od tej bazyliki, 
więc łatwo było nam do niej trafić, ponieważ 60-metrowa wieża bazyliki jest widoczna z wielu miejsc miasta. Okolica ta 
jest świetnym miejscem na wieczorny spacer podczas zachodu słońca, oferując piękne widoki na port, MUCEM i Cosquer Méditerranée 
tuż obok. Podłoga bazyliki zasługuje również na uwagę, gdyż ozdobiona jest wspaniałymi mozaikami.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_170032.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103065.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_130617.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gorąco polecamy wizytę na dachu Muzeum Cywilizacji Europy i Śródziemnomorza (MUCEM), do którego można dotrzeć przechodząc 
przez kładkę z Fortu św. Jana lub przez samo muzeum. Muzeum to ma fascynującą architekturę, przypomina z daleka ogromną 
gąbkę lub koralowce głębinowe. Będąc na dachu, który oferuje wolny dostęp, możesz rozkoszować się rozległymi widokami na 
miasto oraz port przez azurowe, zewnętrzne ściany budynku. To idealne miejsce na przerwę, aby podziwiać widoki! Kontrast 
między starożytnymi budowlami fortu a nowoczesnym muzeum jest widoczny, ale oba obiekty pięknie się uzupełniają. Kontynuując, 
eksplorowaliśmy wąskie ścieżki i ogrody na fortyfikacji miasta, odnajdując spokój i ciepło słońca w ustronnych zakątkach, 
gdzie nie docierał chłodny wiatr. Wiele punktów widokowych pozwoliło nam podziwiać zarówno Bazylikę Notre-Dame de la Garde, 
jak i Katedrę La Major. Obszar ten kryje wiele niespodzianek, znaleźliśmy tutaj urokliwy plac z fontanną, mural kobiety 
oraz mnóstwo roślin, które czynią to miejsce naprawdę wyjątkowym. Jest to miejsce warte odwiedzenia, jeśli szukasz ucieczki od 
zgiełku miasta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103117.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141649.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_135459.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103111.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bazylika Notre-Dame de la Garde, oferująca panoramiczny, 360-stopniowy widok na miasto, jest niewątpliwie miejscem, które 
koniecznie trzeba odwiedzić. Mimo że nie spędziliśmy wiele czasu wewnątrz kościoła, nie mogliśmy nie zauważyć fascynujących 
dekoracji, w tym statków zawieszonych na suficie, które podkreślają głębokie związki miasta z morzem. Koniecznie spójrz w 
górę – sufit zapiera dech w piersiach! Z zewnętrznego obszaru możesz podziwiać rozległą panoramę Marsylii, w tym nowy port 
dla statków wycieczkowych, położony w bardziej przemysłowej części miasta, która znajduje się kilka kilometrów od starego 
historycznego centrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141834.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_162108.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_161130.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103129.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Z tyłu kościoła roztacza się widok na Endoume, najbardziej prestiżową dzielnicę miasta, gdzie domy są ciasno zgrupowane, 
otoczone z jednej strony morzem a z drugiej górami. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103128.jpg&quot; /&gt;
Stadion Orange Velodrome i duże kompleksy mieszkalne zdecydowanie wyróżniały się wśród budynków po tej stronie miasta, 
z zapierającym dech w piersiach Parkiem Narodowym Calanques w tle, który był naszym celem na następny dzień.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103130.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kochamy naturę i wędrówki, więc zawsze staramy się łączyć krótkie wycieczki miejskie z przynajmniej jednym dniem spędzonym 
na łonie natury. Park Narodowy Calanques, położony między Marsylią a Cassis, był oczywistym wyborem po przejrzeniu mapy 
okolic miasta. Główne aktywności dostępne w tym parku narodowym to piesze wędrówki, wspinaczka skalna, pływanie i kajakarstwo. 
Ostre, białe klify i czysta woda u ich podnóża tworzą wspaniały widok, który można podziwiać wędrując szlakiem. “Calanque” 
to unikalny typ formacji geologicznej z wapienia znajdującej się wzdłuż wybrzeża Morza Śródziemnego. Pierwsze zdjęcie 
poniżej pokazuje główny punkt widokowy, Sugiton, który jest najbardziej dostępnym miejscem, znajdującym się około 2,5 km 
od przystanku autobusowego. Stamtąd można również zejść na plażę (dodatkowy 1 km) lub przedłużyć spacer o kilka-kilkanascie 
kilometrów w stronę Cassis, podążając głównym szlakiem GR. To była nasza decyzja i wcale tego nie żałowaliśmy! Ścieżka 
była bardzo kamienista i wymagająca, z wieloma stromymi i wąskimi odcinkami, ale fantastyczne widoki w pełni wynagrodziły 
wysiłek. Niestety, musieliśmy wrócić tą samą drogą, ponieważ nie byliśmy pewni, dokąd prowadzą inne ścieżki; Google Maps 
tym razem nie było zbyt pomocne, a poleganie wyłącznie na oznaczeniach na skałach nie wystarczało do nawigacji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113218.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113224.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113148.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113215.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_152147.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113195.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podczas naszego drugiego wieczoru odwiedziliśmy muzeum repliki Jaskini Cosquer (Villa Méditerranée), znajdujące się zaledwie 
kilkaset metrów od naszego apartamentu. W 1985 roku jaskinię odkrył Henri Cosquer, entuzjasta nurkowania, który znalazł jej
wejście prowadzące do ogromnej zatopionej galerii. Ten niemal 175-metrowy korytarz odsłonił prawdziwy skarb datowany na 
30 000 lat, zawierający ponad 480 dzieł, w tym malowidła i grawery przedstawiające pingwiny, jelenie, kozice, bizonów, 
jak również odciski dłoni i ślady ogniska. W tamtym czasie poziom morza był około 120 metrów niższy niż dzisiaj, a wody 
znajdowały się kilka kilometrów dalej. Jednak z powodu podnoszenia się poziomu morza to prehistoryczne miejsce jest zagrożone 
zatopieniem, niektóre malowidła są już częściowo poniżej poziomu wody. Pilne zatem stało się zachowanie oraz udostępnienie 
tego niesłychanego odkrycia światu. Obecnie jaskinia nie jest dostępna dla publiczności, a jej wejście zostało zamknięte 
dla jej ochrony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wynajęliśmy apartament na Airbnb w dzielnicy La Joliette, zaledwie kilka budynków od Katedry Marsylskiej, znajdujący 
się na 6. piętrze bez windy. Zauwazylismy wiele podobnych ofert wynajmu. To może nie być najlepsze rozwiązanie dla osób z dużą 
ilością bagażu lub dla rodzin z dziećmi. Kiedy ruch morski przekroczył pojemność Starego Portu, założono nowy, a nasz 
apartament znajdował się tuż przy wejściu do tego ogromnego portu. Dworzec kolejowy ‘Saint-Charles’ jest w odległości 
15-20 minut spacerem, więc nawet nie rozważaliśmy korzystania z transportu publicznego.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wycieczka z przewodnikiem &lt;a href=&quot;https://marseillefreewalkingtour.com/&quot;&gt;Marseille Free Walking Tour&lt;/a&gt; trwala ok 2.5 godziny i bardzo polecamy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delicious patisserie La Pâtisserie des Marseillais &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lapatisseriedesmarseillais.fr/&quot;&gt;Pascal Guglielmi&lt;/a&gt; zdecydowanie warta odwiedzenia!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Autobus numer 60, od przystanku Capitainerie do Bazyliki Notre-Dame de la Garde, oferuje prawie 20-minutową jazdę. 
Wstęp do kościoła jest bezpłatny. Spędziliśmy tylko około 15 minut w okolicy kościoła z powodu silnego, zimnego wiatru, 
a następnie wróciliśmy tym samym biletem, który był ważny przez 1 godzinę. Gdy ponownie wsiedliśmy do autobusu, 
zeskanowaliśmy nasz bilet, ale nie został on obciążony, i mogliśmy z niego skorzystać następnego dnia w metrze. Każdy 
zakupiony przez nas bilet był ważny na 2 przejazdy, ale maszyna oferuje wiele opcji przy wyborze liczby przejazdów. 
Dla osób z dziećmi świetną opcją jest skorzystanie z małego pociągu ze Starego Portu (znajdującego się naprzeciwko 
ratusza w Marsylii), który podjeżdża pod samą bazylikę!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Korzystając z linii metra 2 z Joliette do Castellane, a następnie z autobusu B1, po 30-40 minut jazdy w kierunku 
Campus de Luminy, dotarliśmy do przystanku Luminy – PN des Calanques. Nasza wędrówka po Parku Narodowym Calanques, 
około 16 km, trwała 5-6 godzin z przerwami. Na poniższej mapie, która pokazuje naszą trasę, widoczna jest małą odnogą 
wskazującą punkt widokowy Belvédère de Sugiton, popularne miejsce wśród wielu odwiedzających. Jest łatwo dostępny, 
gdyż widzieliśmy ludzi z psami i niemowlakami w wózkach, jednak solidne koła będą niezbędne. Teren jest bardzo skalisty, 
więc noszenie butów trekkingowych jest zdecydowanie zalecane. Należy uważnie patrzeć na oznaczenia szlaku, ponieważ kilka 
razy przypadkowo zaczęliśmy wspinać się na skały niebędące częścią szlaku (oznaczenia szlaku nie zawsze były jasne i 
wiele z nich było uszkodzonych). Pogoda była niesamowita, piękny słoneczny dzień w listopadzie z przyjemnymi temperaturami. 
Jednak dalej musieliśmy wziąć pod uwagę wczesny zachód słońca o tej porze roku, aby uniknąć problemów, ponieważ nie 
mieliśmy czołówek.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 210407.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 214111.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113202.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113217.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replika Jaskini &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grotte-cosquer.com/en/homepage/&quot;&gt;The Cosquer Cave&lt;/a&gt; w Villa Méditerranée oferuje zwiedzanie 
tego miejsca słuchając audioprzewodnika w języku angielskim podczas 35-minutowej przejażdżki łodzią, podczas której 
zwiedzający mają możliwość odkrycia ponad 400 dzieł na ścianach jaskini. Następnie, w amfiteatrze pokazywany jest 
film dokumentalny opowiadający o odkryciu jaskini przez Henri’ego Cosquer. Niestety, film jest po francusku, a angielskie 
napisy na małych telewizorach obok dużego ekranu, bardzo utrudniają jednoczesne oglądanie filmu i czytanie tekstu na 
innych ekranach. Kolejne rozczarowanie czekało na nas w następnym pomieszczeniu, gdzie krótkie filmy przedstawiały krok 
po kroku tworzenie repliki jaskini, bez napisów w języku angielskim. Ponadto, prezentujący wyjaśniał techniki używane 
do replikowania oryginalnej jaskini, ale ponownie, tylko po francusku. Dlatego czuliśmy, że nie mogliśmy w pełni 
doświadczyć potencjału muzeum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2023/12/Marsylia-Francja/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2023/12/Marsylia-Francja/</guid>
        
        <category>Francja</category>
        
        <category>Marsylia</category>
        
        <category>Calanques</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weekend in Marseille: Exploring the Oldest City of France</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The small park with archaeological remains next to the Marseille History Museum is the place where the story of Marseille began. 
It was here, in this very spot, that the first Greek settlers from Phocaea breathed life into the city around 600 BC, 
laying down the roots of what would become the bustling port of Marseille. You can still see the 
real-size boat used by Greeks to sail on rough Mediterranean Sea to get to this naturally tranquil bay, offering 
excellent protection from the wind and providing shelter to outlanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_112904.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a stone’s throw away, the modern port buzzes with activity, visible from the “Mirador de Saint-Jean,” viewpoint close to 
city fortification that is guiding ships to the entrance of the port. 
At the port’s end, the Quai des Belges comes alive each morning as fishermen hawk their freshest catch. Here also stands 
a memorial honoring those first adventurous Greek settlers, commemorating their foundational role in the city’s history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103113.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103082.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103080.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103077.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The district of ‘Le Panier’ was in direct neighborhood to our apartment, so we found ourselves wandering through this area a few times,  always 
getting lost in the narrow streets, while discovering some new graffiti, colorful alleys and charming boutiques with Marseille soap. Actually 
the original Marseille soap looks very boring, just large cube (300g) of greenish soap that has subtle scent. However, this is exactly
what your skin needs, 72% of olive oil will definitely moisturize your skin properly and a true panacea for the skin. Don’t be 
attracted by all beautiful soaps
full of colouring, perfume or synthetic additives. Besides cute little shops, you can also find here small galleries and 
interesting cafés.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103093.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_125351.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103108.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_172204.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Old Charity Center’s forecourt, deserted in the chill of November, our guide assured us, would be difficult to pass 
during high season months when all restaurants and cafés put their tables out here. In late autumn, much like the rest of the Le Panier district, this area empties out, with shops closing and the neighborhood 
quieting down, awaiting the vibrancy of spring and several busy months to follow. A few years ago, it was still possible 
to live there, signing a long-term lease, but now the majority of homes are listed on Airbnb. Short-term rentals, even 
just for a few months, prove to be far more profitable than renting to permanent city residents. We noticed often “Airbnb 
dehors” spray-painted on the walls, which translates to “Airbnb go away”. A clear statement by locals who cherish 
living here, but find it less and less affordable to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103136.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103135.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This magnificent basilica, the Cathedral of La Major, was built in the 19th century near the foundation of the original 
Marseille port. The colors of the walls were stunning, especially when highlighted by the sunset light that accentuated 
the different stones used in the construction, which lasted more than 40 years to complete.
Our apartment was just a few hundred meters from this basilica, so we never got lost as its 60-meter-high tower was very 
easy to spot. The surrounding area is a great place for an evening walk during the sunset, offering lovely views of the 
port, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mucem.org/&quot;&gt;MUCEM&lt;/a&gt;, and Cosquer Méditerranée just next to it. The floor of the basilica is adorned with magnificent mosaics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_170032.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103065.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_130617.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We highly recommend visiting the rooftop of the Museum of Civilizations of Europe and the Mediterranean (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mucem.org/&quot;&gt;MUCEM&lt;/a&gt;), which 
you can reach via a catwalk from Fort St. Jean or through the museum itself. This museum has fascinating architecture, 
resembling a huge sponge or deep-water corals from a distance. Once on the rooftop, which offers free access, you can 
soak in the expansive views of the city, harbor, and fort through the intricate outer metal walls. It’s the perfect spot 
for a break to enjoy the views! This contrast between the fort’s old buildings and the modern museum complements each 
other beautifully. As we continued, we explored the narrow paths and gardens, finding the tranquility and warmth of 
the sun in secluded corners where the wind couldn’t reach us. Multiple viewpoints allowed us to admire both the Basilica 
of Notre-Dame de la Garde and the Cathedral of la Major. Our exploration was full of surprises, from hidden squares with 
fountains to murals of women and an abundance of plants that made this place truly unique. It’s a must-visit if you’re 
looking to escape the city’s bustle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103117.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141649.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_135459.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103111.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Basilica of Notre-Dame de la Garde, offering a 360-degree view of the city, is undoubtedly a must-visit destination. 
Although we didn’t spend much time inside the church, we couldn’t help but notice the fascinating decorations, including 
ships suspended from the ceiling, which emphasize the city’s deep connection to the sea. Make sure to look up—the ceiling 
is breathtaking! From the outdoor area, you can take in the extensive panorama of Marseille, including the new cruise port 
situated in a more industrial part of the city, which lies beyond walking distance from the old historic center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141834.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_162108.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_161130.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103129.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the back side of the church, the view opens up to Endoume, the city’s most prestigious neighborhood, where houses are 
densely nestled together, surrounded by the sea and mountains&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103128.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Orange Velodrome Stadium and big apartment complexes were definitely standing out among the buildings on this side of 
the city with the stunning Calanques National Park in the backdrop, our destination the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103130.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We love nature and hiking, so we always try to combine short city trips with at least one day spent in nature. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.calanques-parcnational.fr/en&quot;&gt;Calanques 
National Park&lt;/a&gt;, located between Marseille and Cassis, was the obvious choice after examining the map of the city’s surroundings. 
Hiking, rock climbing, swimming, and canoeing are the primary activities available in this national park. The sharp, white 
cliffs and the clear waters at their base create a magnificent view that you can enjoy along the hiking path. A ‘calanque’ 
is a unique type of geological formation made of limestone found along the Mediterranean coast. The first photo below shows 
the main viewpoint, Sugiton, which is the most accessible one at approximately 2.5 km from the bus stop. From here, you can 
also descend to the beach (about an extra 1 km) or extend your walk by several more kilometers toward Cassis, following the 
main GR trail. That was our choice, and we didn’t regret it at all! The path was very rocky and demanding, with many steep 
and narrow parts, but the fabulous views were well worth the effort. Unfortunately, we had to retrace our steps because we 
were unsure of where the other paths led; Google Maps wasn’t very helpful this time, and relying solely on the markers on 
the rocks wasn’t sufficient for navigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113218.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113224.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113148.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113215.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_152147.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113195.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our second evening, we spent time at the Cosquer Cave replica museum, located just a few hundred meters from our apartment. 
In 1985, the cave was discovered by Henri Cosquer, a diving enthusiast, who found the entrance leading to an immense submerged 
gallery. This nearly 175-meter-long passage unveiled a real treasure dating back 30,000 years, featuring over 480 
pieces including paintings and engravings of penguins, deer, ibex, bison, as well as hand prints and traces of a fireplace. 
At that time, the sea level was about 120 meters lower than it is today, and the shoreline was several kilometers 
distant. However, due to rising sea levels, this prehistoric site is at risk of vanishing, with some artworks already 
partially submerged. The urgency to preserve and share this unparalleled discovery with the world has become urgent. 
Currently, the cave is not accessible to the public, and its entrance has been sealed for its protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We rented an apartment on Airbnb in the La Joliette neighborhood, just a few buildings away from Marseille Cathedral, 
located on the 6th floor without an elevator. There were many similar rental offers. This might not be the best solution 
for people with a lot of luggage or those with children. When maritime traffic exceeded the capacity of the Old Port, 
a new one was established, and our apartment was situated right at the entrance to this vast port. The ‘Saint-Charles’ 
train station is within a 15-20 minute walk, so we didn’t even consider using public transportation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guided tour &lt;a href=&quot;https://marseillefreewalkingtour.com/&quot;&gt;Marseille Free Walking Tour&lt;/a&gt; for about 2.5hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delicious patisserie La Pâtisserie des Marseillais &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lapatisseriedesmarseillais.fr/&quot;&gt;Pascal Guglielmi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bus number 60, from the Capitainerie bus stop to the Basilica of Notre-Dame de la Garde, offers an almost 20-minute ride. There is no entrance fee for the church. We only spent about 15 minutes in the area around the church due to the strong winds 
and cold weather, and we returned using the same ticket, which was valid for 1 hour.
When we boarded the bus again, we scanned our ticket, but it wasn’t charged, and we were able to use it the next day for the metro. 
Each ticket we bought was valid for 2 rides, but the machine offers multiple options when selecting the number of rides. For 
those with children, taking the small train from the old port (located directly across from the city hall in Marseille) 
is a great option!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take Metro line 2 from Joliette to Castellane, and then catch bus B1 for a 30-40 minute ride in the direction of Campus de 
Luminy, getting off at the Luminy – PN des Calanques stop. Our hike in the Calanques National Park covered approximately 
16 km (5-6 hours including breaks). On the map below, which highlights our route, you’ll notice a small branch indicating 
the Belvédère de Sugiton viewpoint, a popular destination for many visitors. It’s quite accessible; we saw people with prams, 
but sturdy wheels are essential. The area is very rocky, so wearing good trail running or hiking shoes is crucial for safety. 
Be vigilant for trail markers, as we accidentally started climbing rocks not part of the trail a few times (the trail markers 
are not always clear, and many have been damaged). We were fortunate to have amazing weather, a beautiful sunny day in November 
with pleasant temperatures. However, we had to be mindful of the early sunset at this time of year to avoid any problems, 
since we did not have headlights&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 210407.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 214111.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113202.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113217.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The replica of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grotte-cosquer.com/en/homepage/&quot;&gt;The Cosquer Cave&lt;/a&gt; in Villa Méditerranée offers an 
engaging audio guide in English for a 35-minute boat 
ride, during which visitors can explore over 400 works on the cave’s walls. Afterwards, there’s a documentary film in 
an amphitheater that chronicles the cave’s discovery by Henri Cosquer. Unfortunately, the film is in French, and English 
subtitles are provided on small TVs adjacent to the big screen, making it challenging to watch the film and read the text 
on the other screens simultaneously. Another disappointment awaited us in the next room, where short films depicted the 
step-by-step creation of the cave’s replica without any English subtitles. Additionally, a presenter explained the 
techniques used to replicate the original cave, but once again, only in French. This was similar to the rest of the 
text displayed on the gallery walls. Therefore, we felt as though we couldn’t fully experience what the museum is offering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/12/Marseille-France/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/12/Marseille-France/</guid>
        
        <category>France</category>
        
        <category>Marseille</category>
        
        <category>Calanques</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wiosenna przygoda w okolicy Bredy przy granicy z Belgią</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Miesiąc maj ma dla mnie szczególne znaczenie. Nie tylko dlatego, że w tym miesiącu świętuję urodziny, ale także z powodu 
licznych długich weekendów, które sprawiają, że jest to idealny moment na odkrywanie lokalnych atrakcji. W tym roku nasz wybór padł na okolice Bredy, 
urokliwego miasta w Holandii. Gdy wreszcie opuściliśmy monotonną autostradę, krajobraz zmienił się na bardziej wiejski, 
zaczęliśmy dostrzegać malownicze farmy, swobodnie pasące się konie i traktory pracujące na odległych polach. Nasz pierwszy 
dzień spędziliśmy na odkrywaniu uroków Natuurgebied Pannenhoef, 
zielonego obszaru na mapie, który okazał się być miłym miejscem na spacery i obserwację ptaków. Widzieliśmy nie tylko ptaki, 
ale również konie i owce. Miejsce to miało naprawdę piękne otoczenie z licznymi trasami rowerowymi i drewnianymi mostkami. 
Wędrując wąskimi ścieżkami, odkryliśmy małe ławeczki strategicznie umieszczone w najbardziej zapierających dech w piersiach 
miejscach. Te ukryte miejsca odpoczynku oferowały doskonałą okazję, by zatrzymać się i cieszyć się najlepszymi widokami.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230429_163700.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230429_165908.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230429_161342.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hetaardbeienterras.nl/&quot;&gt;Farma truskawek&lt;/a&gt; znajdowała się zaledwie kilkaset metrów od naszego wynajętego domu, 
więc była oczywistym wyborem na wizytę kolejnego dnia. Obszar piknikowy wokół farmy truskawkowej jest świetny, z mnóstwem 
zabawek dla dzieci i rowerami w różnych rozmiarach. Byliśmy tam na samym początku sezonu truskawkowego, więc jeszcze nie 
było opcji zbierania truskawek samemu, co będzie możliwe w późniejszym terminie, więc ominęła nas największa atrakcja tego 
miejsca. Pierwszy rzut świeżych truskawek był już dostępny do kupienia, jednak nie były one tak słodkie, jak się tego 
spodziewaliśmy, prawdopodobnie z powodu pierwszego tygodnia z naprawdę słoneczną pogodą. Nasze główne rozczarowanie dotyczyło 
jednak jedzenia - zamówione gofry z bitą śmietaną okazały się bardzo słodkie i suche, jak te z półek sklepowych, a polewa 
czekoladowa bardziej przypominała kakaowe gęste mleko. Naprawdę szkoda!
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_114407.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_114300.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_114314.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wiemy, jak bardzo nasza córka uwielbia obserwować zwierzęta, więc znaleźliśmy idealne miejsce do odwiedzenia: gospodarstwo 
dziecięce o nazwie  &lt;a href=&quot;https://leijhoeve.nl/&quot;&gt;Kinderboerderij Leijhoeve&lt;/a&gt;. Dobrze utrzymane place zabaw, mała kawiarnia z 
przystępnymi cenami, leśny zakątek z grzybami, a zwłaszcza łąka z kozami biegającymi wolno i chętnymi do głaskania sprawiają, 
że to miejsce jest tak interesujące. Jest tam naprawdę spokojnie, a wiele ławek zachęca do odpoczynku w ciszy. Lokalizacja 
kawiarnianego tarasu pozwala na doglądanie bawiących się na placach zabaw dzieci, więc to także idealne miejsce dla rodziców, 
aby wypić świeżą kawę. Miejsce jest prowadzone przez osoby niepełnosprawne, i wygląda na to, że wykonują bardzo dobrą robotę!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_145356.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_150442.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_151727.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_152056.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_145724.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nie bez powodu szukaliśmy zakwaterowania w okolicach większego miasta. Liczyliśmy, że Breda dostarczy nam alternatywnych 
atrakcji w razie złej pogody. Jednak pogoda na tyle się udała, że wybraliśmy się tylko do miasta na obiad, przechodząc 
przez park miejski pełen ludzi leżących na kocach. Następnie minęliśmy zamek i zakończyliśmy wizytę w włoskiej restauracji 
na głównym rynku. Potem poszliśmy na krótki spacer po ulicach handlowych położonych wokół głównego kościoła, a następnie 
wróciliśmy do naszego wynajętego domu, który okazał się świetnym miejscem do obserwowania startujących oraz lądujących na 
pobliskiej łące balonów.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_160527.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_174142.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podczas ostatniego dnia pobytu, po wcześniejszym wymeldowaniu się rano, pojechaliśmy w kierunku, 
parku narodowego położonego na granicy belgijsko-holenderskiej. Szlak pieszy “Duna” był naszym wyborem, prowadzącym przez 
rozległe wrzosowiska, które są popularną atrakcją pod koniec lata, gdy kwitną fioletowe kwiaty. O tej porze roku krajobraz 
był dość monotonny, z dominującą zielenią i brązem w scenerii.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jednak kiedy dotarliśmy do wydm, stało się to bardziej interesujące, szczególnie dla naszego malucha, który uwielbiał tę
gigantyczną piaskownicę. Dla mnie było mniej przyjemne, ponieważ nosiłem ją w nosidle, a dodatkowe 12 kg sprawiało, że moje 
stopy zapadały się głębiej w piasek. Och, moje łydki płonęły następnego dnia! Warto zauważyć, że psy nie są dozwolone na 
tym szlaku, ponieważ prowadzi on przez obszar wypasu owiec, chociaż nie widzieliśmy żadnych zwierząt. Po drodze weszliśmy 
również obowiązkowo na największą wieżę widokową w parku.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_113319.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_150355.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_113815.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_132917.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_121422.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To był niezapomniany czas spędzony na łonie natury, pełen niepowtarzalnych chwil i magicznych widoków. Majówka w okolicach 
Bredy zdecydowanie zapisze się w mojej pamięci jako wyjątkowa podróż, która otworzyła nasze oczy na piękno holenderskiego 
krajobrazu. Z niecierpliwością oczekiwałem na moją kolejną przygodę.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wynajęliśmy dom &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hoevenelleveld.nl&quot;&gt;na Airbnb niedaleko Rijsbergen&lt;/a&gt; znajdujący się na farmie, 
tylko 1.5 godziny jazdy z Leuven. Plac zabaw dla dzieci był niesamowity, a na dodatek mieszkały tam dwa konie 
przechadzające się pod naszymi oknami, kury oraz pies. To była bardzo cicha okolica, idealna do jazdy na rowerze i 
biegania. Każdego ranka i około zachodu słońca mogliśmy obserwować balony na gorące unoszące się na horyzoncie.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nasza wędrówka w parku Kalmthoutse Heide miała około 8km. Zaparkowaliśmy obok Centrum dla Odwiedzających Kalmthout
(parking jest darmowy, ale lepiej być tam wcześnie rano, ponieważ około południa robi się bardzo tłoczno). Trochę się 
zgubiliśmy w okolicach 4km, jak można zobaczyć na mapie. Skręciliśmy za szybko w lewo i skończyliśmy na parkingu, ale tak 
naprawdę powinniśmy byli podążać długą ścieżką przez park, zanim skręcimy w lewo, aby dotrzeć do wydm. Ta część wędrówki 
nie była dla nas wystarczająco jasno oznaczona. Zdecydowanie łatwiej byłoby, gdyby mapy szlaków były dostępne w większej 
liczbie miejsc. Nie zrobiliśmy zdjęcia szlaku przy wejściu do parku, co bardzo by nam pomogło. Więcej wędrówek z 
dokładnymi opisami można znaleźć na &lt;a href=&quot;https://grensparkkalmthoutseheide.com/en/wandelroutes/0&quot;&gt;oficjalnej stronie parku&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_150346.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/Screenshot 2023-05-02 215019.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wokół Natuurgebied Pannenhoef znajduje się kilka miejsc parkingowych. Raz zaparkowaliśmy nasz samochód na parkingu 
Pannenhoef Parkeerplaats het Vaartven. To nie jest właściwy parking, tylko kilka miejsc między drzewami, gdzie można 
parkować, i mogę sobie wyobrazić, że po deszczu może być trudno tam dojechać.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Każdego wieczoru wybierałem się na bieganie w okolicach rezerwatu przyrody Pannenhoef i miasta Rijsbergen. Poniżej 
znajdują się mapy moich biegów, oba około 8 km. Pierwszy, w rezerwacie przyrody, był bardzo miły, głównie eksplorowałem 
tereny podmokłe. Drugiego dnia skierowałem się w stronę mini zoo, które odwiedziliśmy, próbując używać małych ścieżek, 
które przecinały otaczające pola.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/Screenshot 2023-06-14 204244.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/IMG_20230429_195444_469.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/IMG_20230429_200134_380.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/Screenshot 2023-06-14 204339.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2023/05/Breda-Holandia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2023/05/Breda-Holandia/</guid>
        
        <category>Netherlands</category>
        
        <category>Breda</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Peaceful Dutch countryside close to Belgium border</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;May holds a special place in my heart, not only because it marks my birthday but also because it offers plenty of long 
weekends, making it the perfect time for local trips. This year, we set our sights on the tranquil countryside surrounding 
Breda, a charming city in the Netherlands. As we left the highway, the landscape 
changed to large farmhouses with many horse and a tractors dotting the fields. Our adventure began right away as we 
admired the rural landscape while walking around the place we stayed. Natuurgebied Pannenhoef was our first destination, 
a green area on the map that turned out to be a nice place for walks and bird watching. We not only saw birds but also 
horses and sheep. It had really beautiful surroundings with many cycling routes and wooden bridges. Along the narrow paths, 
we discovered small benches strategically placed in the most breathtaking spots. These hidden resting spots offered the 
perfect opportunity to pause and enjoy the best views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230429_163700.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230429_165908.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230429_161342.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hetaardbeienterras.nl/&quot;&gt;The Strawberries Terrace&lt;/a&gt; was situated just several hundred meters from our rented house, so it was an obvious choice 
for the next day’s visit. The picnic area around the strawberry farm is great, with lots of toys for kids and bikes in 
different sizes. We were there at the very beginning of the strawberry season, and it was still not allowed to pick them 
ourselves, which is the biggest attraction of this place. Fresh strawberries were on sale, but you could taste the 
difference; they were not as sweet as we would have liked, but the really sunny days were just starting. Our main 
disappointment was regarding the food. We ordered waffles with whipped cream, and both were of very poor quality. 
Simply re-selling waffles from the supermarket is really not acceptable to us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_114407.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_114300.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_114314.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we know how much our daughter enjoys looking at animals, we found a perfect place to visit: a children’s farm called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://leijhoeve.nl/&quot;&gt;Kinderboerderij Leijhoeve&lt;/a&gt;. Well-maintained playgrounds, a small café with affordable prices, a 
mushroom forest, and especially a meadow with goats accessible for petting made this place so interesting. It’s really 
quiet there. You can just sit and enjoy the coffee while your kids are running around. You can keep a good eye on them 
from the terrace. The place is run by disabled people, and it looks like they do a very good job!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_145356.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_150442.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_151727.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_152056.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_145724.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying close to Breda was our intention to have some backup places to visit in case of bad weather, or mostly to have 
options for indoor playgrounds. However, the weather was so nice that instead, we walked through the city park, passed 
by the castle, and ended up at the Italian restaurant on the main market. Afterwards, we took a short walk on the 
shopping streets situated around the main church and then headed back to our place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_160527.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_174142.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our last day, after checking out early in the morning, we drove towards Grenspark Kalmthoutse Heide, a national park 
situated on the Belgian-Dutch border. The hiking trail “Dune” was our choice, leading through vast heathlands which are a 
popular attraction in late summer when the purple flowers bloom. At this time of the year, the landscape was quite monotonous, with green and 
brown dominating the scenery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, once we reached the dunes, it became more interesting, especially for our toddler who loved this giant sandbox. 
It was less enjoyable for me, as I was carrying her in the carrier, and the extra 12kg made my feet sink deeper into the 
sand. Oh, my calves were burning the next day! It’s worth noting that dogs are not allowed on this hike because it passes 
through a grazing area, even though we didn’t see any animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_113319.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_150355.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_113815.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_132917.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_121422.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May truly proved to be the ideal time for local trips, allowing us to immerse ourselves in nature’s embrace while creating 
cherished memories along the way. I found myself eagerly looking forward to my next adventure. This time, the excitement 
was amplified as it marked my first weekend trip without my daughter. It was a chance to immerse myself in the vibrant 
energy of Paris, accompanied by a friend. With a mere 36 hours in the City of Light, we were determined to make every 
moment count and create lasting memories. More details in upcoming post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We rented a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hoevenelleveld.nl&quot;&gt;cottage house on Airbnb close to Rijsbergen&lt;/a&gt;, only a 1.5-hour drive from 
Leuven. The house had an amazing playground for kids, and there were two horses, chickens, and a dog living on the farm. 
It was a very quiet area, perfect for cycling and running. Every morning and around sunset, we could see hot air balloons 
on the horizon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our hike in Kalmthoutse Heide park was about 8km. We parked next to the Kalmthout Visitor’s Center (free parking but 
  it’s better to be there early in the morning as it gets very crowded around lunchtime). We got a little bit lost around 
  the 4km mark, as you can see on the map. We turned left too quickly and ended up at the parking area, but we were actually 
  supposed to follow the long path through the park before turning left to reach the dunes. This part of the hike was not 
  marked clearly enough for us. It would have been much easier if maps of the trails were available in more places. We 
  didn’t take a photo of the trail at the entrance to the park, and that would have helped us greatly. You can find more 
  hikes with detailed descriptions on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://grensparkkalmthoutseheide.com/en/wandelroutes/0&quot;&gt;park’s website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_150346.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/Screenshot 2023-05-02 215019.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are several parking spaces around Natuurgebied Pannenhoef. We left our car once at Pannenhoef Parkeerplaats het 
Vaartven. This is not a proper parking lot, just some spaces between trees where you are allowed to park, and I can 
imagine it can be difficult to drive there after rain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every evening, I went for a run in the surroundings of the nature reservoir Pannenhoef and Rijsbergen city. Below 
are the maps of my runs, both around 8km. The first one, in the nature reservoir, was very nice, mainly exploring wetlands. 
On the second day, I headed towards the mini zoo that we visited, trying to use small paths that crossed the surrounding 
fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/Screenshot 2023-06-14 204244.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/IMG_20230429_195444_469.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/IMG_20230429_200134_380.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/Screenshot 2023-06-14 204339.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/05/Breda-Netherlands/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/05/Breda-Netherlands/</guid>
        
        <category>Netherlands</category>
        
        <category>Breda</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tips to make travelling with the baby or toddler easier</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We had to change our way of travelling and adjust to the needs of our little one. People always say that you can keep travelling
even after you became a parent. Yes, it’s true, you can … but it will not be the same! Our holidays now are less intense, we are visiting
kids-friendly places where we can have realistic chances to relax and have a break. A bored, tired or frustrated toddler will 
not allow you to do so! We are travelling on regular basis from Belgium to Poland to visit my family. The first time we went 
to Poland when our daughter was 3 months old. We also managed to go twice for holidays in Europe: to Lisbon (at 6 months 
old) and Malaga (at 14 months). Both trips were very different because of the baby’s age, but also because we have 
learned a lot during the first trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are our tips for the flight itself?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take in consideration the time of the flight and if it will fit with yours baby daily routine. E.g. we don’t book flights
with departures time before 10am or after 4pm (which limits our options considerably!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always travel with the buggy and baby carrier (we switch to the carrier while boarding the plane). Do note that
even though you are allowed to take the carrier up to the plane, you are required to get a label for it before going 
through security from the check-in desk. In theory, you are allowed
to take 1 small bag when you buy infant ticket (under age of 2) but we always had a small additional cotton bag with all the 
little one’s food and drinks, no one ever complained (in case there would be an issue, all things would comfortably
fit in our luggage). In general, the less luggage you have the better. We have standard carry-on bags when 
traveling for a week (1 small backpack per person) and it’s really enough! Once you reach your destination, it’s time to 
find your buggy. Every airport have them in a different spot, usually together with oversized luggage but never next 
to the plane. This is why having a carrier can be extremely helpful as sometimes it’s a really long walk from the plane 
to the baggage reclaim. It’s also useful to have small blanket to cover the baby while boarding the plane, sometimes it’s very 
windy, and you never know how long you’ll have to queue outside to get into the plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take enough water and snacks for your baby. According to TSA (Transportation Security Administration), there are no 
restrictions of liquids when you travel with 
kid under age of 12. Water is allowed in reasonable quantities. We usually have a 1 L bottle of water, an extra sippy cup 
already filled with water, soy milk in cardboard (250 mL), and 2-3 jars of baby food. As well some sandwiches, fruits and
veggies. This might look like a lot, but it is good to have some extras in case of emergency (unexpected delays or 
flight cancellation). Keeping the water and food in a separate cotton bag, is convenient as you’ll need to show all baby 
liquids at the security. If your baby is still on breast or formula, it’s good to give the milk during takeoff and 
landing. Apparently, babies can’t pop their ears intentionally, but we can help them by encouraging them to swallow. 
Flight attendant will provide some hot water to make your formula upon request. If you are breastfeeding, a big scarf 
and special bra will be helpful to give you some privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also helps to have a new small toy for your baby, they will have a better mood and hopefully will be occupied with the
new gift for quite some time :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are specific hints about the airports we’ve used so far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zaventem, Belgium - amazing playing area for kids next to the food corner (entrance next to the Starbucks). There is 
a microwave, high chairs, changing stations, big table for parents to sit, perfect place to wait for the flight! Going 
through securing was easy with the baby, all baby food and water was checked so better keep it in a separate bag for easy 
access.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pyrzowice, Poland - we didn’t find any playing area for toddlers, there are changing rooms. Security here is
inefficient and needlessly long. E.g. this is one of the few airports where they require shoes to be taken off and scanned. 
Expect long queues without a no priority line for families with kids.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lisbon, Portugal - there is a single special land for security checks for elderly, people in wheelchair and parents with 
babies, but be aware that it could take even longer than going by regular line as all the “slower people” will be 
in the special queue! They discourage this because there are a few steps down to get to the regular security check, 
which shouldn’t be an issue when travelling with a buggy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands - it’s the best airport for parents with babies when it comes to the security checks. 
The staff ensures parents with kids can move through security swiftly, and their modern scanners allow you to keep 
most things inside your backpacks/suitcases. They just check all baby food and water afterwards in the special machine.
It is always for us very nice experience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Malaga (AGP), Spain - There was enough space to comfortably sit at the airport but the playing area we found was 
very small and closed off for unknown reasons. Going through security was a pleasant experience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the important criteria when looking for accommodation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Airbnb is our favourite platform when travelling. When we went for you first trip to Lisbon, we thought that having an 
apartment in the city center will give us flexibility.
We could come back to the apartment, it will be close to the shops and restaurants. BUT, we didn’t predict that houses in 
the old part of the city have paper thin walls. It was so laud that we couldn’t sleep and our baby had even more problems with 
sleep. It also happened few time around midnight and early morning that people were discarding glass bottles outside, waking up
everyone in the neighborhood. Next time, we checked the reviews of the apartments carefully, looking for any clues about 
the noise level. Our apartment in Benalmadena was much better! It had bigger bedroom that even with extra travel cot had enough space 
to be comfortably used. This time we also stayed in quiet area next to the park (with animals and playground), the beach and 
bus stops (this time we also relied on public transportation). Dark curtains to make the apartment dark for our baby nap, 
was another useful feature of the apartment. A small kitchen for making breakfasts and snacks is always a must for us. 
A bigger shower helped us a lot when it comes to the evening baths, especially after playing on the beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arrived at your destination? What to do next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It always makes sense to search in advance for playgrounds in the areas that you are going to visit. Sometimes they can 
be really nice, perfect for a break with a toddler. Once babies start to walk, it becomes impossible to keep them long
in their stroller, they need to run and explore :D It’s useful to have a small blanket or sport towel to use in the parks 
for a break. Even if your baby is very small, it’s good for them to have a break for tummy time or play with their toys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As public toilets with changing stations are rare, having a changing mat is a must. The waterproof layer can
also come in handy as an extra layer while sitting on grass. Keep in mind that even in some restaurants toilets can
be very small and lack a changing station, in those cases you’ll also be happy you have your own mat with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Lisbon, all tourists attractions had a separate line for families, so we didn’t have to wait much at all. Also in the shops, people 
were letting us ahead, even if we didn’t ask them for this and that was really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20220221_163710.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20220215_153807.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We travel with both a buggy and baby carrier. It gives us the flexibility needed for visiting different kind of places. 
For example, it would not be possible to visits city center of Lisbon, Moorish Castle in Portugal or Calamorro Mountain 
in Spain with the buggy. On the other hand a buggy comes handy for long walks along the see or while visiting some sites like the
Jerónimos Monastery in Lisbon (which is perfectly suited for a buggy). The easiest way to make a decision 
“buggy or carrier?” is to check the reviews on the trip advisor or on Google and look for any that describes how kids-friendly a particular tourist attraction is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dreambaby.be/e/fr/db/dreambee-essentials-poussette-canne-grey-melange-214187?utm_source=google&amp;amp;utm_medium=shopping&amp;amp;s_kwcid=AL!6321!3!!!!x!!&amp;amp;gclid=CjwKCAiAheacBhB8EiwAItVO2yQ7N_C6VWkn4sxHW_TIX8rNzywIH3wWZIyx8EqOYPPCespcWfD0HxoCK10QAvD_BwE&quot;&gt;Buggy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com.be/-/en/BABYBJ%C3%96RN-Carrier-Black-Cotton-White/dp/B07KPSS456/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2Q7TKLKF68UZ8&amp;amp;keywords=BabyBj%C3%B6rn+carrier+one&amp;amp;qid=1671045227&amp;amp;sprefix=babybj%C3%B6rn+carrier+one%2Caps%2C60&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Baby Bjorn carrier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nanabeebi.com/en/products/luiertas-rugzak&quot;&gt;Nanabeebi backpack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2022 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/12/Travelling-toddler-tips/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/12/Travelling-toddler-tips/</guid>
        
        <category>plane</category>
        
        <category>toddler</category>
        
        <category>baby</category>
        
        <category>Malaga</category>
        
        <category>Lisbon</category>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our top 3 half-day trips from Benalmadena </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Malaga, and Benalmadena specifically, are nice places as a home-base for doing small trips in this part of Andalusia. We had 
three days, and we decided to spend each of the afternoons exploring another destination. You can easily do everything 
in half the time, but we didn’t want to rush with the baby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mijas-village&quot;&gt;Mijas Village&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first (and the best!) destination was Mijas village. Beautiful,
small village on the slopes of the mountain, white houses decorated with flowers in blue pots. Many shops with leather 
goods, nougat, spices, honey and other delicatessen produced locally. Amazing view of the coast and the mountains!
Definitely check Parque La Muralla with church Iglesia Inmaculada Concepción and amazing views of the mountains and Alboran 
Sea. I would highly recommend to get lost in the narrow streets of this cute village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_164928.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_165256.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_162249.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_173539.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_173301.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_160725.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_162008.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_160657.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_160454.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_161834.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_152929.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-colomares-monument-butterfly-park-and-stupa&quot;&gt;The Colomares Monument, Butterfly park and Stupa&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our second destination, the Colomares Monument is a castle-style monument honoring Christopher Columbus and his discovery of the new world, America. 
This monument was built between 1987 and 1994 by Esteban Martin Martin and his two co-workers. A great place to take some interesting pictures! 
It’s not big, but it feels intense because of the number of ornaments.  It is a mix of many architectural styles and materials: brick, 
stone and cement. One part of the monument resembles of the stern from La Santa Maria, the largest of the three Spanish 
ships used by Christopher Columbus in his first voyage across the Atlantic Ocean in 1492.  You can love it or hate it. 
We had vastly different opinions, so check it yourself in what camp you’ll fall!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154146.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154729.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154519.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154713.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_160055.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a 30-minute walk along the main road, we reached the Butterfly Park and Stupa of Enlightenment. At the entrance you will receive
a small list of different butterfly species with names and photos to see if you can spot all of them. This place looks 
like a big greenhouse, very hot and humid with a lot of plants, not unlike being in a tropical forest.
The most spectacular species we spotted were &lt;em&gt;Greta Oto&lt;/em&gt;, a butterfly with transparent wings, the bright blue 
&lt;em&gt;Morpho pheleides&lt;/em&gt; and the black &lt;em&gt;Parides iphidamas&lt;/em&gt; with its big red dots on the wings. Besides the butterflies, you 
can see their small wallaby and very colorful, rainbow finches, both native to Australia. It’s a great place for older 
kids. Young toddlers can have difficulties to spot the butterflies and if they do, you need to be careful and not let 
them damaged the fragile butterflies as some do get very close to visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_164017.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_164638.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_165254.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_170245.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_164147.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_174647.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;el-calamorro-monte&quot;&gt;El Calamorro Monte&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El Calamorro Monte, panoramic view of Benalmadena. It has several access points, but we decided to take the Benalmádena Cable Car, 
which runs along its slope from Arroyo de la Miel (next to the old Tivoli amusement park) to the very top of the mountain 
(approximately 780 metres above the see level). There are a few beautiful view points and a show featuring birds of prey at the top.
You can also start hiking from there in various directions or even cycle downhill (you can take your bike by cable car, 
though you might need to detach a wheel to get it in the cabin). We were too late for last show with birds of prey 
(3:00 pm) but we enjoyed a small tour around the peak, remember to take some extra clothes, with wind and clouds 
accumulating around the peak, it can get chilly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_151532.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_154359.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_160116.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_160633.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_163236.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_161609.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Playground, Patio de Juegos, next to Parque La Muralla in Mijas. We spend there a lot of time, this amazing playground has
attractions for each age group. Our one-year-old baby loved it and it not so easy to find a playground that suits her age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_164100.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.castillomonumentocolomares.com/&quot;&gt;Castillo Colomares&lt;/a&gt;  - entry 3 euro per adult, 2 euro for seniors and kids&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Butterfly Park - we bought tickets online, 8.50 euro per adult, seniors 7.50 euro. The online ticket system was a 
little strange. After paying, you should get a code via mail that can be redeemed for the tickets at the reception… We never got that mail though.
As for the tickets with PayPal fortunately the order ID was also included in the PayPal order confirmation. You need to buy tickets at 
least one hour before the visit. More on the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mariposariodebenalmadena.com/en/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Benalmadena cable car - tickets bought on spot, 16.90 euro per adult, seniors 12.90 euro&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can check how to travel by bus by reading practical info section of my related &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2022/10/Benalmadena-Spain/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;
It took us 40 min from Benalmadena to Mijas (Butterfly park was half-way to Mijas) by line 121, 126&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/11/Benalmadena-trips/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/11/Benalmadena-trips/</guid>
        
        <category>Mijas</category>
        
        <category>Benalmadena</category>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Colomares</category>
        
        <category>Monument</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Banalmadena, perfect autumn destination for a sunny holiday!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After planning all our trips to Poland for the remaining of the year, we still had approximately a week of holidays left,
so we decided to find some nice, warm place to visit in Europe. After checking all possible flight connections 
from the nearest airport, we decided to go for the warmest option, the south of Spain. Our destination, Benalmadena, had 
everything we needed: easy connection by train from the airport, beach, mountains, many shops and restaurants, 
few tourist attractions nearby and plenty of options for the nice accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This city is located approximately 20 km from Malaga where you can get easily by the same train that goes to the airport. 
We were pleasantly surprise by the weather, it was more than 20°C with no rain, and it was the beginning of November! There 
was no need to rent a car since train connection was so convenient. I had a list of places to visit prepared in 
advance, and we actually managed to see all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day we spent on exploring the city, doing some shopping and buying bus card that would allow us to travel cheaper, 
more information in the section at the end of the post. We particularly liked the marina that surprised us by very 
original shape and style of the buildings. There are plenty of shops and restaurants. In the evening the main promenade turned into small
market with (fake?) shoes, clothes or purses of well known designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_093340.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_172138.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_171721.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_173429.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_174142.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_173641.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parque de la Paloma, full of green parrots, rabbits, ducks, seagulls and dogs was our favourite destination in the
early mornings when our daughter was full of energy and couldn’t stay any longer in the apartment. The entrance 
to the park was just in front of our hotel. We were going to the playgrounds, the succulent garden or just watching green 
parrots, fooling around. Can you see them on the last photo? They were perfectly matching the color of the grass :)
The park was very clean and well-maintained, turning into huge picnic area during the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_091520.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_092653.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_093145.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_093201.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_092936.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_100804.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During next the days, we were checking nearby tourist attractions, going everywhere by bus. There is a separate post
describing these small trips &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2022/11/Benalmadena-trips/&quot;&gt;around Benalmadena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent last day of our holidays on wandering in Malaga; the city where Pablo Picasso was born. Our main goal was visiting Alcazaba,
Moorish fortress with city view. On the way there, we stopped by the main cathedral in the city (Catedral de la Encarnación 
de Málaga) though we didn’t check the church inside. Once we noticed soon after an ancient Roman theater, we knew it’s already Alcazaba.
Firstly, we were not sure if it’s possible to even visit this place with the buggy but there was a sign pointing to the back entrance where you can take a  lift,
so we gave it a try. Once up there, the areas you can easily access with a buggy (or for visitors in a wheelchair) are limited. 
While the stairs were not huge, and could be taken with a buggy, repeating this over and over however made 
our walk down challenging. As our pram is light, we were able to fold it and carried it down with us while our daughter was walking, 
avoiding the trip back down with the elevator, but we would not recommend visiting the castle if
your baby can’t walk unless you take a carrier instead of a buggy. While I was walking amongst narrow streets of the 
old part of Malaga during Laura’s nap, Sebastian visited the Picasso Museum. Even in November, it was crowded inside (mostly 
because of the school trips). Downtown Malaga would be nice for shopping, eating some local specialties, but didn’t make much of an impression on us. 
The city was already decorated with Christmas lights and many poinsettia, but we can’t tell how it looked at
night since we left before it got dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_104452.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_103845.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_104558.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_113539.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_113827.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_114324.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_114023.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_142240.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_143907.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_150056.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t miss out on the opportunity to visit this vibrant and welcoming destination on your next European holiday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The airport has perfect connection with Malaga and nearby cities on the coast by train. Buying tickets was very easy,
someone from the train service told us to use one debet card and scan once for each person and then again while leaving 
the train station. Our card was charged exactly the price for signe ticket, 2.05 euro per person (20min ride). 
Train C1 Benalmádena-Arroyo de la Miel in Malaga (walking distance from to the old part of the city), 30min ride, 2.70 euro
More info about trains on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.malagaweb.com/transport/commuter-train-malaga.php&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We stayed at BenalBeach hotel, huge complex where many apartments were owned by private people and available on 
booking.com. We noticed that these apartment were renovated and had better reviews than ones still owned by the hotel.
There was a big garden in the middle part of the hotel complex and it was possible to walk through the garden to the gate 
leading directly to the beach (not accessible for the buggy). Huge amount of plants, water running in between and lights in
the evening surprised as a lot! You could feel like in the jungle, although the highest plants were really dusty.
Despite the fact that we were in the middle of the city, it was very quiet and nice area, next to the beach, many 
restaurants and most importantly, just next to the only big park in the city center, Parque de la Paloma. I can only imagine
how crowded it can get on the beach or in the city during summer since there are many huge hotels, often 10
floors high. We felt like our hotel was mostly empty and every restaurant was trying to get our attention since not so many
tourists were walking around.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_140608.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_175542.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Playground
 Pocoyo Parque de Juegos, next to the bus stop Rotonda García Lorca - great for toddlers 1-3 years, crowded in the afternoons&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Buses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheapest and most convenient way of travelling by bus is by buying green bus card in Tobacco shops. You will pay 1.80 euro
as card deposit (you will get the cash back while returning the card). Then you need to charge the card with the amount
of money you wish, minimum 5 euro. Remember, money left on the card will not be paid back but you can charge your card 
again. For example, it is 0.79 euro per ride to Mijas, Butterfly Park and any other closer bus stop (ticket directly from 
the driver is 1.60 euro). This card can be used by the group of people, you just need to tell the driver how many people 
enter the bus, and he will print the number of tickets accordingly (each ticket notes the amount of money left to use). 
Note that this card gives discounts only for bus tickets
(not trains). In front of our hotel, there were taxis parked with predefined prices, see photo below. We couldn’t figure 
out what was the departure time of the bus based on the information from the bus schedule on the bus stop. The QR code 
listed on the board was extremely useful, immediately redirecting you the website with departure time of all buses from
particulat bus stop, including delays in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_090914.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_085802.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Museo Casa Natal de Picasso, more than 200 works donated by the members of Picasso’s family (including really early work).
Don’t expect the most famous works, but a nice overview of how he grew into the artist we all know.
Audio guide included in the ticket price, only listening to details on works that appeal to you, you can see everything 
in less than an hour. If you listen to more details it can take much longer. No entrance to the museum with any food or drinks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/10/Benalmadena-Spain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/10/Benalmadena-Spain/</guid>
        
        <category>Malaga</category>
        
        <category>Benalmadena</category>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Colomares</category>
        
        <category>Monument</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
