<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Going beyond the known</title>
    <description>A travel blog by Monika Suchoszek.</description>
    <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 19:54:28 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 19:54:28 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Madeira Adventure: Day 3 - Exploring the Beauty of the Wild West Coast</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Every evening, we made plans for the next day based on the weather and how tired we felt that day. The idea was to avoid 
having the most intense hiking days one after another. The weather looked more stable the next day, so we decided to hike 
up Pico Grande later. Today would be a less demanding day with a 9 km hike and a longer drive along the 
west coast, stopping at many viewpoints along the way. Our final stop was in Porto Moniz, where the famous natural pools 
are located. Everything took us longer than we planned, so I had to drive back to Funchal after sunset. However, the road 
via the inland (VE4) route is really good, traffic was low, and the drive was very pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started our hike with &lt;strong&gt;Levada do Moinho&lt;/strong&gt;, which was very easy and well-maintained. After taking a look at the river and 
having a break next to it, we started climbing the stairs to reach &lt;strong&gt;Levada Nova&lt;/strong&gt;, which had been above us the whole time. 
In this area, we also noticed signs of last summer’s wildfires and new ferns growing through the ash of the burnt forest, 
bringing life back to this place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC08973.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC08958.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC08997.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09002.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, the path was very easy, leading to spectacular waterfalls, not necessarily because of their height or size, but 
because you can walk behind them. A waterproof jacket is highly recommended as both levadas have some more wet parts with
water dripping above the head. Afterward, there was also a fairly long 
tunnel on the way, but the light from a cellphone was enough to walk through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the tunnel, the view opened up to a huge gorge behind, and for me, that was the scariest part of all the hikes during 
our entire stay on Madeira. I don’t remember the last time I was paralyzed by fear like this—probably when I was rock 
climbing in France years ago. I don’t have a strong fear of heights; flying isn’t my favorite thing, and I found paragliding 
stressful, but I still enjoy hiking in high mountains and tackling technical rocky sections, unlike my husband. However, 
this time, I really couldn’t force myself to take another step at one point, right after passing the waterfalls, where the 
beautiful views of the gorge began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem was the missing railing. At least half of the trail has no handrail, and the path itself is just a 30 cm-wide 
concrete levada that ends with a vertical drop. There is absolutely nothing to protect you—not even trees—so it caused me 
a lot of stress to finish this section. I would not do it again. I’m not really convinced the walk was worth it. The 
passage behind the waterfall is cool, but other than that, we found this hike quite mediocre. I would not recommend it on 
a rainy day, nor for children or elderly people. Photo below was taken after the problematic section, here you can see
very nice railing that was unfortunately not covering the whole exposed part of leveda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09014.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/IMG_20241030_110623047_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it was time to relax, and our first stop was &lt;strong&gt;Madalena do Mar&lt;/strong&gt;, a tiny town known for its famous banana plantations. 
There is a very short trail, RB3 Vereda da Vargem, also called the Banana Route, which allows visitors to immerse themselves 
in the world of banana cultivation. It was really cool to explore! It’s definitely a great place to visit with kids, and it 
might be helpful to read a little about banana plants and their growth stages beforehand to understand what you’re looking at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see bananas already covered with blue plastic bags, ready to be harvested. Bananas are cut while still green 
and left to ripen off the tree. On the other hand, you can also see tiny bananas just starting to grow and many banana 
flowers with delicate white pistils that will eventually become bananas. I found banana flowers especially spectacular and
beautiful! Make sure you’re not scared of lizards because we could hear many of them running away with each step we took. 
It was difficult to see them since they moved so fast, but when we tried walking slowly and staying very quiet, we managed 
to spot a few resting in the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09041.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09039.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It typically takes 9 to 12 months for a banana plant to produce a flower. After the flower appears, it takes 3 to 6 months 
for the bananas to develop and ripen. The female flowers at the top of the banana stem develop into bananas, forming a 
“bunch”. Each bunch consists of multiple “hands” (clusters of bananas), and each hand contains 10 to 20 individual 
bananas (often called “fingers”). A full bunch from a banana tree in Madeira typically consists of 5 to 10 hands, meaning 
one flower can yield around 50 to 150 bananas on average. After producing only one bunch, the banana plant dies, and a new plant 
grows from its base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09031.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09042.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the larger Cavendish bananas found in supermarkets, Madeira bananas (banana da Madeira) are smaller, sweeter, and 
have a more intense flavor. For us, these bananas had a different texture, more like pudding and felt less starchy. They 
are mostly grown by small farmers and harvested by hand. Most Madeira bananas are consumed locally or exported to mainland 
Portugal, we had already tried them in Lisbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/20241030_122824_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/20241030_121541_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09043.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it was time to stop by a few viewpoints. Our first stop was &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro do Massapez&lt;/strong&gt;, the only viewpoint where we were 
completely alone, surrounded by flowering aloe vera plants. It offered a stunning view and was a very quiet place, with 
a sheltered seating area and a huge stone barbecue if you wish to bring your own coal and food. We had to take a short 
detour to get here, but the parking area was spacious, and we really enjoyed the stop! Many people describe this place as 
an excellent sunset-watching spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09048.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09051_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miradouro do Fio&lt;/strong&gt;, with its cozy-looking restaurant, was our next stop. The coastline might look similar to what we had 
admired from the last viewpoint, but this time, the mountains going directly into the ocean. There was no city or road 
below, just pure nature. From here, you can see the nearby lighthouse on the right, Madeira’s westernmost point at Ponta do 
Pargo, so let’s go there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09062.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels like Madeira’s west coast is less touristy because this was another place with very few visitors. We explored 
&lt;strong&gt;Miradouro Farol da Ponta do Pargo&lt;/strong&gt;, where the lighthouse stands 300 meters high, by walking around it and checking out 
the dramatic view from the cliff. You can go down a bit, but be careful, there is no security, so do not get too close to 
the cliff edge. We didn’t go inside the museum because it was already closed. There are no benches to sit on, and after 
a rainy day, this area will get very muddy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09074.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09068.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to viewpoints, &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro da Boa Morte&lt;/strong&gt; was definitely one of the best. The combination of the blue ocean, 
deep green vegetation, and cows walking around made it look very special. The view from the parking spot and the path leading 
to the viewpoint was quite unusual. From the viewing platform, you can look straight down and admire waves crashing against 
the rocks.
When we were there, some tourists were having a lunch break with lots of snacks, which attracted a huge number of lizards 
that surrounded them. One even tried to climb my leg when I got too close! There is something magical about this place, the 
beautiful greenery, the breathtaking coastal view, the peace and quiet, and the lack of crowds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/20241030_144924_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09075.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09085.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, you can see the coastline towards Achadas da Cruz, which you can reach by cable car. Initially, we wanted to 
take this cable car (Miradouro do Teleférico das Achadas da Cruz) and explore the area, but after the stress of the exposed 
parts of Levada Nova, we lost our enthusiasm for it and decided to skip it this time. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09084.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to our last stop for the day, we had lunch at a small bar near Achadas da Cruz and also stopped to grab some 
pastries in one of the villages along the main road (more details in the practical section of this post). 
To get a nice view of Porto Moniz before entering the town, it is worth stopping for a moment at &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro da Santinha&lt;/strong&gt;, 
which is right by the road, definitely a quick stop worth making. When we arrived in Porto Moniz, we noticed that quite 
a few parking areas were under construction. Because of this, we parked a bit further away, about 100 meters from the 
main parking lots. Fortunately, it was marked on the Organic Maps app that we always use, so we had no trouble finding it
(address at the end of the post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09088.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we passed by the Porto Moniz Natural Swimming Pools, where you need to pay for entrance. There were fewer people 
than we expected, but that was likely due to the late afternoon hours and the fact that the sun had already disappeared 
behind the mountains. The pools looked really cool, especially with the waves crashing against the rocks nearby, but we 
decided to walk further to another more natural spot with no admission fee. These natural pools, formed within lava rock 
directly at the edge of the ocean, looked very interesting. However, having 
swimming shoes would have been a good idea, as the rocks felt quite sharp. The area wasn’t crowded, and a few people were 
still swimming. What really caught our attention were the spots where the water was completely calm, forming clear, still 
pools right next to the wild ocean waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09099.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09102.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09103.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we decided to go back and enter the first swimming pool, if not to swim, at least to get closer to the crashing 
waves and see the town from a different perspective. The water, however, turned out to be way too cold for my liking, and 
I only managed to immerse myself up to my waist, so no swimming for me this time! If the weather had been sunnier, I think 
we could have really enjoyed this place, but unfortunately, we arrived too late (around 5 PM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09093.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09174_01_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09180.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an hour of driving, we were back in Funchal, ready to hit the bed before exploring Curral das Freiras valley next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ifcn.madeira.gov.pt/pt/atividades-de-natureza/percursos-pedestres-recomendados/percursos-pedestres-recomendados.html&quot;&gt;Official website&lt;/a&gt; 
to check if hiking trails are open after the wildfires that occurred during the summer last year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tickets for paid hiking trails can be bought online &lt;a href=&quot;https://simplifica.madeira.gov.pt/services/78-82-259&quot;&gt;on this website.&lt;/a&gt;
From January 1, 2025, non-residents will need to pay to hike on over 30 routes managed by the Institute of Forests and 
Nature Conservation (ICNF) in Madeira. These are basically all hikes marked as PR.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting point for the hike mas church Igreja da Lombada in Ponta do Sol where we parked our car. We did both Levada do 
Moinho and Levada Nova as loop of 9km. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://visitmadeira.com/pt/o-que-fazer/exploradores-da-natureza/atividades/trail-running/lombada-da-ponta-do-sol/&quot;&gt;Ponta do Sol spine run - Levada Nova&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/Screenshot 2025-01-26 204438_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During our travels, we always use Organic Maps: Offline Hike, Bike, Trails, and Navigation app, which was very accurate 
on Madeira, we didn’t get lost even once. We didn’t even need to use the app during the first hike of the day, but the 
coastal hike was more complicated since we were hiking on parts of different trails. We noticed only one proper wooden 
post when we reached the crossing between Vereda da Boca do Risco and Vereda do Larano (the first viewpoint with an ocean 
view).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RB3 Vereda da Vargem called Banana route, very short, perfect for a walk with small kids.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/DSC09044.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/Screenshot 2025-01-26 204523_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restaurant  - 101 Bar. Very friendly owner. We liked the beef sandwich, but the second dish was disappointing (some kind of meat stew), I had to 
leave half of the meat as it was tough and felt like very low quality. Very cheap, but no prices listed anywhere. We paid 
less than 20 euros for both of us, including two mains and beverages.
Address: ER101, Sitio da Igreja, ER101 39, 9270-013 Achadas da Cruz, Portugal
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/20241030_154900_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bakery - Padaria Rodripan, A very small bakery located in someone’s house. Very tasty and cheap, offering a few different 
types of pastries as well as bread, including a soft, sweet one that we bought for our hike the next day. Highly recommended, 
but expect a very basic seating area with simple plastic chairs.                                                      &lt;br /&gt;
Address: Rua da Terra Coimeira, Santa, 9270-093, Porto Moniz, Portugal
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/20241030_163145_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Porto Moniza parking, free parking on a lawn, but a bit hidden. 5-minute walk from the swimming pools, though I’m not 
sure how long it will remain free since all other parking areas were now paid. We also noticed a large information board 
near the construction site of a new parking lot closer to the swimming pools.
Address: R. da Escola Velha 32, 9270-095 Porto Moniz, Portugal
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day3/20241030_170310_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.portomoniz.pt/pt/&quot;&gt;Natural Swimming Pools&lt;/a&gt; – €3 entry fee. Nice swimming pools, but the water was very cold! 
The sunset happens early due to the mountains, so we arrived too late to fully enjoy the sun and didn’t stay long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/03/Day3/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/03/Day3/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>hike</category>
        
        <category>Madeira</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Madeira Adventure: Day 2 – coastal hike and walking on the surface of another planet</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2025/02/Day-1/&quot;&gt;The first day&lt;/a&gt; was already intense, but for the second, we planned even more: two 
dramatically different hikes—the rugged, barren landscapes of The Dragon’s Tail and the lush, coastal beauty of Vereda 
do Larano. The first one offered a feeling of being on another planet, especially with the rising sun that made the 
colors of the landscape truly spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were advised to leave Funchal before 8:00 AM to avoid traffic. Solid advice, as parents drop off their kids at schools 
in the center of Funchal, which in combination with people getting to their workplace gets really busy. We arrived 
at an empty São Lourenço parking lot around 8:10 AM, but by the time we finished the hike at 11:00 AM, 
cars were parked up to 1.5 km away from the start of the hike, reaching another big parking lot close to the Resort Spa &amp;amp; Marina hotel. 
We always made it a point to do the most famous hikes first thing in the morning to avoid crowds and parking issues. That day, not 
only was parking much easier, but the number of people we encountered on the way back was drastically higher. It was 
surreal to start the hike with almost no one around and then finish with a line of people going the opposite direction. When we started 
our hike, there were already a few people coming back, they had surely gone there to see the sunrise. We once hiked up &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2018/07/AnnapurnaPoonHill/&quot;&gt;Poon Hill&lt;/a&gt;
in the dark and on an empty stomach to see the sunrise, but learned this isn’t for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08772.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ponta de São Lourenço peninsula is called the Dragon’s Tail because of its shape, especially when seen from above. 
The morning sun was amazing—the colors were warm, and the place was unbelievably quiet. That day, there was 
almost no wind, and the ocean looked very calm. We particularly liked the red-colored, iron-rich volcanic rock called 
basalt and the stark landscape devoid of vegetation, which made this place look surreal. The contrast between the red, 
black, and yellowish rocks and the blue ocean in this area makes the landscape even more unique. During the hike, we also 
observed boats coming to the nearby bays and fishing nets used by local fishermen. This area is known for its rich marine 
biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08778.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08784.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08792.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08790.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good shoes are definitely a must, as the path is rocky, especially toward the end, where it becomes more demanding. After 
passing the café, the last stretch climbs steeply uphill, with wires to hold onto. However, many of these wires were rusty 
and therefore dangerous, and large sections of the path was broken and in poor condition. Additionally, the wire used 
to assist with the climb was broken or missing in many places, with some sections having fallen or frayed, leaving sharp 
bits sticking out that could easily cut your hands. The challenging trail conditions make the café you’ll encounter 
even more appealing, as it stands like a little green oasis surrounded by palm trees. Great stop for everyone that 
needs a coffee break or grab something sweet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08824.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08838_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very end of the trail there is a viewpoint where the protective fence was damaged. We noticed several people 
stepping beyond it to the very edge to snap better pictures, which struck us as quite irresponsible given the steep drop. 
One downside of hiking so early during this time of year was that the peninsula’s tip—known as the “Dragon’s Tail”—was 
barely visible from this viewpoint due to the sharp sunlight shining directly into our eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08828.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08829.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08841.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived in Madeira the same week that the government started applying fees (October 28, 2024) to the most stunning 
trails, including this one. We bought our tickets online, but when we arrived shortly after 8 AM, there was an older 
man with paper tickets getting ready for the day. After our hike, a small queue had formed with people trying to buy 
tickets with cash, and two additional younger park rangers were checking them. I hope this money will be used to renovate 
the trails and make them safer, as this one was in bad shape, with broken wooden boards in several places. According to 
the government’s statement, all profits from the new tourist fee will go toward trail maintenance, cleaning, and preservation 
efforts. With Madeira experiencing a rise in tourism, this change was really necessary. The number of people we passed on 
the way back to the car was remarkable—the highest during our whole stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08845_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/20241029_104400_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miradouro da Ponta do Rosto was our next stop since it is located just a couple hundred meters from the road leaving 
the PR8 hike. It gave us a great overview of the part of the hike we just did, from another angle. We could see 
dramatic cliffs with colorful volcanic rock formations. Ponta de São Lourenço is one of Madeira’s must-visit 
hikes, offering a completely different experience from the island’s lush levada trails. I really enjoyed this walk with 
truly mind-blowing scenery! This easternmost point of Madeira Island is just unreal and a must-see for everyone visiting. 
I was very happy that we didn’t arrive too late and could quickly move on to our next goal for the day: a longer coastal 
hike to Porto da Cruz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08855.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a short car ride and passing Caniçal, we parked on the ER109 road near the old tunnel, where we started with Levada 
do Caniçal. We were following Organic Maps because we hadn’t seen any trail signs next to the road. First, the path 
passed many houses, and we admired pomegranate trees and hydrangeas that still had nice colors if growing in the shade. 
From the very beginning, we followed a small levada. Once we reached the local road, we had to look for a sharp turn to 
the left, which was luckily marked on a stone pointing to Vereda da Boca do Risco. The first few kilometers led close to 
fields where local people grow their crops and vegetables. Next, the path entered the forest, where we saw goats running 
around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/20241029_121957.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/20241029_122550_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08862.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/20241029_122633_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forest became denser, the path steeper and rockier. We passed only a few people and a trail runner before reaching 
the top. When the ocean view opened, and we reached Vereda do Larano, the landscape changed dramatically. We were now 
walking along a steep slope, but luckily, small trees growing there created a feeling of protection. This part of the hike 
was definitely more crowded but not to the point that it would negatively affect our experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/20241029_130057_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08884.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08882.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most exposed parts, there was a wire fence. It got quite windy, but we could admire stunning cliffs for most of the 
hike, so it was definitely worth exploring this area. Also, the rocks next to the trail were covered with numerous succulents. 
We mostly know these from garden centers, so seeing them thrive on the rugged, nearly vertical rocks beside us was 
unexpected—a beautiful reminder of nature’s resilience. At one point, we 
even noticed majestic Ponta de São Lourenço peninsula far in a distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08913.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08894.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After passing the rusty-looking cable car near Porto da Cruz, we followed the road for a moment where many cars were parked 
as most people start their hike here and return to the same place (out and back variant of the hike). Next, we turned onto a path leading through 
fields and a nearby hill to admire the view of the city (marked as the only dashed line near the coast in Organic maps app). 
It’s also possible to just walk along the road, but it is longer 
and less safe. Finally, we reached the black sand and pebble beach and followed the coastline until the city center. Below, 
you can see in the photo Penha de Águia towering over the city. This volcanic rock formation clearly dominates the landscape, 
standing at almost 600m in height! It was a very diverse hike, starting with dirt paths, forested sections, and finally reaching 
a dramatic cliffside walk. It was relatively easy but had some narrow and exposed areas—not for those really afraid of 
heights!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08928.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/20241029_151649.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it was time for a proper meal after this exhausting day. Since there was only one available Bolt driver, taking a 
normal taxi back to our car was now the cheaper option. We were happy with this decision despite the extra cost because it 
allowed us to complete a longer hike without repeating any part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we still had some time, we decided to finish the day at Miradouro do Pico do Facho, just a little over 1 km from 
our car, where we could admire the view of Cristiano Ronaldo International Airport. I was shocked in the morning when I 
realized that, at one point, we were driving underneath the airport runway! Madeira Airport has a unique elevated runway 
extension, supported by large concrete pillars, allowing vehicles to pass 
underneath. This extension was built to accommodate larger planes and improve safety, as the original runway was quite 
short and challenging for landings. The road that passes beneath is part of the VR1 highway, making it a really cool 
experience for drivers. Miradouro do Pico do Facho was a peaceful spot to sit and relax, surrounded by large cactuses. 
There were also restrooms and a small snack bar, though it was closing when we arrived after 5 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08943.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08947.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we’ll explore Madeira’s West Coast and natural pools in Porto Moniz so stayed tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ifcn.madeira.gov.pt/pt/atividades-de-natureza/percursos-pedestres-recomendados/percursos-pedestres-recomendados.html&quot;&gt;Official website&lt;/a&gt; 
to check if hiking trails are open after the wildfires that occurred during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tickets for paid hiking trails can be bought online &lt;a href=&quot;https://simplifica.madeira.gov.pt/services/78-82-259&quot;&gt;on this website.&lt;/a&gt;
From January 1, 2025, non-residents will need to pay to hike on over 30 routes managed by the Institute of Forests and 
Nature Conservation (ICNF) in Madeira. These are basically all hikes marked as PR.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ponta de São Lourenço ‘The Dragon’s Tail’ – 7.5 km, 2h30min. This hike already had an entrance fee of 1 euro before the 
most recent changes. Looking at our hike and the official map now, I wonder if the last part after the bar is even an 
official trail—maybe that’s why it was not properly maintained. However, there was no sign or information indicating that 
we shouldn’t continue, at least none that we noticed. We just followed a well-visible path to the end, deliberately skipping 
the restaurant since we didn’t have time for an extra break.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://visitmadeira.com/en/what-to-do/nature-seekers/activities/hiking/pr-8-vereda-da-ponta-de-sao-lourenco/&quot;&gt;PR8&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://visitmadeira.com/media/bnpngpg0/pr8-vereda-da-ponta-de-sao-lourenc-o.jpg&quot;&gt;a detailed summary of the hike&lt;/a&gt; can be
found on official websites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/Screenshot 2025-01-26 204122.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/20241029_081142_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to get here by 113 bus from Funchal, see schedule below (photo from the bus stop at São Lourenço parking).
Overall, the path is well maintained in the main section but not at the beginning, where many wooden boards are missing 
or broken, and not after passing the café (still questionable whether this is part of the official hike).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08771.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08851.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Miradouro da Ponta do Rosto - small parking area, but people come and go quickly, so finding a spot for a short 10-minute 
stop is usually not a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Levada do Caniçal - Vereda da Boca do Risco - Vereda do Larano - Porto da Cruz – 13.44km, 3h30min
Taxi back to the car 18euro, 11km ride (only one available car on &lt;a href=&quot;https://bolt.eu/en/support/articles/115003024753/&quot;&gt;Bolt app&lt;/a&gt; 
but more expensive, 24euro). We left the car at: P6MP+44 Machico, Portugal&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/Screenshot 2025-01-26 204224_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/DSC08873.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During our travels, we always use Organic Maps: Offline Hike, Bike, Trails, and Navigation app, which was very accurate 
on Madeira—we didn’t get lost even once. We didn’t even need to use the app during the first hike of the day, but the 
coastal hike was more complicated since we were hiking on parts of different trails. We noticed only one proper wooden 
post when we reached the crossing between Vereda da Boca do Risco and Vereda do Larano (the first viewpoint with an ocean 
view).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Restaurant A Pipa - restaurant &amp;amp; bar with big portions, clean, and tasty food. About 20 euro per person including drinks.
Address: Casas proximas, 9225-050 Porto da Cruz, Portugal&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/20241029_160617_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day2/20241029_160626_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/02/Day2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/02/Day2/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>hike</category>
        
        <category>Madeira</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Przygoda na Maderze: Dzień 1 – Wyzwania na drodze, obiekt UNESCO</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Po naszej pierwszej nocy w &lt;a href=&quot;/pl/podroze/2025/01/Funchal-PL/&quot;&gt;Funchal&lt;/a&gt;, byliśmy gotowi, aby zacząć zwiedzać Maderę 
samochodem! Jednak, gdy zobaczyłam, gdzie zaparkowany był nasz wynajęty samochód (na jednej z najbardziej stromych ulic w 
pobliżu naszego apartamentu), przez chwilę ogarnęła mnie panika. Czy w ogóle uda mi się stamtąd wyjechać? Na szczęście 
udało się, głównie dlatego, że była to ulica jednokierunkowa i miałam wystarczająco dużo miejsca przed samochodem, aby po 
prostu skręcić kierownicą i od razu wyjechać z miejsca parkingowego bez dodatkowych manewrów.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Przeczytałam wiele historii o prowadzeniu samochodu na Maderze: o stromych ulicach, nieprzewidywalnych ostrych zakrętach, 
spotkaniach z dużymi autobusami w drodze na punkty widokowe oraz o niezwykle trudnej sytuacji parkingowej w Funchal. Nie 
spodziewałam się jednak, że to ostre światło słoneczne okaże się największym wyzwaniem, zwłaszcza przy wyjeździe z tunelu, 
gdy niskie, jesienne słońce może być wyjątkowo oślepiające. Okulary przeciwsłoneczne to absolutna konieczność podczas jazdy, 
nawet w pochmurne dni, ponieważ słońce potrafiło pojawić się nagle, dosłownie znikąd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nie doświadczyliśmy ulewnego deszczu, jedynie trochę mgły w drodze powrotnej z lasu Fanal i kilka razy lekkiej mżawki. Pierwszy 
dzień był najbardziej stresujący, ale już od trzeciego naprawdę zaczęłam cieszyć się jazdą po tej wyspie! Najważniejsza 
rada, jaką mogę dać, to zaczynać dzień od najpopularniejszych miejsc, aby uniknąć tłumów i problemów z parkowaniem. 
Odwiedziliśmy również kilka mniej znanych punktów widokowych i mieliśmy je niemal wyłącznie dla siebie, więc zdecydowanie 
warto dodać takie miejsca do naszej listy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;odwiedzone-miejsca&quot;&gt;Odwiedzone miejsca:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cabo Girão Skywalk&lt;/strong&gt; Nazwa „Skywalk” może być nieco myląca, ponieważ jest to raczej platforma widokowa niż prawdziwy 
„spacer w przestworzach”. Mimo to znajduje się ona na najwyższym klifie morskim w Europie! Stojąc na platformie ze 
szklaną podłogą, znajdujemy się 580 metrów nad oceanem. Niestety, szkło jest już mocno porysowane, trudno przez 
nie cokolwiek dostrzec, może właśnie dlatego, nie bałam się po nim chodzić
Podczas innej wycieczki, wędrowaliśmy szlakiem Levada Nova, który dostarczył mi znacznie więcej stresujących chwil. 
Musieliśmy przejść przez bardzo eksponowane, strome zbocza bez żadnych zabezpieczeń, to było dla mnie dużo większe wyzwanie 
niż Skywalk!
Z punktu widokowego rozpościera się panorama na wybrzeże, Fajãs de Cabo Girão (małe uprawne tereny u podnóża klifu, 
patrz zdjęcie poniżej), Câmara de Lobos, a nawet centrum Funchal w oddali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08610.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capela de Nossa Senhora de Fátima&lt;/strong&gt; Sama kaplica jest niewielka, ale bardzo zadbana. Nie było tam tłumów, więc to idealne 
miejsce na spokojny odpoczynek. Widok na dolinę São Vicente, Ocean Atlantycki, wzgórza i okoliczne wioski był oszałamiający. 
Dzień był pochmurny, ale w pewnym momencie chmury się rozstąpiły, a promienie słońca przepięknie oświetliły fragmenty 
wzgórz, tworząc spektakularny krajobraz!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08616.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08619.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08631.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08632.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zwróciliśmy uwagę na tradycyjny tarasowy system uprawy na Maderze, zwany „poios”. Ludzie budują tarasy na stromych 
zboczach, aby stworzyć płaskie powierzchnie do uprawy. Podtrzymywane przez kamienne mury, zapobiegają erozji gleby i 
pozwalają maksymalnie wykorzystać ograniczoną przestrzeń. Podobne rozwiązania widziałam w północnej Portugalii. Słynne 
lewady, wąskie kanały nawadniające, dostarczają wodę na te tarasy i rozprowadzają ją po całej uprawie. Dzięki temu 
systemowi można tu uprawiać winogrona, banany, bataty, marakuje, papaje i wiele innych owoców oraz warzyw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08621.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miradouro Véu da Noiva&lt;/strong&gt; Nazwa „Véu da Noiva” oznacza „Welon Panny Młodej”, ponieważ wodospad przypomina delikatny ślubny 
welon spływający po skałach. Dawna droga przybrzeżna prowadząca do wodospadu została zniszczona przez osunięcia ziemi, więc 
punkt widokowy to jedyne miejsce, z którego można go podziwiać. Droga za punktem widokowym jest zablokowana betonowymi 
blokami, aby nikt przez nią nie przechodził.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08641.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jak w wielu miejscach na Maderze, mogliśmy również tutaj podziwiać spektakularne fale rozbijające się o brzeg i głęboki 
błękit oceanu. Po deszczu, gdy wody jest więcej, wodospad wygląda jeszcze bardziej imponująco!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08636.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Água d’Alto Waterfall (przydrożny wodospad)&lt;/strong&gt; Minęliśmy ten wodospad w drodze do Seixal i planowaliśmy zatrzymać się przy
nim wracając, ale ostatecznie wybraliśmy inną trasę powrotną do Funchal i już tutaj nie wróciliśmy. Przejeżdżając obok wodospadu,
zauważyliśmy, że woda spływała dość obficie, ale słyszeliśmy, że jego moc zależy w dużej mierze od ostatnich opadów. Czasami 
jest znacznie mniejszy, a nawet całkowicie wysycha w suchej porze roku. Innym razem, ze względu na swoją siłę, powoduje 
nawet tymczasowe zamknięcie drogi. Warto się tu zatrzymać, bo można podejść naprawdę blisko wodospadu i mieć go niemal na 
wyciągnięcie ręki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Praia do Seixal (Czarna Plaża)&lt;/strong&gt; Google Maps wskazywało, że droga do głównego parkingu była zamknięta, więc zaparkowaliśmy 
przy Estrada Santo Antão, gdzie szybko znaleźliśmy oznaczenia prowadzące na strome schody w dół na plażę. Po drodze 
zatrzymaliśmy się w Mercearia Amanhecer i kupiliśmy kilka bułek w piekarni, żeby zjeść je na plaży. Nie spodziewałam się 
jednak, że zobaczę tak dużą liczbę karaluchów w drodze na plażę. W życiu widziałam ich tylko kilka, a ścieżka prowadząca 
na plażę była pełna tych martwych insektów (szczególnie widocznych w drodze powrotnej po schodach). Wiem, że to jedne z 
najczęstszych owadów na Maderze, ale nie przepadam za tymi dużymi, szybko poruszającymi się insektami.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moje pierwsze wrażenie na plaży to rozczarowanie, wydawała się zdecydowanie mniejsza i zupełnie inna niż na zdjęciach w 
Internecie. Udało mi się jednak zrobić kilka ładnych zdjęć i to tylko potwierdza, że wszystko zależy od perspektywy i 
filtrów, które sprawiają, że to miejsce wygląda znacznie lepiej w sieci niż w rzeczywistości.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08649.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Na plaży wiele osób było ładnie ubranych, pozując do zdjęć na Instagrama. Gdy robiliśmy własne, zaskoczyła nas fala, która 
nie wyglądała na wysoką, ale zdołała zalać całą plażę, mocząc nasze buty pozostawione przy skałach. Ledwo zdążyliśmy je 
złapać, zanim zostały porwane przez ocean! Na szczęście plecaki były na skałach i pozostały suche. Lepiej jednak zostawić 
rzeczy z dala od mokrej części piasku, bo byliśmy tam już dobre 15 minut, zanim pojawiła się ta jedna, dużo większa fala. 
Po tym incydencie, przez resztę popołudnia chodziliśmy w mokrych butach po lesie Fanal, gdzie temperatura wynosiła 12°C. 
Naprawdę zdziwiłam się, że nie skończyło się to przeziębieniem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08659.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_122812_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mimo wszystko połączenie czarnego wulkanicznego piasku i bujnej zieleni było spektakularne. Na wyspie rzadko można znaleźć 
plaże z drobnym piaskiem, większość jest kamienista, dlatego mimo wszystko polecam się tu zatrzymać.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08688.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08677.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_122535_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Restauracja Las Caraibas&lt;/strong&gt; Zatrzymaliśmy się tutaj na posiłek, czekając, aż nasze buty trochę wyschną przed wyruszeniem 
do lasu Fanal. Lokalizacja tego miejsca jest przepiękna, widok na ocean i fale był cudowny! Atmosfera w restauracji była 
spokojna, a taras bardzo przytulny. Jedzenie okazało się pyszne, spróbowaliśmy burgera, szaszłyków z kurczaka i sernika 
z marakui, który był bardzo delikatny i kremowy. Warto spróbować! Ceny były rozsądne, a obsługa bardzo miła.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_135455_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_142518_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Las Fanal (Szlak Vereda do Fanal PR13)&lt;/strong&gt; 
Zdecydowaliśmy się odwiedzić Las Fanal po południu, mimo że słyszeliśmy, iż słynna mgła pojawia się zazwyczaj rano. Podczas 
lunchu w Seixal zauważyliśmy, że szczyty gór nadal były pokryte chmurami, co podobno również zwiększa szansę na wystąpienie
mgły. Po dotarciu na miejsce nie zauważyliśmy żadnej mgły, więc byłam dość rozczarowana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08695.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jednak po około 15 minutach marszu mgła zaczęła się pojawiać. Mieliśmy wrażenie, jakby chmury zbliżały się do nas, a wiatr 
się wzmógł. Gdy dotarliśmy na pobliskie wzgórze, chmury nagle się rozstąpiły, odsłaniając zapierający dech w piersiach 
widok na ocean! Byłam całkowicie zaskoczona, po tak długiej jeździe nie spodziewałam się zobaczyć oceanu z tego miejsca. Skręcone, 
porośnięte mchem drzewa tworzyły idealne tło do surrealistycznych zdjęć. Wiele osób ubrało się w jaskrawe kolory, 
które świetnie kontrastowały z mgłą i kolorystyką tego miejsca. Była tam nawet kobieta w sukni ślubnej, pozująca do zdjęć. 
Na łąkach spowitych mgłą pasło się mnóstwo krów. Niektóre drzewa mają ponad 500 lat! Są to drzewa wiecznie zielone, więc 
Las Fanal zachowuje swój niepowtarzalny wygląd przez cały rok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08731.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08752.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_161725_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08770.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08762.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08708.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_153842_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nasz pierwszy dzień na Maderze był intensywną mieszanką ekscytacji i wyzwań, od pokonywania stromych dróg i nieprzewidywalnych 
warunków jazdy po odkrywanie zapierających dech w piersiach punktów widokowych i cudów natury. Pomimo kilku stresujących 
momentów, jak niemal utrata butów przez niespodziewaną falę na plaży Seixal, już wtedy byliśmy oczarowani dzikim pięknem 
Madery. A to był dopiero początek!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Przed nami były jeszcze cztery dni pełne niezwykłych przygód. W kolejnym wpisie zabierzemy Was na dwa zupełnie różne szlaki: 
surowy, pustynny krajobraz podczas marszu przez półwysep św. Wawrzyńca oraz nadmorski szlak Vereda do Larano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drogi i poruszanie się po Maderze:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staraliśmy się korzystać z głównych autostrad na Maderze, które łączą różne części wyspy i przecinają ją z południa na 
północ. Dzięki temu unikaliśmy utknięcia na bardzo wąskich i trudniejszych drogach. Choć pokonywaliśmy większą liczbę 
kilometrów, było to ogólnie szybsze rozwiązanie niż wybieranie krótszych, ale bardziej zawiłych tras. Duża liczba tuneli 
na wyspie zdecydowanie usprawnia podróżowanie! Byliśmy też świadkami wypadku, który wydarzył się tuż przed nami na autostradzie. 
Zjazdy i odcinki dołączania się do ruchu 
na autostradach są tam bardzo krótkie, więc nie można dojechać do końca pasa, jak jesteśmy do tego przyzwyczajeni. Często 
trzeba zatrzymać się w połowie, ponieważ druga część pasa to jednocześnie zjazd dla samochodów opuszczających autostradę. 
To właśnie w takich miejscach najczęściej dochodzi do kolizji, warto o tym pamiętać. Zwierzęta na drodze oraz spadające 
skały mogą również stanowić zagrożenie. Na bardzo ostrych zakrętach często montowane 
są lustra, warto z nich korzystać, aby zwiększyć widoczność i bezpieczeństwo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parkowanie na Maderze:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:SkyBlue&quot;&gt;Niebieska linia&lt;/span&gt; oznacza strefę płatnego parkowania.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:Gold&quot;&gt;Żółta linia&lt;/span&gt; oznacza zakaz parkowania.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:Gainsboro&quot;&gt;Biała linia&lt;/span&gt; oznacza darmowy parking, chyba że zawiera literkę „M”, wtedy miejsce jest zarezerwowane tylko dla mieszkańców.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cabo Girão Skywalk&lt;br /&gt;
Położony tuż przy głównej drodze ER101, prowadzącej do Funchal. Wstęp kosztuje 2€, płatność możliwa online lub w automacie 
biletowym (gotówką lub kartą). Dedykowany parking jest bardzo mały, a część miejsc zarezerwowana jest dla autobusów, więc 
prawdopodobnie trzeba będzie zaparkować wzdłuż drogi prowadzącej do Santuário de Nossa Senhora de Fátima. My dotarliśmy 
około godziny 10:00 i było już bardzo tłoczno. Na szczęście był to jedyny punkt widokowy podczas naszego pobytu, który 
wydawał się nadmiernie zatłoczony. To najbardziej ruchliwe miejsce, jakie odwiedziliśmy. Punkt widokowy jest dostępny 
także dla osób poruszających się na wózkach inwalidzkich.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Capela de Nossa Senhora de Fátima&lt;br /&gt;
Parking znajduje się blisko schodów i tuż przy głównej drodze. To świetny przystanek między Seixal a Funchal. Ponieważ 
miejsce nie jest tak turystyczne jak inne punkty widokowe, można tu zaznać ciszy i spokoju. Widok na góry jest przepiękny.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Miradouro Véu da Noiva&lt;br /&gt;
Położony tuż przy drodze ER101, zaraz za tunelem, jadąc z São Vicente w kierunku Seixal. Znajdują się tu dwa parkingi, 
sklep z pamiątkami, toalety oraz stoiska z przekąskami. Przed południem nie było tłoczno, ale zatrzymują się tu autobusy, 
Czy były puste, czy zatłoczone, zależało w dużej mierze od szczęścia. Sytuacja potrafiła zmieniać się co 5–10 minut.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Las Caraibas Restaurant&lt;br /&gt;
Dotarliśmy tu około 14:00 i musieliśmy czekać w kolejce około 20 minut, aby otrzymać stolik. Parking dostępny jest wzdłuż 
drogi lub bezpośrednio przed restauracją. Główne danie z napojem kosztowało nieco poniżej 20€ za osobę.
Adres: Rua do Porto do Laje 15, Fajã da Parreira, 9270-122 Seixal, Portugalia.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Las Fanal &lt;br /&gt;
Dotarliśmy do Lasu Fanal z Seixal, przejeżdżając przez Ribeira da Janela. Znaleźliśmy ogromny parking tuż obok szlaku, 
więc nie mieliśmy problemu z miejscem. Początkowo planowaliśmy wracać tą samą trasą, aby uniknąć serpentyn, ale ponieważ 
czułam się już pewniej za kierownicą, wybraliśmy drogę ER209 do Funchal. Na płaskowyżu ponownie przejeżdżaliśmy przez mgłę, 
ale na szczęście ruch był niewielki. Gdy droga zaczęła prowadzić w dół, zakręty stawały się coraz ostrzejsze, słońce wyszło 
zza chmur, a widoki na ocean były cudowne! Bardzo podobała nam się ta trasa, z wyjątkiem ostatnich kilku kilometrów wzdłuż 
ER222 przed dołączeniem do głównej autostrady do Funchal, to bardzo ruchliwy odcinek, przebiegający przez teren mieszkalny.
Nawet latem może być tutaj chłodno z powodu wysokości (~1150 m n.p.m.). Podczas naszej wizyty temperatura wynosiła 12°C, 
więc polar i wodoodporna kurtka bardzo się przydały. Dobre buty to konieczność, ponieważ niektóre szlaki mogą być błotniste. 
Nawet gdyby nasze buty nie zostały zalane na czarnej plaży, tutaj i tak zostałyby całkowicie przemoczone. Niektóre fragmenty 
szlaków przypominały nasiąkniętą wodą gąbkę, więc przydałyby się naprawdę dobre górskie buty albo kalosze. Naszym zamiarem 
był dłuższy spacer wokół Lasu Fanal po szlakach, które widnieją w aplikacji Organic Maps, ale było zbyt zimno na wędrówkę 
w przemoczonych butach, a dodatkowo błota było naprawdę dużo. Przy parkingu znajduje się toaleta, ale budynek wygląda 
tak źle, że naprawdę zastanawiałam się, czy powinnam tam wchodzić, podobne reakcje widziałam na twarzach innych turystów. 
Wnętrze przypominało opuszczony bunkier. Mam nadzieję, że po wprowadzeniu opłat turystycznych takie obiekty zostaną odnowione.
Nasz spacer liczył 3.5 km.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/Screenshot 2025-01-26 203915.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inne opcje w tej okolicy, których nie sprawdziliśmy:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://visitmadeira.com/en/what-to-do/nature-seekers/activities/hiking/pr-13-vereda-do-fanal/&quot;&gt;Vereda do Fanal PR13&lt;/a&gt; – malowniczy szlak z Assobiadores (10,8 km, średni poziom trudności), kończący się w Fanal, 
ale nie będący pętlą wokół Lasu Fanal.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://visitmadeira.com/en/what-to-do/nature-seekers/activities/hiking/pr-14-levada-dos-cedros/&quot;&gt;Levada dos Cedros PR14&lt;/a&gt; Szlak 7.2km, który zaczyna się przy drodze ER209 w Lesie Fanal i kończy się przy tej samej 
drodze, ale w okolicy Curral Falso. Między punktem początkowym a końcowym tego szlaku jest dodatkowo 4,4 km odległości.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2025/02/Dzien-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2025/02/Dzien-1/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugalia</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>Madera</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Madeira Adventure: Day 1 – Driving Challenges and first UNESCO site</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After our first night in &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2025/01/Funchal/&quot;&gt;Funchal&lt;/a&gt;, we were ready to explore Madeira by car! However, 
when I saw where our rented car was parked (on one of the steepest streets near our apartment), I had 
a brief moment of panic. Would I even be able to drive out of there? Luckily, I managed to, but only because it was a one-way 
street, and there was enough space in front of the car to simply turn the steering wheel and get out of the parking spot 
immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had read many stories about driving in Madeira: how steep the streets can be, the unpredictable sharp turns, encountering 
big buses on the way to viewpoints, and the incredibly difficult parking situation in Funchal. However, I wasn’t expecting 
the sharp sunlight to be the most problematic weather condition. Especially when exiting a tunnel, the low winter-sun can 
be particularly blinding. Having sunglasses ready at all times is a must.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t experience heavy rain, only some mist on the way from Fanal Forest and light drizzle a few times. The first 
day was the most stressful, but starting from day three, I actually enjoyed driving there! The most important tip I would 
give to everyone is to start your day with the most popular destinations to avoid crowds and parking issues. There were a 
few viewpoints that were less popular, and we had them almost to ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;places-we-visited&quot;&gt;Places we visited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cabo Girão Skywalk&lt;/strong&gt; The name “Skywalk” might be a bit misleading, as it’s more of a viewing platform than a true skywalk 
experience. However, it’s the highest sea cliff in Europe! While standing on the glass-floored platform, you will be 580 
meters above the ocean. Unfortunately, the glass floor is very scratched, so you can’t see through it well—perhaps that’s 
why I wasn’t scared to walk on it. On another day, we hiked on Levada Nova, which gave me a few really stressful moments while passing very exposed steep slopes 
without any protection, that was more of skywalk experience :) From the viewpoint, you can see the coastline, Fajãs de Cabo Girão (the small cultivated land at the cliff’s base—see 
photo below), Câmara de Lobos, and even Funchal in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08610.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capela de Nossa Senhora de Fátima&lt;/strong&gt;  The chapel itself is very small but well-maintained. It wasn’t crowded when we 
visited—a perfect spot for a quiet break. The view over São Vicente Valley, the Atlantic Ocean, hills, and villages was 
breathtaking. It was a cloudy day, but for a moment, the clouds opened up, allowing rays of light to highlight parts of the 
hills, creating a spectacular scene!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08616.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08619.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08631.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08632.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We noticed the traditional terraced farming system used in Madeira, called “poios.” People built these terraces on the 
steep hillsides to create flat land for agriculture. Supported by stone walls, they help prevent soil erosion and maximize 
the use of limited land. I have seen the same system in the northern part of Portugal. The famous levadas distribute water 
across these terraces—narrow water channels that act as an irrigation system. Grapes, bananas, sweet potatoes, passion 
fruit, papaya, and many more fruits and vegetables are cultivated using this system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08621.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miradouro Véu da Noiva&lt;/strong&gt; The name “Véu da Noiva” means “Bride’s Veil” because the waterfall 
resembles a delicate bridal veil flowing down the rocks. The original coastal road leading to the waterfall was damaged 
by landslides, so the viewpoint is the best place to admire it from a distance. The road beyond the viewpoint is blocked by concrete block,
not allowing anyone to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08641.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in many places, we could admire dramatic waves crashing against the shore and the deep 
blue ocean. After rainfall, when the water flow is stronger, the waterfall looks even more impressive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08636.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Água d’Alto Waterfall (Roadside Waterfall)&lt;/strong&gt; We passed this waterfall on the way to Seixal and planned to stop on the 
way back, but we ended up taking another road to Funchal and never passed it again. When we first saw it, a lot of water 
was running down, but we heard that its flow depends on recent weather conditions. Sometimes, it’s significantly reduced
or even stops, while at other times, more water rushes down. This can even lead to temporary road 
closures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Praia do Seixal (Black Sand Beach)&lt;/strong&gt; Google Maps indicated that the road to the main parking lot was closed, so we 
parked on Estrada Santo Antão, where we quickly found signs pointing to steep stairs leading to the beach. On the way 
down, we stopped by Mercearia Amanhecer and bought some pastries to enjoy on the beach. One thing I wasn’t expecting was 
the sheer number of cockroaches. I haven’t seen many in my life—just two in Asia—but 
this path leading to the beach was full of dead ones, especially visible while walking back up the stairs. I know these 
are some of the most common insects on Madeira, but I’m not great with fast-moving, crunchy bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first impression of the beach was disappointment—it looked dirty, small, and nothing like the photos online. I still 
managed to take some nice pictures, but everything depends on perspective and filters that make this place look much cooler 
on the internet. That said, there were very few places on Madeira that looked worse in reality than in photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08649.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite a few people were dressed up nicely, taking Instagram photos. While taking our own, we were surprised by a wave that 
didn’t look high but somehow managed to wash over the entire beach, soaking our shoes next to the rocks. We barely managed 
to grab them before they were swept into the ocean! Luckily, our backpacks were on the rocks and stayed dry. However, we 
ended up walking in wet shoes later that afternoon in Fanal Forest, where the temperature was 12°C. I was really surprised 
we didn’t get sick. We had already been on the beach for 20 minutes, so stay alert—big waves can appear 
at any moment! The waves can be strong sometimes, making it a popular spot for surfers, and we noticed a few trying to 
surf during our visit. It’s a perfect stop after visiting Miradouro Véu da Noiva since it’s a short drive away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08659.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_122812_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combination of black volcanic sand and lush green surroundings was truly spectacular though. It’s rare to see a 
beach with fine sand, as most beaches on this island are rocky, so I would still recommend to stop here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08688.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08677.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_122535_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Las Caraibas Restaurant&lt;/strong&gt; We ate here while trying to let our shoes dry a bit before heading to Fanal Forest. The 
location is stunning, with an ocean view and great waves. The atmosphere is peaceful, with a cozy terrace. It was the 
first time in my life that I had a meal while admiring such amazing waves. The staff was very friendly, the food was 
great (we tried the burger, chicken, and passion fruit cheesecake—a must!), and the prices were reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_135455_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_142518_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fanal Forest (Vereda do Fanal Hike PR13)&lt;/strong&gt; 
We decided to visit Fanal Forest in the afternoon despite hearing that the famous mist is usually present in the morning. 
While having lunch in Seixal, we noticed that clouds were still covering the mountain peaks, which is apparently also a 
good sign for mist. When we arrived, there was no mist, and I felt disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08695.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after about 15 minutes of walking, 
the mist started to roll in. It felt as though the clouds were approaching us, and the wind picked up.
When we reached a nearby hill, the clouds suddenly opened, revealing a stunning view of the ocean! I was totally 
surprised—we had been driving for so long that I never expected to see the ocean from there. The twisted, moss-covered 
trees create surreal photos, and you can see many people taking pictures in special outfits or even wedding dresses. There 
were also plenty of cows grazing in the misty fields. Some trees are over 500 years old! These are evergreen trees, so 
Fanal looks lush year-round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08731.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08752.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_161725_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08770.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08762.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/DSC08708.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/20241028_153842_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first day in Madeira was an intense mix of excitement and challenges, from navigating the island’s steep roads and 
unexpected driving conditions to discovering breathtaking viewpoints and natural wonders. Despite a few stressful 
moments—like nearly losing our shoes to a rogue wave at Seixal Beach—we were already captivated by Madeira’s wild beauty. 
And this was just the beginning! With four more days ahead, we had even more incredible adventures waiting for us. In the 
next post, we’ll take you on two dramatically different hikes: the rugged, barren landscapes of The Dragon’s Tail and the 
lush, coastal beauty of Vereda do Larano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tried to take the main highways on Madeira, which connect different parts of the island and also cross from South to 
North, to avoid getting stuck on very narrow and more difficult roads. Even though we covered more kilometers, it was 
overall faster than taking the smaller roads. The large number of tunnels makes a huge difference!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We witnessed one accident that happened right in front of us on the highway. The on- and off-ramps are incredibly short, 
so when merging onto the highway, you can’t drive to the end of the lane like we’re used to. Instead, you often have to 
stop halfway because the second part of the lane is also the off-ramp for cars exiting the highway—this is where accidents 
tend to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animals on the road and falling rocks can also be hazards. On very sharp turns, there are often mirrors installed, so be 
sure to use them to make driving easier and safer. If you park in a spot marked with a blue line, you need to pay for it. 
A yellow line means parking is forbidden, and a white line means parking is free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cabo Girão Skywalk
Located close to the ER101 main road leading to Funchal. The entrance fee is €2, payable online or at the ticket machine 
(cash or card). The dedicated parking lot is very small, with part of it reserved for buses, so you’ll likely need to 
park along the road leading to Santuário de Nossa Senhora de Fátima. It was already very crowded when we arrived shortly 
after 10 AM. Luckily, this was the only viewpoint during our stay that felt overly crowded! This was the busiest spot we 
visited. The viewpoint is wheelchair accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Capela de Nossa Senhora de Fátima
There’s parking near the stairs, and it’s close to the main road. It’s a great stop between Seixal and Funchal, and 
since it’s not as touristy as other viewpoints, you’ll get a peaceful experience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Miradouro Véu da Noiva
Located right next to the ER101 main road, just after the tunnel when driving from São Vicente in the direction of Seixal. 
There are two parking lots, a souvenir shop, toilets, and snack stands. It wasn’t crowded before noon, but buses do stop 
here, so the number of tourists can vary. We noticed this pattern at most viewpoints, whether they were empty or crowded 
was often just a matter of luck.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Las Caraibas Restaurant
There was a queue when we arrived around 2 PM, and we had to wait about 20 minutes. Parking is available along the road 
or in front of the restaurant. A main dish with a drink was just below €20 per person.
Address: Rua do Porto do Laje 15 , Fajã da Parreira 9270-122 Seixal PMZ, 9270-120 Seixal, Portugal&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fanal Forest. We reached Fanal Forest from Seixal, passing by Ribeira da Janela. There was a huge parking area next to Fanal Forest, 
so we had no trouble finding a spot. Initially, the plan was to return the 
same way to avoid zigzag roads, but since I felt more comfortable driving, we took the ER209 road to Funchal instead. 
On the plateau, we encountered more mist but luckily very few cars. Once the road started descending, there were more and more sharp 
turns, the sun came out, and the ocean views were stunning! We really enjoyed this drive, except for the last few 
kilometers along the ER222 before joining the main highway to Funchal (very busy, residential area). 
Even in summer, it can be chilly due to the altitude (~1,150m). It was 12°C when we were there, so a fleece and waterproof 
jacket were very handy. Good shoes are a must, as some trails can be muddy. We visited after two rainy days, and it was 
extremely wet—we regretted not having proper waterproof shoes. Since our shoes were already soaked from our small accident 
at Seixal Beach, walking here didn’t make much difference. However, in many places, the water was so deep that small lakes 
had formed along the paths, making it impossible to walk through. The grass around the trails felt like a sponge.
There are no shops or restaurants nearby, so bring your own snacks. There was a toilet building, but it was honestly one 
of the worst public restrooms I’ve ever seen—definitely not a pleasant place to enter.
Our walk was 3.5 km long.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Day1/Screenshot 2025-01-26 203915.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other options in this area of Fanal Forest that we haven’t done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://visitmadeira.com/en/what-to-do/nature-seekers/activities/hiking/pr-13-vereda-do-fanal/&quot;&gt;Vereda do Fanal PR13&lt;/a&gt; – A scenic hike from Assobiadores (10.8 km, moderate) but this one is ending in Fanal but it’s not 
circuit around Fanal Forest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://visitmadeira.com/en/what-to-do/nature-seekers/activities/hiking/pr-14-levada-dos-cedros/&quot;&gt;Levada dos Cedros PR14&lt;/a&gt; this one is 7.2km
trail that starts on the road ER209 Fanal Forest and ends on the same road but in the area of Curral Falso. 4.4km by car
between start and end point of this trail.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/02/Day-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/02/Day-1/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>hike</category>
        
        <category>Madeira</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Funchal – świetny punkt wypadowy do zwiedzania wyspy wiecznej wiosny</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Wybierając miejsce na naszą podróż poślubną, chcieliśmy doświadczyć czegoś wyjątkowego, egzotycznego, ale wciąż w Europie. 
Nasz maluch został pod opieką dziadków, więc po raz pierwszy od dawna mogliśmy podróżować tak, jak przed założeniem rodziny. 
Marzyliśmy o miejscu z zapierającymi dech w piersiach szlakami, pysznym jedzeniem i nieskażoną przyrodą. Madera spełniała 
wszystkie te wymagania pomimo, że wakacje planowaliśmy na przełom października i listopada. Słyszeliśmy świetne opinie o tej portugalskiej wyspie od rodziny i znajomych. Nasz plan był prosty: 
spędzić pierwszą i ostatnią noc podróży w Funchal, urokliwej stolicy wyspy, a pozostałe pięć dni poświęcić na zwiedzanie 
Madery samochodem. Taki plan okazał się strzał w dziesiątkę!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po długim locie potrzebowaliśmy odpoczynku, ale również musieliśmy znaleźć dogodny parking na kolejne dni, gdy będziemy już 
mieli wynajęty samochód. Już podczas pierwszego spaceru do supermarketu zauważyłam, jak niewiarygodnie strome są ulice w tym 
mieście! Na samą myśl o tym, jak będę manewrować po tych wąskich, nachylonych uliczkach, robiło mi się gorąco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pogoda pierwszego dnia na Maderze nie była idealna. Szybko przekonaliśmy się, że to prawda, co wszyscy mówią o kapryśnej aurze na tej
wyspie. Naszym głównym celem na ten dzień była wizyta w słynnym ogrodzie botanicznym &lt;strong&gt;Monte Palace Madeira&lt;/strong&gt;. Po krótkiej 
jeździe z szalonym, lokalnym kierowcą autobusu, z ulgą wysiadłam, aby wreszcie zaczerpnąć świeżego powietrza. Po tych wszystkich 
ostrych zakrętach w ciągu ostatnich 15 minut jazdy, spokojny spacer to coś, czego bardzo potrzebowałam. Przygotujcie się na 
niezłą jazdę wsiadając do lokalnych autobusów bo zaparkowane na poboczach dróg auta zmuszają kierowców do intensywnych manewrów!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W drodze do ogrodu botanicznego minęliśmy &lt;strong&gt;Igreja de Nossa Senhora do Monte&lt;/strong&gt;, urokliwy kościół na wzgórzu. Pomnik przed świątynią 
to posąg cesarza Karola I Habsburga (Karl I), upamiętniający ostatniego cesarza Austro-Węgier. To właśnie tutaj spędził 
ostatnie dni swojego życia i został pochowany w kościele. Na zdjęciu poniżej widać jeszcze mokrą nawierzchnię placu zaraz po 
tym, jak wysiedliśmy z autobusu, zaczęło mocno padać, ale już po chwili wyszło słońce. I właśnie taka zmienna pogoda 
towarzyszyła nam do końca dnia.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_110240_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuż u podnóża schodów prowadzących do kościoła znajduje się jedna z najsłynniejszych atrakcji turystycznych, zjazd wiklinowymi 
saniami. To właśnie tutaj zaczyna się 2-kilometrowy zjazd po stromych ulicach Funchal. Kiedy przechodziliśmy obok tego 
miejsca około 10 rano w niedzielę, nie było jeszcze nikogo obsługującego te sanie, a potem na stronie internetowej znalazłam 
informację że w niedziele zjazdy te się nie odbywają. Tradycyjne pojazdy przypominające sanki wykonane są z wiklinowych 
koszy osadzonych na drewnianych płozach i służą do przewożenia turystów z wioski Monte w dół, do niżej położonych ulic 
Funchal. Trasa ma około 2 kilometry, a prędkość może sięgać nawet 30 km/h. Kierowcy, zwani „Carreiros”, stoją za sankami 
i wykorzystują swoją siłę, równowagę oraz gumowe podeszwy butów, by sterować i kontrolować prędkość podczas zjazdu.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08450.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soczysta zieleń, egzotyczne rośliny i spokojna atmosfera sprawiały, że czuliśmy się jak w tropikalnym lesie deszczowym wchodząc do Monte Palace Madeira. 
Sam Pałac Monte został pierwotnie zbudowany jako luksusowy hotel pod koniec XIX wieku. Jednak z czasem hotel napotkał 
problemy finansowe i ostatecznie został zamknięty w połowie XX wieku. W późnych latach 80. José Berardo (portugalski biznesmen, 
inwestor, kolekcjoner sztuki) zakupił nieruchomość 
i postanowił przekształcić ją w ogród botaniczny i przestrzeń kulturalną. Po transformacji ogrody zostały otwarte dla 
zwiedzających na początku lat 90., prezentując zachwycającą kolekcję egzotycznych roślin, minerałów i sztuki współczesnej.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08565.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08483.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08523.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spędziliśmy około 2,5 godziny spacerując po ogrodzie, choć musieliśmy zrobić kilka przerw, by schronić się przed deszczem. 
Kapryśna pogoda dodała temu miejscu nastrojowego, niemal mistycznego klimatu, co tylko spotęgowało wyjątkowość tej wizyty. 
Ogród oferuje zapierające dech w piersiach panoramiczne widoki na Funchal, zatokę i Ocean Atlantycki. Ale najbardziej 
zaskoczyła mnie wystawa minerałów. Nie spodziewałam się, że zachwycą mnie kamienie, a jednak kreatywna ekspozycja naprawdę 
mnie urzekła. Większość okazów pochodziła z Brazylii, Portugalii i Południowej Afryki, były po prostu przepiękne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_113302_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_113133_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_113038_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oprócz minerałów, w pawilonach prezentowana była także sztuka współczesna, co stanowiło ciekawe uzupełnienie 
naturalnego piękna ogrodu. Część ogrodu inspirowana Azją, z wyrazistymi czerwonymi elementami, wspaniale kontrastowała z 
tłem soczyście zielonego lasu. Kolejną atrakcją był ogród sukulentów, gdzie różnorodne gatunki zostały rozmieszczone w 
niezwykle artystyczny i efektowny sposób.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08539.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08529.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08467.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08553.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08555.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zdecydowaliśmy się wrócić pieszo do Funchal, ponieważ pogoda zaczęła się poprawiać, a my chcieliśmy odkrywać miasto we 
własnym tempie. Wyszliśmy na ulicę znajdującą się poniżej kolejki linowej, obok parkingu przy górnej stacji kolejki. 
Stamtąd, tuż przed cmentarzem skręciliśmy w lewo, kierując się uroczą ścieżką biegnącą za kilkoma domami, aż dotarliśmy do 
ulicy Caminho do Lombo. Droga szybko stała się tak stroma, że nasze łydki zaczęły już po kilku minutach dawać oznaki 
zmęczenia! Podążaliśmy cały czas tą przyjemną dzielnicą mieszkaniową, ale mimo tego że mijaliśmy przystanki autobusowe, 
nigdzie nie było dokładnych rozkładów jazdy i nie zauważyliśmy też ani jednego autobusu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08596.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po pewnym czasie dotarliśmy do Miradouro da Tabaiba, punktu widokowego oferującego fantastyczną panoramę Funchal, zatoki 
i trasy kolejki linowej do Monte. Mówi się, że to jedno z najlepszych miejsc do podziwiania słynnych fajerwerków w sylwestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08598.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kontynuowaliśmy spacer ulicą Caminho do Lombo, przechodząc pod drogą ekspresową. Kolejny odcinek trasy był jedynym, gdzie 
przez około 200 metrów nie było chodnika ani bezpiecznego miejsca dla pieszych, a ostre zakręty sprawiały, że czuliśmy się 
niepewnie. Szybko przetruchtaliśmy ten fragment, żeby jak najszybciej mieć go za sobą. W końcu dotarliśmy do Rua Pedro 
José de Ornelas, ulicy, która bezpiecznie poprowadziła nas w kierunku centrum Funchal. Gdy dotarliśmy do naszego celu, 
czyli portu, mieliśmy za sobą 6 kilometrów marszu i aż 550 metrów zejścia w dół. Wyszło słońce, a widok ogromnych statków 
wycieczkowych i migoczącej wody był absolutnie zachwycający. Zanim poszliśmy na kolację, przeszliśmy przez Parque de 
Santa Catarina, spokojne miejsce w samym środku miasta. To właśnie stamtąd, w oddali zauważyliśmy Muzeum CR7, obowiązkowy punkt dla 
fanów piłki nożnej, z jego słynnym pomnikiem Cristiano Ronaldo przed wejściem. Pomnikiem, który, jak żartują wszyscy, 
zupełnie nie przypomina piłkarza i w pełni się z tym zgadzam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08605.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po tym wymagającym spacerze zasłużyliśmy na porządną kolację w lokalnej restauracji. Nie mogłam się oprzeć i zamówiłam 
jedno z popisowych dań wyspy, pałasza czarnego z bananem. Na początku połączenie smaków wydawało się ciekawe i wyjątkowe, 
ale w miarę jedzenia słodycz banana zaczęła nieco zbyt dominować. Mimo to było to doświadczenie warte spróbowania i był 
to prawdziwy przykład kulinarnej kreatywności Madery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Już podczas tej pierwszej kolacji odkryliśmy również Brisa Maracujá, popularny napój gazowany z dodatkiem prawdziwego 
soku z marakui. Jego orzeźwiający i słodki smak doskonale oddaje tropikalny charakter tej znanej maderskiej owocowej 
specjalności jaką jest marakuja. Później trafiliśmy także na wersję bez cukru, która okazała się zaskakująco smaczna, 
nawet dla kogoś takiego jak ja, kto zwykle nie przepada za napojami typu „light”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_152841_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zdecydowałam się wybrać na wieczorny bieg, żeby jeszcze przed zachodem słońca trochę pozwiedzać miasto. Trudno było znaleźć 
trasę, która nie wiązałaby się z wymagającym podejściem, ale w końcu jako cel obrałam Fortaleza de São João Baptista do Pico. 
Bieg do fortecy był trudny (na szczęście krótki!), bo ulice były naprawdę strome – idealne na solidny trening. Kiedy 
dotarłam na miejsce, okazało się, że forteca nie jest w najlepszym stanie. Część, z której rozciągał się najlepszy widok 
na miasto, była akurat w remoncie, co trochę mnie rozczarowało. Pomimo to, samo wbiegnięcie pod górę dało mi już dużo satysfakcji. 
Choć forteca wyglądała na opuszczoną, to pobliski plac zabaw i kawiarnia tętniły życiem. Stamtąd pobiegłam w stronę portu 
i dalej wzdłuż nabrzeża aż do Forte de São Tiago. Oświetlone ulice i żywa atmosfera na ulicach sprawiły, że ta część biegu była 
szczególnie przyjemna.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_183150_01.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_183451_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jednak po minięciu fortu ulice stały się ciemniejsze i opustoszałe, więc postanowiłam zawrócić. Skierowałam się pod górę 
w stronę naszego apartamentu, mijając po drodze liczne restauracje pełne ludzi rozkoszujących się wieczorem. To była 
idealna końcówka tak pełnego wrażeń dnia, miasto po zmroku ma swój niepowtarzalny charakter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podczas jednego z wieczornych spacerów odwiedziliśmy &lt;strong&gt;Rua de Santa Maria&lt;/strong&gt;, jedną z najstarszych ulic Funchal. W 2010 
roku rząd zainicjował tam projekt „Sztuka Otwartych Drzwi” jako sposób na ożywienie tej części Starego Miasta. Lokalni i 
międzynarodowi artyści zostali zaproszeni do malowania swoich obrazów na drzwiach budynków, zamieniając ulicę w galerię sztuki na świeżym powietrzu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warto przejść się tą ulicą zarówno rano, jak i wieczorem, ponieważ w różnych porach dnia różne miejsca są zamknięte, 
odsłaniając ciekawe malowidła, takie jak Mały Książę, Drzwi Syreny, ukazujące sceny winobrania, historie i kulturę miasta 
Funchal czy obrazy życia morskiego wokół wyspy. Ulica tętni życiem, pełno tu sklepików z pamiątkami, restauracji, kawiarni 
i barów. Wieczorami jest szczególnie gwarno, gdy miejscowi i turyści spotykają się by zjeść kolacje lub wypić drinka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241101_192208_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09549.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funchal można zwiedzać pieszo, taksówką, kolejką linową, a nawet tuk-tukiem. Te trójkołowe pojazdy to popularny i ekologiczny 
sposób na poruszanie się po mieście i jego okolicach, ponieważ z łatwością przemieszczają się wąskimi uliczkami Starego 
Miasta. Tuk-tuki w Funchal są obsługiwane przez różne firmy i kierowców, którzy często oferują swoje usługi jako przewodników, 
pomagając turystom odkrywać najważniejsze atrakcje w okolicy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To świetna opcja dla osób z ograniczoną mobilnością lub dla tych, którym trudno jest spacerować po stromych ulicach miasta. 
Podczas przerwy na punkcie widokowym Lazareto zauważyliśmy starszą parę, która przyjechała tuk-tukiem. Zatrzymali się na około 
pięć minut, a ich kierowca opowiadał im o mieście, zanim ruszyli dalej.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09553.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09545_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forteca Forte de São Tiago, ze swoim charakterystycznym, intensywnie żółtym kolorem, wspaniale kontrastuje z błękitem wód 
Atlantyku i zielonymi wzgórzami Madery. Szczególnie spodobało mi się to miejsce podczas wieczornego biegu, panowała tam 
spokojna atmosfera, idealna do relaksu, podziwiania zachodu słońca oraz obserwowania przypływających statków wycieczkowych 
i kutrów rybackich. W ciągu dnia fort oferuje spektakularne widoki na ocean, miasto i okoliczne góry. W środku znajduje 
się restauracja oferująca wyjątkowe kulinarne doznania, a sam fort wykorzystywany jest także do organizacji wydarzeń, 
wystaw i innych kulturalnych aktywności.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09559.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Byliśmy absolutnie zachwyceni różnorodnością owoców dostępnych w sklepach, nawet w supermarketach, smakowały o wiele 
lepiej niż te, które znamy z Belgii. Sklepy z owocami, zwane „frutaria”, przyciągały naszą uwagę za każdym razem, gdy 
obok nich przechodziliśmy. Naszym ulubionym owocem była lokalna papaja.
Ostatni dzień przeznaczyliśmy na zakupy, a jednym z miejsc, które bardzo chcieliśmy odwiedzić, był &lt;strong&gt;Mercado dos Lavradores&lt;/strong&gt;. 
Ten słynny targ oferuje imponującą gamę egzotycznych owoców, takich jak marakuja, annona (flaszowiec) czy intrygujące 
hybrydy banana z ananasem. Sprzedawcy często oferują degustacje, ale trzeba uważać na ceny, są znacznie wyższe niż gdzie 
indziej, kilkukrotnie wyższe niż na straganach ulicznych czy w frutariach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choć targ cieszy się popularnością wśród mieszkańców, niektóre jego części, szczególnie stoiska z owocami, są bardziej 
nastawione na turystów. Odwiedziliśmy go w sobotę, czyli w jeden z najbardziej ruchliwych dni, kiedy gromadzą się tam zarówno 
lokalni mieszkańcy, jak i turyści. Energia i żywa atmosfera tylko dodawały temu miejscu uroku, mimo tłumów. Stoiska 
prezentowały pięknie ułożone owoce, suszone zioła, papryczki i kwiaty, prawdziwa uczta dla oczu! Dla osób preferujących 
spokojniejsze doświadczenia, lepszym rozwiązaniem może być wizyta rano lub w dzień powszedni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chociaż nie planowaliśmy kupować na tym targu owoców ze względu na wysokie ceny, odkryliśmy, że parter hali to doskonałe 
miejsce na zakup cebulek kwiatowych. Stoiska z kwiatami były wyjątkowo kolorowe, prezentując tropikalne gatunki, takie jak 
chociażby słynna strelicja (rajski ptak). Kobiety ubrane w tradycyjne wielokolorowe, pasiaste sukienki, sprzedające kwiaty, 
wprowadzały do tego miejsca tradycyjny aspekt. Tuż przy wejściu znajdują się na ścianach przepiękne azulejos (tradycyjne 
portugalskie płytki), przedstawiające, jak targ wyglądał w przeszłości, to taka mała lekcja historii dla odwiedzających. 
Jeśli jesteś miłośnikiem ogrodnictwa, koniecznie zajrzyj na parter, cebulki strelicji to niebanalna pamiątka, która przez 
długi czas będzie Ci przypominać o Maderze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09540.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09512.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09535_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jedną z najciekawszych części targu jest strefa z owocami morza. Można tam zobaczyć wiele gatunków ryb, których wcześniej 
ja sama nawet nie widziałam. Gwiazdą tego miejsca jest pałasz czarny, czyli „espada” – głębinowa ryba, która od wieków 
jest podstawą maderskiej kuchni. Jej długie, smukłe ciało, czarna skóra i ostre zęby nadają jej niemal mityczny wygląd. 
Występuje na głębokościach sięgających nawet 1500 metrów w północnym Atlantyku, a poławiana jest przez doświadczonych 
lokalnych rybaków tradycyjnymi metodami. Mimo nietypowego wyglądu, mięso pałasza jest delikatne, białe i łagodne w 
smaku, idealne do wielu pysznych dań – od klasycznej espady z bananem (która próbowałam juz pierwszego dnia) po inne 
kreatywne wariacje dostępne w restauracjach na Maderze. Co ciekawe, pałasz czarny występuje tylko w rejonie Madery 
oraz w pobliżu Japonii.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09526.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09541.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09528.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ostatnie popołudnie spędziłam, odkrywając druga część wybrzeża, kierując się w stronę dzielnicy Câmara de Lobos. Mój bieg tym 
razem zaprowadził mnie do naturalnych basenów Doca do Cavacas. Cała trasa prowadziła łatwym chodnikiem, mijając liczne 
duże hotele z basenami i zapierającymi dech w piersiach widokami na ocean. Wzdłuż głównej i ruchliwej(!) ulicy znajdowały się również 
restauracje i sklepy z pamiątkami. Naturalne baseny Doca do Cavacas były mniejszą wersją tych, które odwiedziliśmy w Porto
Moniz. Po drodze minęłam też kolejny kompleks odkrytych basenów o nazwie „Ponta Gorda Lido.” Oba miejsca miały tę samą 
tablicę informacyjną z cenami, więc prawdopodobnie należą do tej samej sieci basenów. Drugi basen miał również wydzieloną 
strefę dla małych dzieci.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_161407_02.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_155924_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transport: Skorzystaliśmy z aplikacji &lt;a href=&quot;https://bolt.eu/nl-be/&quot;&gt;Bolt&lt;/a&gt; aby wieczorem dostać się z lotniska do Funchal, koszt wyniósł 19 euro. 
W dzień wylotu, z samego rano zapłaciliśmy więcej (29 euro), ponieważ było mniej dostępnych samochodów, a dodatkowo zarezerwowaliśmy przejazd na 
konkretną godzinę.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nocleg: Wynajęliśmy apartament przez Airbnb i był to najlepszy, w jakim kiedykolwiek mieszkaliśmy! Adres: R. Elias 
Garcia 15. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/625124896734414040?source_impression_id=p3_1737231851_P3iFToGbXtka81Qm&quot;&gt;Mieszkanie na najwyższym piętrze z widokiem na ocean, 1 sypialnia, 5-10min spacer od centrum.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wynajem auta: Samochód wynajęliśmy przez &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wyspamadera.pl/auto&quot;&gt;Wyspa Madera&lt;/a&gt; od firmy Adratica. Koszt wynajmu auta klasy A na pięć dni 
wyniósł 185 euro, plus dodatkowe ubezpieczenie obejmujące opony, szyby i lusterka, 5 euro dziennie. Mieliśmy szczęście, bo 
dostaliśmy Nissana Micra Turbo (klasa C), który świetnie sprawdził się na stromych uliczkach. Kontakt z osobą, która 
dostarczyła nam samochód, za pośrednictwem WhatsAppa był bardzo pomocny. Zwrot samochodu również odbył się w centrum miasta, 
po zaparkowaniu po prostu wysłaliśmy naszą lokalizację, a osoba odbierająca pojazd pojawiła się na miejscu po około 10 minutach
(wcześniej została uprzedzona, że już wróciliśmy i szukamy miejsca do zaparkowania).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parking: Każdego wieczoru zostawialiśmy wynajęty samochód na pobliskim podziemnym parkingu, Parking Santa Luzia (Rua 5 
de Outubro, São Martinho, 9000-216 Funchal). Zawsze płaciliśmy 4,5 euro (tylko gotówką, automat). Warto zwrócić uwagę, że wiele 
miejsc jest zarezerwowanych i wyraźnie oznaczonych banerami zawieszonymi nad stanowiskami. Tylko raz musieliśmy zjechać 
na najniższy poziom, ponieważ parter był zajęty (było to po godzinie 20:00). Parkowanie małym autem nie stanowi problemu 
(pomijając fakt, że musiałam wielokrotnie manewrować, bo było naprawdę wąsko), ale większym pojazdom może być trudno zaparkować 
na wielu wyznaczonych miejscach.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_103435_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_103345_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Więcej szczegółów na temat zjazdów wiklinowymi saniami ulicą Carreiros do Monte znajdziesz &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carreirosdomonte.com/v3/en/index.php&quot;&gt;tutaj&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08446.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Na oficjalnej stronie ogrodu &lt;a href=&quot;https://montepalacemadeira.com/en/&quot;&gt;Jardim Monte Palace Madeira&lt;/a&gt; dostępne są różne opcje biletów, cena biletu dla osoby 
dorosłej wynosi 15 euro. Dojechaliśmy lokalnym autobusem z przystanku R 31 Janeiro Finanças (9C), linia 21 (linia 20 
również jedzie w tym kierunku). Podróż trwała około 13 minut i kosztowała 1,95 euro (bilet kupiony u kierowcy, gotówka).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nie skorzystaliśmy z &lt;a href=&quot;https://madeiracablecar.com/en/&quot;&gt;kolejki linowej w Funchal&lt;/a&gt; ponieważ cena była dość wysoka. Doświadczyliśmy podobnych atrakcji 
w innych krajach, więc nie uznaliśmy jej za obowiązkowy punkt programu. Słyszeliśmy też, że Madera oferuje tyle niesamowitych 
widoków, że spokojnie można ją pominąć. Za każdym razem, gdy mijaliśmy dolną stację kolejki, widzieliśmy długą kolejkę. 
Poza tym 13-minutowa przejażdżka autobusem była bardzo emocjonująca, prowadził przez wąskie ulice pełne samochodów, a 
umiejętności lokalnego kierowcy w pokonywaniu ostrych zakrętów naprawdę zrobiły na Nas wrażenie.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restauracje, które odwiedziliśmy:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.informalfoodexperience.com/&quot;&gt;Restaurante Informal&lt;/a&gt;: Przyszliśmy 15 minut przed otwarciem i ledwo udało nam się dostać stolik. Lokal nie 
przyjmuje rezerwacji, więc jeśli ktoś nie dostanie stolika zaraz po otwarciu, zostanie wpisany na listę oczekujących 
i musi wrócić po około 1,5 godziny. Zostaliśmy na 1 godzinę i 20 minut, a kiedy wychodziliśmy, przed wejściem już czekali 
ludzie gotowi zajać nasze zwolnione miejsce. Dania tutaj nam bardzo smakowany! Do tego elegancki wystrój i wysoki poziom 
obsługi. Niecałe 30 euro za osobę z napojem, ceny wyższe niż w innych miejscach, ale zdecydowanie warto.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_184011_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_184007_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Reidaponcha&quot;&gt;Rei da Poncha&lt;/a&gt;: Naszym ulubionym drinkiem był Nikita, mieszanka soku ananasowego, piwa i lodów waniliowych. Pycha!
To bardzo popularne miejsce, nigdy nie udało nam się tam usiąść, ale można kupić drinki na wynos (ok 3euro).
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_192527_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_192727_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rota23.pt/&quot;&gt;Rota 23 Hamburgueria&lt;/a&gt; Jedyna knajpka otwarta po 22:00 w pobliżu naszego apartamentu, kiedy dotarliśmy tam z 
lotniska. Okazało się, że to bardzo przyjemne miejsce.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bar “O Avô”: Smaczna espada com banana (ryba pałasz z bananem) oraz espetada de frango (szaszłyk z kurczaka). Ceny uczciwe, 
obsługa świetna. Niestety, widok dwóch karaluchów w drodze do toalety trochę popsuł wrażenie. Później jednak zauważyłam je 
również na chodnikach w różnych miasteczkach na wyspie i przeczytałam, że to poważny problem w tym regionie. Trudno więc 
ocenić, czy była to kwestia zaniedbania właścicieli, czy raczej ogólna plaga na wyspie. Niecałe 20 euro za osobę z napojem.
Adres: R. Da Praia 49A, São Martinho, 9000-643 Funchal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Casa do Bolo do Caco: Pyszne kanapki z bolo do caco, świetna opcja na szybki lunch lub przekąskę. Tradycyjny płaski 
chlebek bolo do caco jest przekrawany i wypełniany różnymi dodatkami. My próbowaliśmy wersji z grilowaną wołowiną. Niecałe 
10 euro za osobę z napojem.
Adres: Rua Dr. Fernão de Ornelas 26, 9050-021 Funchal
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_123638_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sklepy:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Frutaria Seminário, fajne miejsce, żeby kupić owoce. Jeśli chcesz spróbować lokalnych 
produktów, warto zwrócić uwagę czy owoce są z Madery czy importowane (zawsze obok ceny była informacja o pochodzeniu). 
Kupowaliśmy tam pyszną lokalną papaję pokrojoną w kawałki, ale wieczorem większość towaru była już wyprzedana wiec 
warto wybrać sie tam wcześniej.
Adres: R. do Seminário 16, 9000-053 Funchal&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Przydatne strony internetowe:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ifcn.madeira.gov.pt/pt/atividades-de-natureza/percursos-pedestres-recomendados/percursos-pedestres-recomendados.html&quot;&gt;oficjalna strona z listą zamkniętych oraz otwartych szlaków&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipma.pt/en/otempo/prev.localidade.hora/index.jsp#Madeira&amp;amp;Funchal/Lido&quot;&gt;prognoza pogody&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netmadeira.com/webcams-madeira&quot;&gt;kamery online które pokazują aktualne warunki pogodowe w różnych częściach wyspy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nasze pamiątki: świeże owoce, lokalny alkohol, bulwy roślin, produkty wykonane z korka….ale przede wszystkim wspomnienia!
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_200353_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Baseny naturalne Doca do Cavacas: opłata za wstęp wynosi 5,70 euro dla osoby dorosłej. Dzieci do 6. roku życia wchodzą 
bezpłatnie, a dzieci w wieku 7–17 lat płacą 1,90 euro.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Szczegóły obu biegów:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pierwszy bieg po centrum miasta - 7km, 236m w góre
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/Screenshot_20250128_213104_Suunto_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
Drugi bieg wzdłuż wybrzeża - 11km, 187m w góre
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/Screenshot_20250128_212556_Suunto_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2025/01/Funchal-PL/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2025/01/Funchal-PL/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugalia</category>
        
        <category>miasto</category>
        
        <category>Madera</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Funchal - great starting point for visiting the island of eternal springtime</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When it came time to choose a destination for our honeymoon, we wanted something special. This trip was a rare opportunity—our 
toddler stayed at home, so for once, we could travel as we did before starting a family. We dreamed of a place that offered 
breathtaking hiking trails, delicious food, and unspoiled nature. No need to worry about playgrounds or keeping the little 
one entertained. Madeira checked every box. We’d heard great recommendations about this Portuguese island from friends and family.
Our plan was simple: spend the first and last nights of our trip in Funchal, the island’s charming capital, and use the remaining 
five days to explore the rest of Madeira by car. And it turned out to be the perfect decision!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long flight, we needed to rest, stock up on groceries, and figure out parking for the days ahead. And wow, what 
an introduction to the city! The streets in Funchal are unbelievably steep, and by the time we reached our apartment after 
exploring the city, I was already sweating—not from the heat but from imagining myself navigating those narrow, inclined 
streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather on our first day in Madeira wasn’t exactly ideal. It quickly confirmed what we’d heard about how unpredictable 
Madeira’s weather can be. Our main goal for the day was to visit the famous Monte Palace Madeira botanical garden. After a 
short ride with a crazy local bus driver, I was very happy to get off the bus and finally breathe some fresh air. I was 
starting to feel motion sickness after all the sharp turns the bus made during the last 15 minutes. Be prepared for a wild ride!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to the botanical garden, we passed the Igreja de Nossa Senhora do Monte, a charming hilltop church. The monument 
in front of the church is a statue of Emperor Charles I of Austria (Karl I), honoring the last emperor of the Austro-Hungarian 
Empire. He lived his final days on this island and is buried in the church. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_110240_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just at the bottom of the stairs leading to the church, a famous tourist attraction can be found: the wicker toboggans. 
The 2-kilometer ride down the steep streets of Funchal begins here. When we passed this spot at around 10 a.m. on a Sunday 
morning, there was no one operating the toboggans.
These traditional sled-like vehicles are made of wicker baskets mounted on wooden runners and are used to transport 
visitors downhill from the village of Monte to the lower streets of Funchal. The journey covers about 2 kilometers 
and can reach speeds of up to 30 km/h. The drivers, called “Carreiros”, stand behind the sled and use their 
strength, balance, and rubber-soled boots to steer and control the speed as the toboggan glides down the hill.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08450.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lush greenery, exotic plants, and serene atmosphere made us feel like we’d stepped into a tropical rainforest. The 
Monte Palace itself was originally built as a luxurious hotel in the late 19th century. However, the hotel faced financial 
struggles over the years and eventually closed in the mid-20th century.
In the late 1980s, José Berardo purchased the property and decided to repurpose it as a botanical garden and cultural site. 
After its transformation, the gardens opened to visitors in the early 1990s, showcasing a stunning collection of exotic 
plants, minerals, and contemporary art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08565.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08483.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08523.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent about 2.5 hours wandering through the garden, though we had to take a few breaks to shelter from the rain. The 
unpredictable weather gave the whole place a moody, almost mystical vibe, making the experience even more unforgettable.
The garden offers breathtaking panoramic views of Funchal, the bay, and the Atlantic Ocean. But what surprised me most was 
the mineral exhibition. I wasn’t expecting to be impressed by rocks, but the creative display truly captivated me. Most 
specimens were from Brazil, Portugal, and South Africa, and they were absolutely stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_113302_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_113133_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_113038_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08539.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08529.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08467.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the minerals, there were pavilions showcasing modern and contemporary art, adding an element of surprise 
to the garden’s natural beauty. The Asian-inspired section of the garden, with its striking red elements, stood out 
beautifully against the lush green forest background. Another highlight was the succulent garden, where a variety of species 
were arranged in an incredibly artistic and visually appealing way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08553.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08555.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to walk back to Funchal as the weather was improving, and we wanted to explore the city at our own pace. We 
started on the street beneath the cable car, next to the parking lot of the upper cable car station. From there, we turned 
left just before the cemetery, following a charming path that ran behind some houses until we reached Caminho do Lombo street.
The road quickly became so steep that our calves started burning almost immediately! The area was a lovely residential 
neighborhood, but despite seeing bus stops along the way, there were no detailed schedules, and we didn’t spot a single 
bus. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08596.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some effort, we finally reached Miradouro da Tabaiba, a viewpoint offering fantastic vistas of Funchal, the 
bay, and the cable car route to Monte. It’s said to be one of the best spots to watch the famous New Year’s Eve fireworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08598.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued down Caminho do Lombo, passing underneath the express road. The next part of the walk was the trickiest—there 
was no sidewalk or safe space for pedestrians for about 200 meters, and the sharp turns made it feel unsafe. We quickly 
jogged through this stretch to get it over with. Eventually, we reached Rua Pedro José de Ornelas, a street that led us 
safely toward the city center of Funchal with 
proper sidewalks. By the time we arrived at our destination—the harbor—we had covered 6 kilometers, descending a total of 
550 meters. The sun had come out, and the view of the cruise ships and the shimmering water was absolutely beautiful.
Before heading for dinner, we walked through Parque de Santa Catarina, a peaceful spot in the city. It was there we 
noticed the CR7 Museum, a must-visit for football fans, with its famous statue of Cristiano Ronaldo outside—a statue that, 
as everyone jokes, looks nothing like him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08605.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this demanding walk, we rewarded ourselves with a well-deserved dinner at a local restaurant.
I couldn’t resist ordering one of the island’s signature dishes—black scabbardfish with banana.
At first, the combination felt exciting and unique, but as I made my way through the dish, the banana’s sweetness became 
a bit overwhelming. Still, it was an experience worth trying and a true taste of Madeira’s culinary creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also discovered Brisa Maracujá, a popular soft drink made with real passion fruit juice. Its refreshing and sweet 
flavor perfectly captures the tropical essence of Madeira’s famous passion fruit. Later, we came across the sugar-free 
version of the same drink, which turned out to be surprisingly tasty—even for someone like me, who doesn’t usually enjoy 
sugar-free beverages.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_152841_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to go for an evening run to explore the city before sunset. It was challenging to find a route that wouldn’t 
involve a demanding ascent, but I eventually chose Fortaleza de São João Baptista do Pico as my destination. The run to the 
fortress was tough (luckily, also short!), with steep streets that made for a great workout.
When I reached the fortress, I found it wasn’t in the best condition. The section offering the best view of the city was 
under construction, which left me feeling a bit disappointed. However, the effort of running uphill was rewarding in itself. 
Despite the fortress’s abandoned appearance, the nearby playground and café were full of life, families and 
children enjoying the evening.
From there, I ran towards the harbor and along the waterfront to Forte de São Tiago. The brightly lit streets and lively 
atmosphere made this part of the run especially enjoyable. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_183150_01.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_183451_01.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
However, after passing the fortress, the streets became darker 
and emptier, so I decided to turn back. I headed uphill toward our apartment, passing many restaurants filled with people 
enjoying their dinners.
It was the perfect way to end such an adventurous day—combining exercise, exploration, and the vibrant energy of Funchal in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explored &lt;strong&gt;Rua de Santa Maria&lt;/strong&gt;, one of the oldest streets in Funchal, during our evening walk the other day. In 2010, 
the government launched an initiative called “Art of Open Doors” as a way to revitalize the street and bring new life to 
the Old Town area. Local and international artists were invited to paint the doors of the buildings, transforming the 
street into an open-air art gallery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth walking down this street both in the morning and evening, as different places might be closed or open, 
revealing interesting paintings like The Little Prince, The Mermaid Door, grape harvest scenes, Funchal’s history and 
culture, or depictions of the sea life surrounding the island. The street is full of souvenir shops, restaurants, cafés, 
and bars, and it becomes especially lively in the evenings when locals and tourists gather for dinner and drinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241101_192208_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09549.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can explore Funchal by foot, taxi, cable car, and even tuk-tuks. These three-wheeled vehicles are a popular and 
eco-friendly way to navigate the city and its surroundings, as they can easily maneuver through the narrow streets of 
the Old Town. Tuk-tuks in Funchal are operated by various companies and drivers, often offering guided tours to help 
visitors discover key attractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re an excellent option for people with mobility issues or for those who find it challenging to walk up the city’s 
steep streets. While taking a break at the Lazareto viewpoint, we noticed a couple who had arrived by tuk-tuk. They paused 
for about five minutes as their driver gave them an explanation about the city before heading off to their next destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09553.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09545_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fortress Forte de São Tiago, with its striking bright yellow color, stands out beautifully against the blue waters 
of the Atlantic and the green hills of Madeira. I particularly enjoyed visiting this spot during my evening run for its 
peaceful vibe, where visitors can soak up the atmosphere, watch the sunset, or observe cruise ships and fishing boats in 
the harbor. During the day, the fort offers spectacular views of the ocean, the city, and the surrounding mountains. Inside, there is 
a restaurant that provides a unique dining experience, and the fort is also used for events, exhibitions, and other 
cultural activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09559.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were absolutely amazed by the variety of fruits available in shops, even in supermarkets, which tasted so much better 
than the ones in Belgium. Fruit shops, called “Frutaria,” caught our attention every time we passed them. Our favorite 
fruit was the local papaya.Our last day was reserved for shopping, and one of the places we were eager to visit was Mercado 
dos Lavradores. This famous market offers an impressive array of exotic fruits, such as passion fruit, annona (custard apple) , and the 
intriguing banana-pineapple hybrids. Vendors often let you sample their offerings, but prices can be significantly higher 
than elsewhere—so be cautious about overpaying, as prices can easily be double those at street stalls or in frutarias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the market is popular among locals, some parts, particularly the fruit stalls, are more geared toward tourists. We 
visited on a Saturday, one of the liveliest days when locals and tourists alike gather. The energy and vibrant atmosphere 
added to the market’s charm, despite the crowds. Stalls displayed beautifully arranged fruits, dried herbs, peppers, and 
flowers, creating a feast for the eyes! For those who prefer a quieter experience, visiting earlier in the morning or 
on a weekday might be a better option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we weren’t planning to buy fruit at the market due to the high prices, we discovered that the ground floor is an 
excellent spot to purchase flower bulbs. The flower stalls were especially colorful, showcasing tropical blooms like the 
famous strelitzias (bird-of-paradise). Women dressed in multi-colored striped dresses selling these flowers added a touch 
of tradition to the experience. Just by the entrance, stunning azulejos (traditional tiles) depict how the market looked 
in the past, giving visitors a glimpse into its history. If you’re a gardening enthusiast, make sure to check out the ground 
floor, where you can buy flower bulbs to take home. Strelitzia bulbs, in particular, make for a unique souvenir that’s sure 
to remind you of Madeira long after your trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09540.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09512.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09535_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most fascinating sections of the market is the seafood area. Here, you’ll find a variety of fish you might 
never have seen before. The star attraction is the black scabbardfish, or “espada,” a deep-sea species that has been a 
staple of Madeiran cuisine for centuries. Its long, slender body, black skin, and sharp teeth give it an almost mythical 
appearance. Found at depths of up to 1,500 meters in the North Atlantic, this fish is caught by skilled local fishermen 
using traditional methods. Despite its unusual look, the flesh of the black scabbardfish is tender, mild, and white, 
making it perfect for a range of delicious dishes—from the classic espada with banana to other creative preparations 
you’ll find in Madeiran restaurants. Interestingly, the black scabbardfish is found only around Madeira and near Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09526.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09541.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09528.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent last afternoon exploring another side of the coastline, heading toward Câmara de Lobos. My second run took 
me to the Doca do Cavacas Natural Pools. The entire route followed a pleasant sidewalk, passing several large hotels with 
swimming pools and stunning ocean views. Along the bustling road, there were also restaurants and souvenir shops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doca do Cavacas Natural Pools were a smaller version of the ones we visited in Porto Moniz. On the way, I also passed 
another set of outdoor pools called “Ponta Gorda Lido.” Both locations displayed the same information board with prices, 
so they must be part of a chain of swimming pools. These pools also had sections designed for toddlers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_161407_02.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_155924_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transportation: We used &lt;a href=&quot;https://bolt.eu/nl-be/&quot;&gt;Bolt&lt;/a&gt; to get from the airport to Funchal in the evening for 19 euros.
In the morning, we paid more (29 euros) because fewer cars were available, and we also reserved one for a specific time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Accommodation: We rented our apartment on Airbnb, and it was the best one we’ve ever stayed in! The address was R. Elias Garcia 15.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/625124896734414040?source_impression_id=p3_1737231851_P3iFToGbXtka81Qm&quot;&gt;Top floor/ocean view 1Bdr condo walk to downtown 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Car Rental: we rented a car via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wyspamadera.pl/auto&quot;&gt;Wyspa Madera&lt;/a&gt; from the Adratica rental company. 
The cost for a class A car rented for five days was 185 euros, plus extra insurance for tires, windows, and side mirrors 
at 5 euros per day. We were lucky to receive a Nissan Micra Turbo (class C), which was perfect for the steep streets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parking: We left the rented car at the nearby underground Parking Santa Luzia every night (Rua 5 de Outubro, São Martinho, 
9000-216 Funchal, Portugal). We always paid 4.5 euros (cash only). Note that many spaces are reserved and clearly labeled 
with banners hanging above them. Only once did we need to drive to the bottom level, as the ground floor was full (this 
was after 20:00). Parking a small car is fine, but larger vehicles might be challenging to maneuver.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_103435_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_103345_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more details about wicker toboggan rides along Carreiros do Monte Street, check &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carreirosdomonte.com/v3/en/index.php&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08446.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://montepalacemadeira.com/en/&quot;&gt;Jardim Monte Palace Madeira&lt;/a&gt; official website for details.
Ticket price: 15 euros per person.
We took a local bus from the R 31 Janeiro Finanças (9C) bus stop, line 21 (line 20 also goes the same direction). The 
ride took about 13 minutes and cost 1.95 euros from the driver.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We decided not to try the &lt;a href=&quot;https://madeiracablecar.com/en/&quot;&gt;Funchal Cable Car&lt;/a&gt; because the price was quite high. Since we’ve experienced cable cars in other 
countries, we didn’t consider it an essential attraction.
We also heard that Madeira offers so many amazing views that this one can be skipped. Every time we passed the bottom 
station of the cable car, there was a long queue. Plus, the 13-minute bus ride was exciting, as it navigated narrow 
streets full of cars. The local driver’s skill in maneuvering sharp turns was impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restaurants we visited:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.informalfoodexperience.com/&quot;&gt;Restaurante Informal&lt;/a&gt;: We arrived 15 minutes before opening and barely 
managed to get a table. This place doesn’t take reservations, so if you miss the first wave of seating when it opens, your 
name will be added to a list, and you’ll need to return about 1.5 hours later.
We stayed for 1 hour and 20 minutes, and by the time we left, there were already people waiting outside for a free table.
About 30 euro per person including drinks.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_184011_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_184007_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Reidaponcha&quot;&gt;Rei da Poncha&lt;/a&gt;: The Nikita drink was our favorite (mix of pineapple juice, beer
and vanilla ice cream)!
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_192527_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_192727_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rota23.pt/&quot;&gt;Rota 23 Hamburgueria&lt;/a&gt; The only place still open after 10 p.m. near our apartment when we 
arrived from the airport. It turned out to be a very nice spot.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bar “O Avô” -Tasty scabbard fish with banana and Espetada de Frango. Fair prices and great service. However, seeing 
two cockroaches on the way to the toilet was not a pleasant experience.
Address: R. Da Praia 49A, São Martinho, 9000-643 Funchal, Portugal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Casa do Bolo do Caco -  delicious bolo do caco sandwiches as a great alternative for quick lunch or snack, great way
of using the bolo do caco. Essentially, the traditional Bolo do Caco flatbread is sliced 
in half and filled with a variety of savory ingredients to create a sandwich, we tried one with beef.
Address: Rua Dr. Fernão de Ornelas 26, 9050-021 Funchal, Portugal
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_123638_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shops:
Frutaria Seminário - Frutas, Verduras e Legumes - A nice place to buy fruit. Be sure to check whether the fruit is local 
or imported if you want to try Madeiran produce. They sold tasty local papaya (in small pieces), but by the evening, almost everything was gone.
Address: R. do Seminário 16, 9000-053 Funchal, Portugal&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Useful websites:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ifcn.madeira.gov.pt/pt/atividades-de-natureza/percursos-pedestres-recomendados/percursos-pedestres-recomendados.html&quot;&gt;official list of open and closed hikes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipma.pt/en/otempo/prev.localidade.hora/index.jsp#Madeira&amp;amp;Funchal/Lido&quot;&gt;weather forecast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netmadeira.com/webcams-madeira&quot;&gt;online cameras&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh fruits, alcohol, plant bulbs, cork items… and, of course, memories!
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_200353_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Doca do Cavacas Natural Pools: entrance fee 5,70euro for adults. Children below 6 enters for free, 7-17y pays only 1.90euro.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Details of the runs:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run in the old city center - 7km, 236m ascent
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/Screenshot_20250128_213104_Suunto_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
Run along the coast line - 11km, 187m ascent
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/Screenshot_20250128_212556_Suunto_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/01/Funchal/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/01/Funchal/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>city</category>
        
        <category>Madeira</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Exploring the Natural and Cultural Wonders of Gerês-Xurés: A December Adventure in North of Braga</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Gerês-Xurés Transboundary Biosphere Reserve (&lt;strong&gt;Reserva de la Biosfera Transfronteriza Gerês-Xurés&lt;/strong&gt;) stretches across 
Galicia (Spain) and the North Region (Portugal). With its highest peaks, Nevosa (1,646m) and Fontefría, located in the 
heart of the Serra Gerês-Xurés mountains, it was recognized as a UNESCO Biosphere Reserve in 2009. A rare but iconic 
predator in this area is the Iberian Wolf. More commonly, you can encounter Garrano Horses, semi-wild horses native to 
northern Portugal. They roam freely in the reserve and symbolize the area’s cultural and natural heritage. Pyrenean Oak 
dominates the reserve’s forests, providing essential habitats for wildlife. We also noticed many eucalyptus trees, but 
this depends on the part of the vast reserve you’re exploring. I particularly admired the rock formations visible in the 
higher parts of the mountain range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_111108_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our hike began at &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro da Ermida&lt;/strong&gt; in the village of Ermida, where we left our car. We embarked on a short loop of 6.5 km 
(Miradouro da Ermida – Miradouro Fraga do Justo – Cascata da Rajada – Miradouro Silhas – Miradouro da Vela – Miradouro da Ermida), 
navigating with Organic Maps and partially following the trail marked as the “PR14 Alternativo” loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_113004_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_114348_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_113627_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we followed signs toward &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro Fraga do Justo&lt;/strong&gt;. From this viewpoint, you can see the entire surrounding valley of 
the Arado River, with its fast-flowing waters running between rocks before turning into Rajada waterfall visible below. 
&lt;strong&gt;Cascata da Rajada&lt;/strong&gt; was our main goal—a picturesque waterfall at the end of an enjoyable hike with plenty of shade. The 
trail becomes a bit rocky at the end but isn’t particularly technical. According to Google reviews, there’s less water 
in August, but in early December, the stream was abundant. Some visitors climb the rocks at the end to reach the base of 
the waterfall. Be cautious, as the rocks can get very slippery. You can also find a larger, deeper lagoon for swimming in 
summer. The surroundings of Cascata da Rajada are a pleasant spot to take a break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_122953_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_130642_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_130539_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Close to the waterfall, you can find additional viewpoints on natural rocks, such as &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro Silhas&lt;/strong&gt;. The views from both 
sections of the viewpoint are stunning. It’s worth exploring to find paths leading to both parts, though they are not always 
obvious and require walking between trees and bushes. We then continued our way back to Ermida village, stopping at another 
viewpoint, &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro da Vela&lt;/strong&gt;. This viewpoint is very accessible, with a clear path leading to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearby, we noticed part of the forest had been recently burned. Large parts of central and northern Portugal are covered 
by eucalyptus, a highly flammable tree. Eucalyptus thrives and regenerates after wildfires, making it controversial in Portugal. 
Introduced in the 1850s, eucalyptus is now the most common tree in the country. While it’s valuable to the pulp industry 
for its fast growth and high yield, it depletes soil and water and spreads wildly on unmanaged lands. Its flammable leaves 
and bark exacerbate the wildfire risk. The photos below, clearly show how quickly eucalyptus can recover after late summer
fires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_132806_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_132959_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_133009_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_133028_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After visiting this viewpoint, we continued our relaxing walk to explore the village and its rural surroundings. One 
striking feature of the area is the presence of hórreos, traditional granaries found near almost every house. These structures, 
built from wood or stone and elevated on pillars ending with flat stones, prevent rodents from accessing stored grain. 
They are typically square or rectangular with slits in the walls for ventilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_135700_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, we visited the nearby &lt;strong&gt;Cascata do Arado&lt;/strong&gt;. We parked near the roundabout where the paved road ends (coordinates: 
41.715924, -8.132380) and walked 15 minutes along the dirt road (approximately 850m), which is manageable for children. 
You can also drive closer, as the dirt road is in good condition with ample parking. Cascata do Arado is a beautiful, 
small waterfall that’s easy to access. In summer, visitors often swim in its pools. To reach the base of the waterfall, 
you need to navigate an unmarked trail and wade through the river, as the official path leads only to the top viewpoint. 
Be cautious—there are warning signs about accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_141901_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_142332_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_143209_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_142402_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I hiked to a viewpoint (&lt;strong&gt;Viewpoint Rocas&lt;/strong&gt;) near the parking area. The climb is steep and unmarked, taking about 
five minutes. While there isn’t a clear path, the ascent involves scrambling over rocks, with the last section featuring 
artificial stairs. Though the climb is tricky and involves some trial and error, it was more interesting than the panoramic 
views at the top which is nice but not the best we have seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_145115_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gerês-Xurés Reserve is a remarkable destination for nature enthusiasts, offering opportunities for hiking, wildlife 
observation, and cultural exploration. Spending just one day in this park convinced me it’s a place worth returning to 
for a longer adventure. Especially when days become longer and more daylight would allow for longer hikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://turismo.cm-terrasdebouro.pt/aventura/&quot;&gt;The Geres-Xures Transboundary Biosphere Reserve&lt;/a&gt; website contains 
description of hikes from this region, PR1-PR15 and longer ones GR34 (34km loop), GR50 (187.5km linear). There is pdf file
with all detail for each hike that can be downloaded but it’s not really useful to find your route, it’s nice general 
overview though. We used Organic Maps app to navigate and all trails were marked in this app so we didn’t have any issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/Screenshot_20241219_101439_Suunto.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/Screenshot_20241219_101449_Suunto_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://turismo.cm-terrasdebouro.pt/listings/pr14-trilho-do-sobreiral-da-ermida/#en-pr14&quot;&gt;Details of PR14&lt;/a&gt; can be found 
on the official website. Trail is marked with yellow and red horizontal stripes. Where a route changes direction, the 
red stripe will be L-shaped showing which way to turn (below example means that we should turn left). More detailsed explanation
is included in pdf available under above link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_134714_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_125642_1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were signs on each viewpoint (below Miradouro Silhas) &lt;strong&gt;“Se vir Incendo, ligue 117”&lt;/strong&gt; what can be translated to 
&lt;strong&gt;“In case of fire, call 117”&lt;/strong&gt;. 
 &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_130529_02.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Geres/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Geres/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Heritage and Holidays: A Magical Visit to Braga and Guimarães</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While visiting friends in Pedralva, exploring Portugal’s third-largest city was a must. Our journey began with a 
bus ride, and we arrived near the beautiful Park Avenida Central, where a charming Christmas market awaited us. The park 
was adorned with festive decorations, immersing us in the holiday spirit. We decided to return to the same place after 
dark to experience the market illuminated by Christmas lights. That turned out to be a great decision because, that evening, 
the market hosted a live music performance as part of the 29th edition of CELTA at Theatro Circo. Themed “Urban CELTA,” 
the event brought together over 400 artists from various universities. It was my first time experiencing this type of music, 
and I thoroughly enjoyed it. As I later learned, a “tuna” is a group of university students from Spain, Portugal, or Latin 
America who perform traditional music in traditional university dress. Originating in the 13th century, these groups once 
played to earn money or food. Today, they continue the tradition for fun, travel, and meeting new people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_135837_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_134853_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_135937_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are about 35 churches in the city of less than 200-thousand residents. The “Santa Maria de Braga” Cathedral, with small 
museum, isn’t even the most famous one, but more about other places will follow in the next part of this post. The area 
around the cathedral is a great spot for finding unique souvenirs, with plenty of shops to browse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_170817_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other highlights of the historical city center include:
&lt;strong&gt;The Arch of the New Gate&lt;/strong&gt; (top left photo below). This triumphal arch marks the western entrance to the city’s medieval 
wall. It is located at the start of R. Dom Diogo de Sousa, the main shopping street. Strolling down this street is worthwhile, 
as it is lined with beautiful buildings adorned with blue-tiled facades. It’s also where locals gather on Christmas Eve 
to eat bananas and drink Muscat wine in the hours before Christmas dinner. This tradition, started over three decades ago 
by the owner of Casa das Bananas, still attracts thousands of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_141826_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_172508_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_172404_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_172344_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Braga City Hall&lt;/strong&gt;: An 18th-century building housing the local government.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_171734_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_155837_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City Market&lt;/strong&gt; (Mercado Municipal): Recently renovated with a modern wooden roof, this market features stalls selling 
flowers, vegetables, fruits, cheese, coffee, and more. Although we visited late in the afternoon when many stalls were 
closed, we still managed to buy some delicious mandarins from a local vendor. December is also a great time for spotting 
orange and mandarin trees on many streets during our walk. The best oranges are typically in season from late fall through 
early spring, with peak freshness often occurring between December and March.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_150618_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_145406_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_151501_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Santa Barbara Garden&lt;/strong&gt; This stunning garden, located next to the Archiepiscopal Palace, was a highlight of our walk. The 
colorful flower beds, beautiful central fountain, and well-maintained design made it a visual delight. The garden also 
offers views of the medieval and Baroque wings of the palace, including a section damaged by fire in 1834. Next to 
the garden is the public library and district archive, housed in the palace’s Baroque wing. The area is Very well maintained,
and I was surprised to find such a beautiful spot in the heart of a busy city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_152556_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_152447_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_152818_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, we planned to visit two famous sanctuaries near Braga. Before setting off, we decided to fuel up with a 
popular local dish. Taberna Belga is renowned for its francesinhas—a unique take on the traditional Portuguese dish that 
differs from the famous Porto version. They don’t take reservations, so be prepared to wait for a table. Francesinha is a 
type of sandwich originating in Porto, made with thick slices of white bread, Portuguese ham, sausage, cheese, and steak. 
The version in Braga is creamier and more buttery. It includes bread, wet-cured ham, linguiça, fresh sausage like chipolata, 
steak or roast meat, and is topped with melted cheese and a thick, spiced tomato sauce. This sauce, which resembles a 
tomato cream soup, is poured over a croque madame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first stop was the Sanctuary of Our Lady of Sameiro, which offers panoramic views of the city, surrounding mountains, 
and the River Minho. Located over 350 meters above Braga, it’s a serene and spiritual site visited by Pope John Paul II 
in 1982. This is the second-largest sanctuary dedicated to the Virgin Mary in Portugal, with Fátima being the largest 
Marian sanctuary, and was built in the 19th century. The main Marian festivities take place on the first Sunday of 
June and the third Sunday of August, drawing thousands of pilgrims from across the region. Pilgrims recite prayers and 
sing hymns dedicated to the Virgin Mary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_135553_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_135943_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_140353_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 2 km from Sameiro is the Sanctuary of Bom Jesus do Monte, a UNESCO World Heritage Site since 2019. In the 19th century, 
the area surrounding the church and its grand stairway was transformed into a park. The water-powered funicular, built in 
1882, connects the bottom of the hill to the sanctuary and is the oldest funicular in the world operating on this system. 
This was also the first funicular built on the Iberian Peninsula and remains in use today. The sanctuary is famous for 
its Baroque-style staircase, consisting of 577 steps. It welcomes over one million visitors annually, including pilgrims, 
tourists, and locals. Walking down the stairway is a must to fully appreciate its architectural beauty and design (you can 
take the funicular back up to the church).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_142138_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_142622_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_145611_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_143251_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sanctuary itself is free to enter and features a large park with tall trees and paved walkways, perfect for leisurely 
strolls or quiet reflection. Benches are scattered throughout, offering places to rest and enjoy the peaceful surroundings, 
with designated picnic areas. A small artificial lake provides boat rentals, making it an ideal spot for relaxation. The 
basilica is stunning, and the views of Braga from the top are spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_144436_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_144114_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_141832_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the afternoon, we planned to drive to Guimarães, often referred to as the birthplace of Portugal because it is where 
Afonso Henriques, the first king of Portugal, was born. After finding a parking spot, we started our walk to the historic 
center of the city. The first medieval-looking building we encountered was Torre da Alfândega, with the words “Aqui nasceu 
Portugal” (“Portugal was born here”) written on its walls. This tower was recently renovated and can be visited to enjoy 
views of the city, though we didn’t know about this on the day of our visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_155357_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_155429_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guimarães was founded in the 4th century and became the first capital of Portugal in the 12th century. We fell in love 
with the small cobblestone streets, medieval architecture, and vibrant squares of the city center. The cobblestone streets 
are easy to walk through, offering the chance to discover great little shops and restaurants. Its historic center, a UNESCO 
World Heritage Site since 2001, was truly beautiful, and it was evident that there were more tourists here compared to 
Braga. The streets in this city were also decorated with lights and Christmas ornaments, though they were less spectacular 
than those in Braga. We also passed by a flea market offering a variety of antiques and collectibles, located under the 
columns of the Old Town Council Chambers (Antiga Câmara Municipal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_160048_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_160015_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_160410_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main landmarks of the city is the 10th-century castle, located on a hill overlooking the town. The primary role 
of the castle was to protect the nearby monastery and its residents from Moorish and Norman invasions. It is believed to 
be the birthplace or early residence of Afonso Henriques, who declared the country’s independence after the Battle of São 
Mamede in 1128, which took place near the castle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_162443_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explored the interior courtyard, climbed the towers, and walked along the eight towers, which offer panoramic views of 
Guimarães. The sunset view was stunning, and we could also see the Sanctuary of Penha, located on a nearby hill. According 
to my friends, it’s a lovely place to visit if you have more time, popular for weddings because the view from there is 
spectacular. The sanctuary, built in the 1930s, is an example of modernist architecture. Monte da Penha is covered in 
forests and massive granite boulders, making it a perfect spot for nature lovers and hikers. Located at an altitude of 
around 617 meters, the sanctuary offers breathtaking panoramic views of Guimarães and the surrounding countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_163805_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_162154_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_164457_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This castle is not just a fortress—it is a symbol of Portugal’s national identity and independence. Its well-preserved 
structure, combined with its historical importance, makes it a must-see destination for anyone exploring the roots of 
the Portuguese nation. It is also part of the UNESCO World Heritage Site designation for the Historic Centre of Guimarães.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From Pedralva, take a local bus to Braga for just €2 (around 40 minutes, tickets available from the driver) or opt for 
an Uber ride for €14 (20 minutes).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Santa Maria de Braga Cathedral: Entry ticket €2, includes a small museum.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sanctuary of Our Lady of Sameiro: Large, free parking area located just below the church.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bom Jesus do Monte: Upper parking costs €1, located next to the church. Funicular tickets are €2 for a single trip or 
€3 for a round trip.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restaurants we visited:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tíbias de Braga: A pastry shop offering local delights like tibias. These light, slightly crunchy pastries are filled 
with soft pastry cream and sprinkled with sugar. I tried the lemon-flavored one, which was tasty but a bit too sweet for my liking.
Address: Av. São Miguel O Anjo 5, 4700-210 Braga, Portugal.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Casa das Natas: A pastry shop offering amazing Pastel de nata, just next to the main city bus station.
Address: 4, Pç. da Galiza 8, Portugal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tabernabelga.pt/&quot;&gt;Taberna Belga&lt;/a&gt; Known for its francesinhas. This place doesn’t accept reservations, so 
there’s often a queue even before opening time. A waitress waits outside to take down names and the number of people. 
Once the restaurant opens, names are called systematically to avoid chaos. We arrived just before opening time and 
waited 20 minutes to get in. By the time we left, the queue was significantly longer, so arriving early is a good idea.
This dish was way too heavy for me because of the amount of sauce, even when taking half of the portion!&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rotiveminho: Serves traditional Portuguese dishes. Very popular, we arrived just before opening time and there were no 
free tables 20minutes later (most of them were with reservation). We tried salmon and it was very tasty.
Address: R. do Raio 301, 4710-924 Braga, Portugal.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/IMG-20241206-WA0020_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_124150_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guimaraes: We parked on Av. Dom Afonso Henriques street (coordinates: 41.436881, -8.295615), which offers free parking. 
A nearby side street, Rua da Indústria, also has many new parking spots (both streets are one-way).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guimarães Castle: Entry ticket €2 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pacodosduques.gov.pt/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Learn more here&lt;/a&gt;. There is a huge parking area 
behind the castle, which might be a good spot to park your car while visiting the city.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Palace of the Dukes of Braganza (Paço dos Duques de Bragança): Located next to the castle, entry ticket €6. We didn’t 
have time to visit the palace, but according to Google reviews, it’s really worth checking out. This medieval estate was 
built in the 15th century and served as a noble residence for the Dukes of Braganza until the 16th century. The palace 
was restored in the 20th century and converted into a museum with a fascinating collection that includes 15th- and 
16th-century furniture, ceramics, medieval arms, Portuguese art, and many artifacts related to the history of the 
Braganza dynasty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_162213_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Braga/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Braga/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>Braga</category>
        
        <category>city</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Rainy Day Adventure in Porto</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My journey started with a morning flight to Porto. With an evening train to Braga planned, I had the perfect opportunity 
to spend the day exploring Porto’s historic heart. After a quick 30-minute metro ride, I arrived at Bolhão station. As I 
stepped out, a light drizzle greeted me, turning my first mission into a hunt for an umbrella. Luckily, ALE-HOP, my 
daughter’s favorite shop, came to the rescue with a cheerful selection of umbrellas. 
My next stop was the nearby Mercado do Bolhão, as my stomach started to rumble, and this place has a roof, which was 
especially useful in such unpleasant weather. This market was first established as an open-air market, but in 1914, the 
current neoclassical building was opened. The place was re-opened in 2022 after a major renovation, and you can clearly 
see the changes—it’s modern, well-organized, and clean. It has a glass-covered roof, allowing natural light to reach the 
vendors who sell fresh flowers, vegetables, fruits, meat, cheeses, olives, and seafood. Stalls with traditional handicrafts 
add to the market’s charm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_133924_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_134147_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also find authentic Portuguese dishes at the market, from francesinha (a Porto sandwich) to fresh pastries like 
Pastéis de Nata. These iconic Portuguese pastries originated from the Mosteiro dos Jerónimos in Belém, Lisbon, in the early 
19th century, where Catholic monks developed the first recipe. I’ve had the pleasure of visiting the monastery and Fábrica 
de Pastéis de Belém, the birthplace of these pastries, &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2022/03/Lisbon-Portugal/&quot;&gt;during our first trip to Lisbon&lt;/a&gt;. These are definitely my favorite pastries in Portugal, 
and I would never get bored of eating them.
It’s very interesting to learn why monks created this pastry, which is rich in egg yolks. Monks and nuns used large 
quantities of egg whites to starch clothes, such as habits. The leftover egg yolks were creatively repurposed into desserts. 
Brilliant, right?
The pastry shell should be really crispy—you should clearly hear it when biting into a piece—and the rich, creamy custard 
center creates the perfect contrast in textures and flavors. They’re best when eaten warm and fresh. I tried one at the 
famous bakery Manteigaria, next to the market, and it did not disappoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_140403_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_140313_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearby, the Chapel of Souls is definitely worth a quick stop. Its unique exterior, entirely covered in blue and white 
azulejo tiles, is visible from a distance. These stunning ceramic tiles depict scenes from the lives of saints and were 
added to the chapel in 1929. Located on Porto’s main shopping street, Rua de Santa Catarina, the blue azulejos cover an 
impressive area of about 360 square meters. This chapel is a perfect example of beautiful and unique architecture that 
deserves a visit when exploring the vibrant Bolhão area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_140835_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_141036_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_141054_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued my walk toward Gaia and the iconic Luís I Bridge. This remarkable structure features two levels, each serving 
distinct purposes: the upper deck for trams and pedestrians, and the lower deck for vehicles and pedestrians. Designed by 
Théophile Seyrig, a student of Gustave Eiffel, and completed in 1886, the bridge reflects the rapid industrialization and 
urban development of Porto during that era.
Walking along the upper deck offers breathtaking panoramic views of the Douro River, Porto’s historic Ribeira district, 
and the wine cellars of Vila Nova de Gaia. Its unique two-level design is both functional and visually stunning, making 
it one of Portugal’s most photographed landmarks. I particularly enjoyed the misty weather, which added a magical touch 
to the views of the river and surrounding green hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_150555_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_150709_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_150642_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_151913_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_153140_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mosteiro da Serra do Pilar, a 16th-century monastery and UNESCO World Heritage Site, provides one of the best panoramic 
viewpoints over Porto and the Douro River. After visiting the viewpoint near the monastery, I continued my journey into 
the Gaia district, passing through Jardim do Morro. Gaia is well-known for its Port wine lodges, where visitors can learn 
about the production of this iconic wine and indulge in tastings. A cable car connects the riverside with the upper part 
of Gaia, offering scenic views of the city and the river below. I chose to walk down the narrow streets beneath the cable 
car and along the riverside promenade. This vibrant area is lined with restaurants, cafés, and shops, all offering stunning 
views of Porto and the Luís I Bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_153459_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_153727_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many urban areas in Portugal, Gaia faced economic challenges during the 20th century, resulting in periods of neglect. 
As industries declined and people moved to modern housing developments, many buildings were abandoned. Restoring these 
historical properties can be costly, and owners often lack the resources to renovate, especially when complex ownership 
or legal disputes are involved. This issue is similar to what is happening in Funchal, Madeira.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the rise in tourism has brought renewed interest in revitalizing Gaia. Projects like the WOW (World of Wine) 
district have transformed abandoned spaces into vibrant cultural and leisure destinations. As seen in the photo below, 
some rooftops remain collapsed, but efforts are ongoing to restore the area and breathe new life into its historical charm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_152535_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porto São Bento train station, another place where stunning azulejo tilework can be admired, over 20,000 azulejo tiles! 
It is not just a transport hub but also a cultural and architectural gem that attracts countless visitors. It has very 
convenient location, just in the heart of Porto. Scenes from Portugal’s history,traditional rural life, including festivals, 
markets, and customs can be spotted on the walls. Name of this station originated from former Benedictine monastery. 
Despite its historical charm, São Bento is a fully operational railway station, serving regional and intercity trains, 
including train to Braga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_145023_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_145300_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jardins do Palácio de Crista, well-maintained park with fountains, sculptures was a perfect destination for a leisurely stroll.
However, I would not recommend this place if you have only 6h to visit the city and weather is not great :) At the heart 
of the gardens stands the Pavilhão Rosa Mota, also known as the Super Bock Arena. This multipurpose venue hosts concerts, 
sports events, and exhibitions. I have noticed some  peacocks there but they were all hiding under the roof of the pavilion.
The gardens were originally designed around the Crystal Palace, that was destroyed in 1951 but park kept the same name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_164132_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to the park, I noticed vintage tramcars, symbol of the city’s history and charm. Operated by STCP (Sociedade 
de Transportes Colectivos do Porto), these historic trams are one way to explore its streets. There are only still 3 lines 
that are operating through Porto’s most picturesque areas. The trams are beautifully restored and retain their original 
wooden elements and classic design. If you’re interested in the history of Porto’s tram network, visit the Museu do Carro 
Eléctrico (Tram Museum) and its collection of vintage tramcars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_162405_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was already getting dark when I passed the Christmas market in Jardim da Cordoaria. Though small, it was a pleasant place 
to explore. The streets nearby were filled with the smoky aroma of roasted chestnuts, sold by many vendors using traditional 
carts with small coal ovens. The smoke from the carts created a cozy, festive atmosphere as people walked by. Roasted chestnuts 
are typically sold on the streets during the autumn and winter months, from October to January, making them a seasonal favorite. 
I first tried this healthy snack a few weeks ago on Madeira and really liked them! They’re quite filling and are served in 
small paper cones, perfect for enjoying on the go. The towering structure near the Christmas market turned out to be the 
Clérigos Church, an iconic landmark in Porto. Unfortunately, I couldn’t enter without a ticket as the Spiritus Light Show 
was ongoing at the time. All the Christmas decorations started to light up on the streets, and despite the rainy weather, 
the atmosphere in the city was cheerful. Igreja do Carmo church was another one in the area of the Christmas market that 
caught my attention, visible on the top photo below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_171304_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_180607_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_180859_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to the train station to catch my train to Braga, I realized I hadn’t visited Porto Cathedral! With an hour left 
before my train’s departure, I quickly rushed to the Batalha neighborhood, where the cathedral is located.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching from Avenida Dom Afonso Henriques, the cathedral’s fortress-like appearance immediately caught my attention. 
There were also Christmas stalls along this part of the street, adding to the festive atmosphere of the city. I explored 
the almost deserted area around the cathedral and walked a bit downhill, wandering through narrow streets. 
By then, it was already dark, so unfortunately, there were no views of the Douro River or the Luís I Bridge from the 
cathedral square. The cathedral is a significant stop on the Camino de Santiago pilgrimage route, and it’s common to 
see pilgrims beginning their journey here. While my visit was brief, it was still fascinating to experience this historic 
and iconic landmark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_182435_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_182421_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_182837_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my day in Porto came to an end, I couldn’t help but smile at how much I managed to see and experience in just a few 
hours. From the lively Mercado do Bolhão to the stunning azulejo tiles at São Bento station, the city had a way of surprising 
me at every turn. The Christmas lights glowing in the drizzle and the smoky aroma of roasted chestnuts made the streets 
feel so cozy, even in the rain.&lt;br /&gt;
As I hopped on the train to Braga, I knew one thing for sure—I’d be back to explore even more someday&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Metro ticket was 2.85 euro (2.25euro zone Z4 + Andante card 0.60euro). Andante card can be re-chargeable. On the ticket machine, 
there was a sticker with all metro station names and next to the, there was a zone that applies when you go there from 
the airport. I went to Bolhão metro station so it was Z4. You can also check &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.metrodoporto.pt/pages/391&quot;&gt;more details&lt;/a&gt;
however when I check connection Aeroporto – Bolhao, price for single ticket was 2euro so website is not showing correct 
ticket fare (zone was correct though).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Restaurant in Porto PAPO CHEIO - A Tasca de Cedofeita, the restaurant has a small surface inside and tables outside and
serves delicious local dishes. Superb value and very friendly service.
Address: R. de Cedofeita 95, 4050-166 Porto, Portugal&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_173014_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Manteigaria – &lt;a href=&quot;https://manteigaria.com/&quot;&gt;Fábrica de Pastéis de Nata&lt;/a&gt; sells fresh and hot Pastel de Nata with tasty and very soft
cream. Pastries are prepare and baked on spot (€1.30 a piece).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Train from Porto to Braga was 3.95 euro (3.45euro ticket + 0.50euro SIGA card). This card is reusable and has contactless 
technology to carry up to 31 single tickets that can be used in either direction. Using the ticket machine was a bit 
challenging, as even when switched to English, the translation was inaccurate. It took a few attempts and a bit of trial 
and error to figure out how to purchase the correct ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Porto/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Porto/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>city</category>
        
        <category>Porto</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Family’s Guide to Valencia: Ocean Adventures, Culture, and Scenic Escapes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We paired our stay in Platja de Gandia with a one-day trip to Oceanogràfic, an 
oceanarium located within the stunning Gardens of Turia in the heart of Valencia. More details on how we traveled there 
can be found in the practical section at the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for an unforgettable experience with marine life, Oceanogràfic in Valencia should be at the top of your list. As 
the largest aquarium in Europe, it’s the kind of place where you can easily spend an entire day. From dolphins and 
beluga whales to sharks, penguins, turtles, and an incredible variety of fish, this destination captivates visitors of 
all ages while promoting sustainability and environmental awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so much to explore, plan to spend at least 4–5 hours (or more) to fully enjoy everything. The park is cleverly 
divided into zones, each representing different marine habitats from around the world. One of the standout features is 
the underwater tunnels, where you’re surrounded by breathtaking views of sharks and rays gliding gracefully overhead. 
These tunnels are pure magic but can get crowded since they are one-way only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_115942.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_143015.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A personal highlight? The beluga whales. These charming creatures are as adorable as you can imagine and an absolute must-see.
Oceanogràfic rescued two belugas from the horrors of the war in Ukraine in June of this year. It is the only facility on 
the continent that houses belugas and was able to assist with this very challenging rescue operation. Currently, the new 
belugas are undergoing recovery and acclimation in separate areas that are not accessible or viewable by the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jellyfish tanks were almost hypnotizing visitors with their graceful, harmonic movements. While 
there’s no shortage of fascinating animals, don’t be surprised if some exhibits, like the crocodiles, are a bit 
underwhelming—we only managed to spot one during our visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_145010.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_133136.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_125537.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For families with kids, the dolphin show is the star attraction. There are typically three shows per day, and we 
recommend arriving at least 20–25 minutes early to secure good seats. For us, this was enough time, but some reviews 
mention that the shows can fill up even with that much time in advance. The show itself lasts less than 20 minutes and 
is both fun and educational, with English subtitles on a big screen for 
non-Spanish speakers. Watching the trainers interact with these intelligent creatures was a delight, and the focus on 
environmental issues rather than elaborate tricks made it all the more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/P8273833.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_154023.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_153437.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pick up a map at the reception near the entrance—it’ll save you time and make exploring easier. The layout is intuitive, 
but there is a lot to see, and a map ensures you don’t miss any of the highlights. Additionally, you can enter the 
underground aquariums in one place and exit in a completely different part of the park, which left us a bit confused and 
disoriented at times. If your toddler uses a pram, you’ll need to locate elevators for each underground zone and leave 
it in a small designated storage area while attending the dolphin show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oceanogràfic has a variety of food stands and restaurants (most with poor reviews), but be prepared for 
higher-than-average prices. While the no-outside-food policy might seem strict, many visitors managed to sneak in some 
snacks. Alternatively, bring sandwiches and enjoy them before entering the park—this was our strategy, and it worked 
perfectly (though we still had small snacks inside, not entirely following the rule). Once inside, vending machines 
with drinks are convenient for a quick refresh. If you’re looking for a special treat, the submarine restaurant offers 
a unique dining experience, but be sure to book ahead as it fills up quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After our long visit to Oceanogràfic, we only managed to walk back to the train station on foot, admiring along the way 
the beautiful Turia Gardens, which now stretch more than 8 km and were developed on the dry riverbed of the Turia 
River. The row of uniquely designed buildings—including the Science Museum, Art Center, and IMAX Theater—is stunning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science Museum is particularly well-known, but we would have needed another day to visit it, and it might not be 
the best choice for our almost-three-year-old toddler. The Art Palace of Queen Sofia is Valencia’s Royal Opera House 
and also a venue for music, ballet, and theater performances. It can be visited with a guided tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_165324.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_165824.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visiting the rest of the city was something we saved for the last day before our flight back to Belgium. We booked one 
night in the city center, close to the Turia metro station, so we could easily reach the airport early the next morning. 
After dropping off our luggage at the apartment, we headed straight to the city center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first stop was the spectacular food market, &lt;strong&gt;Mercat Central de València&lt;/strong&gt;. This beautiful market offers a diverse 
selection of food—meats, seafood, baked goods, spices, and cheese—as well as ready-to-eat meals and drinks, allowing 
you to enjoy your food right there. Opened in 1928, it features a unique blend of iron, glass, and ceramics, with its 
central dome reaching nearly 30 meters high! It’s definitely worth a visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_132220.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_125403.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_125502_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_125349_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just opposite the market, you’ll find the Silk Exchange (La Lonja de la Seda), the historic marketplace that once 
thrived during Valencia’s booming silk trade. Recognized as a UNESCO World Heritage Site, it showcases stunning late 
Gothic architecture. Although we didn’t visit it ourselves, our friends highly recommended it, highlighting the 
beautiful ceiling and the twisting columns in the grand hall as standout features. There’s also a charming courtyard 
with a small garden of orange trees at its center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_125002.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next stop was Plaça de l’Ajuntament, home to Valencia’s City Hall, the Main Post Office, and several historic, 
beautiful banks. This square is a popular meeting point for both locals and tourists, as it serves as a hub for many 
bus routes. Flower stalls and a fountain add extra charm to this large, lively space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_133019.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading toward the main cathedral, we passed an intriguing building that turned out to be the &lt;strong&gt;Museu Nacional de 
Ceràmica i de les Arts Sumptuàries González Martí&lt;/strong&gt;, home to a vast collection of ceramics and artworks. Its stunning 
Baroque facade immediately caught our attention. Although we didn’t have time to explore the interior, it appears to 
be budget-friendly, offering free entry on weekends and discounts for certain visitors. With excellent reviews, 
it seems well worth a visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_134351.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were pleasantly surprised upon reaching Plaça de la Reina to discover misting water sprays that offered a refreshing 
cool-down on hot days. Situated right next to the iconic Valencia Cathedral, the square has been recently renovated 
and is surrounded by cafes, restaurants, and shops, making it a perfect spot to grab a bite or enjoy a drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_145242.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Valencia Cathedral, also known as the Cathedral of the Holy Chalice, is one of the city’s most iconic landmarks. 
Most visitors come to see the cup believed to have been used by Jesus at the Last Supper, which is kept in a dedicated 
chapel. Various architectural styles can be observed, a result of its long history of renovations since construction 
began in the 13th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_145643.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_150144.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Túria Fountain on Plaza de la Virgen, located right in front of the Basilica de la Mare de Déu, is a clear 
representation of the Túria River. The fountain features eight sculptures of women, symbolizing the eight main 
irrigation canals (acequias) that distribute water from the Túria to the surrounding fields. The square itself is 
stunning, surrounded by historic buildings, including the Basilica and the nearby Valencia Cathedral. Its vibrant 
atmosphere and rich history make it a must-visit spot in the heart of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_150552.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re searching for a peaceful escape from Valencia’s busy city center and the scorching afternoon sun, the Botanical 
Garden (Jardí Botànic) is the perfect oasis. Tucked away like a hidden gem yet still within walking distance, this 
tranquil park offers a refreshing change of scenery and a chance to reconnect with nature in the heart of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During our late-August visit, the garden wasn’t bursting with blooms, but it still showcased an incredible variety of 
plants, ranging from towering trees to delicate succulents. The old arboretum is another standout feature—its tall 
trees, planted decades ago, have grown to enormous sizes, with some even piercing through the roofs of nearby 
structures. Walking through this area feels like stepping into a magical forest. This spot is perfect for escaping 
Valencia’s summer heat. With plenty of shaded seating areas beneath sprawling tree 
canopies, you can sit back, relax, and enjoy the calm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_162025.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_160726.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_161559.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_155826.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_162311.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing this blog post after the catastrophic floods that hit the eastern Spanish region of Valencia at the end of 
October. It’s truly heartbreaking to see pictures and videos of people trapped in vehicles, buildings, and underground 
parking garages, caught completely off guard as the streets were transformed into rivers within moments. The root of this 
devastating event was a record-breaking downfall: a year’s worth of rain unleashed in just eight hours. When I visited 
Valencia a few months ago, the thought of such a disaster never even crossed my mind. The city seemed so 
vibrant, sunny, and resilient. Yet, nature had other plans, and I now realize how unpredictable things can be. This tragedy 
underscores the growing impact of climate change, with extreme weather events becoming alarmingly more 
frequent and intense. One can only hope that authorities will take this as a call to action, improving early-warning 
systems to prevent such a loss of life in the future. The destruction went beyond human tragedy, with infrastructure, 
bridges, and public buildings heavily damaged, leaving scars that will take years to repair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re arriving at Valencia’s Airport (Aeroport), it’s an easy trip to the city center. Metro lines 3 and 5 will take you from Aeroport to North Station (Xàtiva) in just 21 minutes, covering Zone AB+. The fare is €5.80 per person.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve already described how to get from Valencia to Platja de Gandia—you can find the details in a &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2024/10/Gandia_Cullera/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. From the North Train Station (near the Xàtiva metro stop), we took the metro to Ayora and then walked about 2 km on foot. It wasn’t the fastest way to get to the Oceanarium, but we enjoyed the walk nonetheless. For a more convenient option, the tram stops right in front of the Oceanarium and takes around 15 minutes to reach the city center. It might be a better alternative for those who prefer a quicker journey.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Children under 10 may travel free of charge when accompanied by an adult with a valid transport ticket. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.miivomobility.com/en/blog/Tarjeta-SUMA-ventajas&quot;&gt;SUMA 10 for 10 rides&lt;/a&gt; Zona A - €8, currently €4 due to a discount (single ticket €1.50 in Zone A). It can be used to make up to 15 simultaneous trips by people traveling together.&lt;br /&gt;
Note: The temporary partial reduction of 50% applies to SUMA 10, SUMA Monthly, SUMA Monthly Jove, TuiN tickets, and temporary Metrovalencia season tickets until January 31, 2025. We bought a SUMA 10 card and used it for all four of us, which was considerably cheaper than buying single metro tickets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://oceanografic.experticket.com/en&quot;&gt;Oceanogràfic&lt;/a&gt; - €34.70 per adult, booked online a few days in advance for a specific time slot. This means you will only be able to access the Oceanogràfic from the time selected during the purchase process, and you may stay in the aquarium until closing time. We bought tickets with a time slot at 10:00 a.m. and entered before 11:00, but there were people next to us who couldn’t enter with a ticket for the 12:00 slot, so it’s important to select your time wisely. Prices vary depending on the day, holiday week, etc. We took a train from Gandia as described in my other post, and then metro from Xàtiva to Ayora, with the last part on foot (almost 2 km).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Pro Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; If you’re visiting during peak summer months (July/August), plan to arrive right when the park opens at 10:00 a.m. The first dolphin show around 11:00 a.m. is less crowded, so it’s worth catching early in the day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;La Lonja de la Seda de Valencia - €2 admission fee, quick visit (a few rooms and the main hall, small courtyard).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://visit-cullera.es/guia/castillo-de-cullera/&quot;&gt;Botanical Garden&lt;/a&gt;, entrance fee €3, free for babies and toddlers. If you’re fast, you can be done in 30 minutes, but if you take your time, I would plan for 2 hours. It’s a relatively small garden compared to others around the world, but definitely a must-see at a very cheap price! It wasn’t crowded during our Friday afternoon visit. Clean restrooms are available.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/11/Valencia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/11/Valencia/</guid>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Valencia</category>
        
        <category>Oceanarium</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
