<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Going beyond the known</title>
    <description>A travel blog by Monika Suchoszek.</description>
    <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 21:32:02 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 21:32:02 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weekend w Marsyli, najstarszym mieście Francji.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mały park z pozostałościami archeologicznymi obok Muzeum Historii Marsylii to miejsce, gdzie rozpoczęła się historia tego miasta. 
To właśnie tutaj, w tym konkretnym miejscu, pierwsi greccy osadnicy z Focji tchnęli życie w to miasto około 600 roku p.n.e., 
zakładając podwaliny pod to, co miało stać się tętniącym życiem portem Marsylii. Nadal można tam zobaczyć łódź w rzeczywistym 
rozmiarze, używaną przez Greków do żeglugi po wzburzonym Morzu Śródziemnym, aby dotrzeć do tej naturalnie spokojnej zatoki, 
doskonale chroniącej przed wiatrem i oferującej schronienie przybyszom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_112904.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niedaleko stąd, nowoczesny port tętni życiem. Widoczny z punktu widokowego “Mirador de Saint-Jean”, znajdującego się blisko 
fortyfikacji miasta, która prowadzi statki do wejścia do portu. Na końcu portu, nabrzeże Quai des Belges ożywa każdego poranka, 
gdy rybacy oferują tu swoje najświeższe połowy. W tym miejscu znajduje się również tablica upamiętniająca pierwszych przybyszów z Grecji.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103113.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103082.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103080.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103077.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dzielnica „Le Panier” znajdowała się w bezpośrednim sąsiedztwie naszego apartamentu, więc kilkakrotnie przechodziliśmy 
obok tego miejsca i zawsze gubiliśmy się w wąskich uliczkach, odkrywając nowe graffiti, kolorowe alejki i urocze butiki z 
mydłem marsylskim. W rzeczywistości oryginalne mydło marsylskie wygląda dość niepozornie, jest to po prostu duża kostka (300g) 
zielonkawego mydła o subtelnej woni. Jednakże tego właśnie potrzebuje twoja skóra, 72% oliwy z oliwek z pewnością 
odpowiednio ją nawilży oraz ukoi. Nie daj się zwieść wszystkim pięknym mydłom pełnym 
barwników, perfum czy syntetycznych dodatków. Oprócz uroczych małych sklepów, można w tej dzielnicy znaleźć rowniez małe galerie i 
interesujące kawiarnie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103093.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_125351.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103108.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_172204.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Przestrzeń przed Centrum Charytatywnym, opustoszała w listopadowym chłodzie, według naszego przewodnika, w miesiącach 
szczytu sezonu byłaby trudna do przejścia, gdy wszystkie restauracje i kawiarnie wystawiają tutaj swoje stoliki. Pod 
koniec jesieni, podobnie jak reszta dzielnicy La Panier, ten obszar pustoszeje, sklepy zamykają się a okolica ucicha, 
oczekując na wiosne po ktorej następi kilka pracowitych miesięcy. Jeszcze kilka lat temu można było w tej dzielnicy mieszkać, 
podpisując długoterminową umowę najmu, ale teraz większość domów jest oferowana tylko na Airbnb. Wynajem krótkoterminowy, nawet 
tylko pzrez kilka miesięcy, okazuje się znacznie bardziej opłacalny. Zauważyliśmy często na murach budynkow napis 
“Airbnb dehors”, co oznacza “precz z Airbnb”. Jasno podkreśla to, że lokalni mieszkańcy nie są zadowoleni ze zmian zachodzących 
w tej dzielnicy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103136.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103135.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ta wspaniała bazylika, Katedra La Major, została zbudowana w XIX wieku blisko fundamentów oryginalnego portu Marsylii. 
Kolory ścian są oszałamiające, szczególnie gdy podkreślone światłem zachodzącego słońca, które akcentuje różne kamienie 
żyte podczas budowy, która trwała ponad 40 lat. Nasz apartament znajdował się zaledwie kilkaset metrów od tej bazyliki, 
więc łatwo było nam do niej trafić, ponieważ 60-metrowa wieża bazyliki jest widoczna z wielu miejsc miasta. Okolica ta 
jest świetnym miejscem na wieczorny spacer podczas zachodu słońca, oferując piękne widoki na port, MUCEM i Cosquer Méditerranée 
tuż obok. Podłoga bazyliki zasługuje również na uwagę, gdyż ozdobiona jest wspaniałymi mozaikami.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_170032.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103065.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_130617.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gorąco polecamy wizytę na dachu Muzeum Cywilizacji Europy i Śródziemnomorza (MUCEM), do którego można dotrzeć przechodząc 
przez kładkę z Fortu św. Jana lub przez samo muzeum. Muzeum to ma fascynującą architekturę, przypomina z daleka ogromną 
gąbkę lub koralowce głębinowe. Będąc na dachu, który oferuje wolny dostęp, możesz rozkoszować się rozległymi widokami na 
miasto oraz port przez azurowe, zewnętrzne ściany budynku. To idealne miejsce na przerwę, aby podziwiać widoki! Kontrast 
między starożytnymi budowlami fortu a nowoczesnym muzeum jest widoczny, ale oba obiekty pięknie się uzupełniają. Kontynuując, 
eksplorowaliśmy wąskie ścieżki i ogrody na fortyfikacji miasta, odnajdując spokój i ciepło słońca w ustronnych zakątkach, 
gdzie nie docierał chłodny wiatr. Wiele punktów widokowych pozwoliło nam podziwiać zarówno Bazylikę Notre-Dame de la Garde, 
jak i Katedrę La Major. Obszar ten kryje wiele niespodzianek, znaleźliśmy tutaj urokliwy plac z fontanną, mural kobiety 
oraz mnóstwo roślin, które czynią to miejsce naprawdę wyjątkowym. Jest to miejsce warte odwiedzenia, jeśli szukasz ucieczki od 
zgiełku miasta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103117.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141649.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_135459.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103111.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bazylika Notre-Dame de la Garde, oferująca panoramiczny, 360-stopniowy widok na miasto, jest niewątpliwie miejscem, które 
koniecznie trzeba odwiedzić. Mimo że nie spędziliśmy wiele czasu wewnątrz kościoła, nie mogliśmy nie zauważyć fascynujących 
dekoracji, w tym statków zawieszonych na suficie, które podkreślają głębokie związki miasta z morzem. Koniecznie spójrz w 
górę – sufit zapiera dech w piersiach! Z zewnętrznego obszaru możesz podziwiać rozległą panoramę Marsylii, w tym nowy port 
dla statków wycieczkowych, położony w bardziej przemysłowej części miasta, która znajduje się kilka kilometrów od starego 
historycznego centrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141834.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_162108.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_161130.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103129.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Z tyłu kościoła roztacza się widok na Endoume, najbardziej prestiżową dzielnicę miasta, gdzie domy są ciasno zgrupowane, 
otoczone z jednej strony morzem a z drugiej górami. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103128.jpg&quot; /&gt;
Stadion Orange Velodrome i duże kompleksy mieszkalne zdecydowanie wyróżniały się wśród budynków po tej stronie miasta, 
z zapierającym dech w piersiach Parkiem Narodowym Calanques w tle, który był naszym celem na następny dzień.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103130.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kochamy naturę i wędrówki, więc zawsze staramy się łączyć krótkie wycieczki miejskie z przynajmniej jednym dniem spędzonym 
na łonie natury. Park Narodowy Calanques, położony między Marsylią a Cassis, był oczywistym wyborem po przejrzeniu mapy 
okolic miasta. Główne aktywności dostępne w tym parku narodowym to piesze wędrówki, wspinaczka skalna, pływanie i kajakarstwo. 
Ostre, białe klify i czysta woda u ich podnóża tworzą wspaniały widok, który można podziwiać wędrując szlakiem. “Calanque” 
to unikalny typ formacji geologicznej z wapienia znajdującej się wzdłuż wybrzeża Morza Śródziemnego. Pierwsze zdjęcie 
poniżej pokazuje główny punkt widokowy, Sugiton, który jest najbardziej dostępnym miejscem, znajdującym się około 2,5 km 
od przystanku autobusowego. Stamtąd można również zejść na plażę (dodatkowy 1 km) lub przedłużyć spacer o kilka-kilkanascie 
kilometrów w stronę Cassis, podążając głównym szlakiem GR. To była nasza decyzja i wcale tego nie żałowaliśmy! Ścieżka 
była bardzo kamienista i wymagająca, z wieloma stromymi i wąskimi odcinkami, ale fantastyczne widoki w pełni wynagrodziły 
wysiłek. Niestety, musieliśmy wrócić tą samą drogą, ponieważ nie byliśmy pewni, dokąd prowadzą inne ścieżki; Google Maps 
tym razem nie było zbyt pomocne, a poleganie wyłącznie na oznaczeniach na skałach nie wystarczało do nawigacji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113218.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113224.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113148.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113215.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_152147.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113195.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podczas naszego drugiego wieczoru odwiedziliśmy muzeum repliki Jaskini Cosquer (Villa Méditerranée), znajdujące się zaledwie 
kilkaset metrów od naszego apartamentu. W 1985 roku jaskinię odkrył Henri Cosquer, entuzjasta nurkowania, który znalazł jej
wejście prowadzące do ogromnej zatopionej galerii. Ten niemal 175-metrowy korytarz odsłonił prawdziwy skarb datowany na 
30 000 lat, zawierający ponad 480 dzieł, w tym malowidła i grawery przedstawiające pingwiny, jelenie, kozice, bizonów, 
jak również odciski dłoni i ślady ogniska. W tamtym czasie poziom morza był około 120 metrów niższy niż dzisiaj, a wody 
znajdowały się kilka kilometrów dalej. Jednak z powodu podnoszenia się poziomu morza to prehistoryczne miejsce jest zagrożone 
zatopieniem, niektóre malowidła są już częściowo poniżej poziomu wody. Pilne zatem stało się zachowanie oraz udostępnienie 
tego niesłychanego odkrycia światu. Obecnie jaskinia nie jest dostępna dla publiczności, a jej wejście zostało zamknięte 
dla jej ochrony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wynajęliśmy apartament na Airbnb w dzielnicy La Joliette, zaledwie kilka budynków od Katedry Marsylskiej, znajdujący 
się na 6. piętrze bez windy. Zauwazylismy wiele podobnych ofert wynajmu. To może nie być najlepsze rozwiązanie dla osób z dużą 
ilością bagażu lub dla rodzin z dziećmi. Kiedy ruch morski przekroczył pojemność Starego Portu, założono nowy, a nasz 
apartament znajdował się tuż przy wejściu do tego ogromnego portu. Dworzec kolejowy ‘Saint-Charles’ jest w odległości 
15-20 minut spacerem, więc nawet nie rozważaliśmy korzystania z transportu publicznego.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wycieczka z przewodnikiem &lt;a href=&quot;https://marseillefreewalkingtour.com/&quot;&gt;Marseille Free Walking Tour&lt;/a&gt; trwala ok 2.5 godziny i bardzo polecamy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delicious patisserie La Pâtisserie des Marseillais &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lapatisseriedesmarseillais.fr/&quot;&gt;Pascal Guglielmi&lt;/a&gt; zdecydowanie warta odwiedzenia!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Autobus numer 60, od przystanku Capitainerie do Bazyliki Notre-Dame de la Garde, oferuje prawie 20-minutową jazdę. 
Wstęp do kościoła jest bezpłatny. Spędziliśmy tylko około 15 minut w okolicy kościoła z powodu silnego, zimnego wiatru, 
a następnie wróciliśmy tym samym biletem, który był ważny przez 1 godzinę. Gdy ponownie wsiedliśmy do autobusu, 
zeskanowaliśmy nasz bilet, ale nie został on obciążony, i mogliśmy z niego skorzystać następnego dnia w metrze. Każdy 
zakupiony przez nas bilet był ważny na 2 przejazdy, ale maszyna oferuje wiele opcji przy wyborze liczby przejazdów. 
Dla osób z dziećmi świetną opcją jest skorzystanie z małego pociągu ze Starego Portu (znajdującego się naprzeciwko 
ratusza w Marsylii), który podjeżdża pod samą bazylikę!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Korzystając z linii metra 2 z Joliette do Castellane, a następnie z autobusu B1, po 30-40 minut jazdy w kierunku 
Campus de Luminy, dotarliśmy do przystanku Luminy – PN des Calanques. Nasza wędrówka po Parku Narodowym Calanques, 
około 16 km, trwała 5-6 godzin z przerwami. Na poniższej mapie, która pokazuje naszą trasę, widoczna jest małą odnogą 
wskazującą punkt widokowy Belvédère de Sugiton, popularne miejsce wśród wielu odwiedzających. Jest łatwo dostępny, 
gdyż widzieliśmy ludzi z psami i niemowlakami w wózkach, jednak solidne koła będą niezbędne. Teren jest bardzo skalisty, 
więc noszenie butów trekkingowych jest zdecydowanie zalecane. Należy uważnie patrzeć na oznaczenia szlaku, ponieważ kilka 
razy przypadkowo zaczęliśmy wspinać się na skały niebędące częścią szlaku (oznaczenia szlaku nie zawsze były jasne i 
wiele z nich było uszkodzonych). Pogoda była niesamowita, piękny słoneczny dzień w listopadzie z przyjemnymi temperaturami. 
Jednak dalej musieliśmy wziąć pod uwagę wczesny zachód słońca o tej porze roku, aby uniknąć problemów, ponieważ nie 
mieliśmy czołówek.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 210407.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 214111.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113202.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113217.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replika Jaskini &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grotte-cosquer.com/en/homepage/&quot;&gt;The Cosquer Cave&lt;/a&gt; w Villa Méditerranée oferuje zwiedzanie 
tego miejsca słuchając audioprzewodnika w języku angielskim podczas 35-minutowej przejażdżki łodzią, podczas której 
zwiedzający mają możliwość odkrycia ponad 400 dzieł na ścianach jaskini. Następnie, w amfiteatrze pokazywany jest 
film dokumentalny opowiadający o odkryciu jaskini przez Henri’ego Cosquer. Niestety, film jest po francusku, a angielskie 
napisy na małych telewizorach obok dużego ekranu, bardzo utrudniają jednoczesne oglądanie filmu i czytanie tekstu na 
innych ekranach. Kolejne rozczarowanie czekało na nas w następnym pomieszczeniu, gdzie krótkie filmy przedstawiały krok 
po kroku tworzenie repliki jaskini, bez napisów w języku angielskim. Ponadto, prezentujący wyjaśniał techniki używane 
do replikowania oryginalnej jaskini, ale ponownie, tylko po francusku. Dlatego czuliśmy, że nie mogliśmy w pełni 
doświadczyć potencjału muzeum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2023/12/Marsylia-Francja/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2023/12/Marsylia-Francja/</guid>
        
        <category>Francja</category>
        
        <category>Marsylia</category>
        
        <category>Calanques</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weekend in Marseille: Exploring the Oldest City of France</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The small park with archaeological remains next to the Marseille History Museum is the place where the story of Marseille began. 
It was here, in this very spot, that the first Greek settlers from Phocaea breathed life into the city around 600 BC, 
laying down the roots of what would become the bustling port of Marseille. You can still see the 
real-size boat used by Greeks to sail on rough Mediterranean Sea to get to this naturally tranquil bay, offering 
excellent protection from the wind and providing shelter to outlanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_112904.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a stone’s throw away, the modern port buzzes with activity, visible from the “Mirador de Saint-Jean,” viewpoint close to 
city fortification that is guiding ships to the entrance of the port. 
At the port’s end, the Quai des Belges comes alive each morning as fishermen hawk their freshest catch. Here also stands 
a memorial honoring those first adventurous Greek settlers, commemorating their foundational role in the city’s history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103113.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103082.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103080.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103077.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The district of ‘Le Panier’ was in direct neighborhood to our apartment, so we found ourselves wandering through this area a few times,  always 
getting lost in the narrow streets, while discovering some new graffiti, colorful alleys and charming boutiques with Marseille soap. Actually 
the original Marseille soap looks very boring, just large cube (300g) of greenish soap that has subtle scent. However, this is exactly
what your skin needs, 72% of olive oil will definitely moisturize your skin properly and a true panacea for the skin. Don’t be 
attracted by all beautiful soaps
full of colouring, perfume or synthetic additives. Besides cute little shops, you can also find here small galleries and 
interesting cafés.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103093.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_125351.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103108.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_172204.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Old Charity Center’s forecourt, deserted in the chill of November, our guide assured us, would be difficult to pass 
during high season months when all restaurants and cafés put their tables out here. In late autumn, much like the rest of the Le Panier district, this area empties out, with shops closing and the neighborhood 
quieting down, awaiting the vibrancy of spring and several busy months to follow. A few years ago, it was still possible 
to live there, signing a long-term lease, but now the majority of homes are listed on Airbnb. Short-term rentals, even 
just for a few months, prove to be far more profitable than renting to permanent city residents. We noticed often “Airbnb 
dehors” spray-painted on the walls, which translates to “Airbnb go away”. A clear statement by locals who cherish 
living here, but find it less and less affordable to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103136.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103135.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This magnificent basilica, the Cathedral of La Major, was built in the 19th century near the foundation of the original 
Marseille port. The colors of the walls were stunning, especially when highlighted by the sunset light that accentuated 
the different stones used in the construction, which lasted more than 40 years to complete.
Our apartment was just a few hundred meters from this basilica, so we never got lost as its 60-meter-high tower was very 
easy to spot. The surrounding area is a great place for an evening walk during the sunset, offering lovely views of the 
port, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mucem.org/&quot;&gt;MUCEM&lt;/a&gt;, and Cosquer Méditerranée just next to it. The floor of the basilica is adorned with magnificent mosaics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_170032.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103065.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_130617.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We highly recommend visiting the rooftop of the Museum of Civilizations of Europe and the Mediterranean (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mucem.org/&quot;&gt;MUCEM&lt;/a&gt;), which 
you can reach via a catwalk from Fort St. Jean or through the museum itself. This museum has fascinating architecture, 
resembling a huge sponge or deep-water corals from a distance. Once on the rooftop, which offers free access, you can 
soak in the expansive views of the city, harbor, and fort through the intricate outer metal walls. It’s the perfect spot 
for a break to enjoy the views! This contrast between the fort’s old buildings and the modern museum complements each 
other beautifully. As we continued, we explored the narrow paths and gardens, finding the tranquility and warmth of 
the sun in secluded corners where the wind couldn’t reach us. Multiple viewpoints allowed us to admire both the Basilica 
of Notre-Dame de la Garde and the Cathedral of la Major. Our exploration was full of surprises, from hidden squares with 
fountains to murals of women and an abundance of plants that made this place truly unique. It’s a must-visit if you’re 
looking to escape the city’s bustle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103117.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141649.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_135459.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103111.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Basilica of Notre-Dame de la Garde, offering a 360-degree view of the city, is undoubtedly a must-visit destination. 
Although we didn’t spend much time inside the church, we couldn’t help but notice the fascinating decorations, including 
ships suspended from the ceiling, which emphasize the city’s deep connection to the sea. Make sure to look up—the ceiling 
is breathtaking! From the outdoor area, you can take in the extensive panorama of Marseille, including the new cruise port 
situated in a more industrial part of the city, which lies beyond walking distance from the old historic center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141834.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_162108.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_161130.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103129.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the back side of the church, the view opens up to Endoume, the city’s most prestigious neighborhood, where houses are 
densely nestled together, surrounded by the sea and mountains&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103128.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Orange Velodrome Stadium and big apartment complexes were definitely standing out among the buildings on this side of 
the city with the stunning Calanques National Park in the backdrop, our destination the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103130.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We love nature and hiking, so we always try to combine short city trips with at least one day spent in nature. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.calanques-parcnational.fr/en&quot;&gt;Calanques 
National Park&lt;/a&gt;, located between Marseille and Cassis, was the obvious choice after examining the map of the city’s surroundings. 
Hiking, rock climbing, swimming, and canoeing are the primary activities available in this national park. The sharp, white 
cliffs and the clear waters at their base create a magnificent view that you can enjoy along the hiking path. A ‘calanque’ 
is a unique type of geological formation made of limestone found along the Mediterranean coast. The first photo below shows 
the main viewpoint, Sugiton, which is the most accessible one at approximately 2.5 km from the bus stop. From here, you can 
also descend to the beach (about an extra 1 km) or extend your walk by several more kilometers toward Cassis, following the 
main GR trail. That was our choice, and we didn’t regret it at all! The path was very rocky and demanding, with many steep 
and narrow parts, but the fabulous views were well worth the effort. Unfortunately, we had to retrace our steps because we 
were unsure of where the other paths led; Google Maps wasn’t very helpful this time, and relying solely on the markers on 
the rocks wasn’t sufficient for navigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113218.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113224.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113148.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113215.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_152147.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113195.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our second evening, we spent time at the Cosquer Cave replica museum, located just a few hundred meters from our apartment. 
In 1985, the cave was discovered by Henri Cosquer, a diving enthusiast, who found the entrance leading to an immense submerged 
gallery. This nearly 175-meter-long passage unveiled a real treasure dating back 30,000 years, featuring over 480 
pieces including paintings and engravings of penguins, deer, ibex, bison, as well as hand prints and traces of a fireplace. 
At that time, the sea level was about 120 meters lower than it is today, and the shoreline was several kilometers 
distant. However, due to rising sea levels, this prehistoric site is at risk of vanishing, with some artworks already 
partially submerged. The urgency to preserve and share this unparalleled discovery with the world has become urgent. 
Currently, the cave is not accessible to the public, and its entrance has been sealed for its protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We rented an apartment on Airbnb in the La Joliette neighborhood, just a few buildings away from Marseille Cathedral, 
located on the 6th floor without an elevator. There were many similar rental offers. This might not be the best solution 
for people with a lot of luggage or those with children. When maritime traffic exceeded the capacity of the Old Port, 
a new one was established, and our apartment was situated right at the entrance to this vast port. The ‘Saint-Charles’ 
train station is within a 15-20 minute walk, so we didn’t even consider using public transportation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guided tour &lt;a href=&quot;https://marseillefreewalkingtour.com/&quot;&gt;Marseille Free Walking Tour&lt;/a&gt; for about 2.5hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delicious patisserie La Pâtisserie des Marseillais &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lapatisseriedesmarseillais.fr/&quot;&gt;Pascal Guglielmi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bus number 60, from the Capitainerie bus stop to the Basilica of Notre-Dame de la Garde, offers an almost 20-minute ride. There is no entrance fee for the church. We only spent about 15 minutes in the area around the church due to the strong winds 
and cold weather, and we returned using the same ticket, which was valid for 1 hour.
When we boarded the bus again, we scanned our ticket, but it wasn’t charged, and we were able to use it the next day for the metro. 
Each ticket we bought was valid for 2 rides, but the machine offers multiple options when selecting the number of rides. For 
those with children, taking the small train from the old port (located directly across from the city hall in Marseille) 
is a great option!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take Metro line 2 from Joliette to Castellane, and then catch bus B1 for a 30-40 minute ride in the direction of Campus de 
Luminy, getting off at the Luminy – PN des Calanques stop. Our hike in the Calanques National Park covered approximately 
16 km (5-6 hours including breaks). On the map below, which highlights our route, you’ll notice a small branch indicating 
the Belvédère de Sugiton viewpoint, a popular destination for many visitors. It’s quite accessible; we saw people with prams, 
but sturdy wheels are essential. The area is very rocky, so wearing good trail running or hiking shoes is crucial for safety. 
Be vigilant for trail markers, as we accidentally started climbing rocks not part of the trail a few times (the trail markers 
are not always clear, and many have been damaged). We were fortunate to have amazing weather, a beautiful sunny day in November 
with pleasant temperatures. However, we had to be mindful of the early sunset at this time of year to avoid any problems, 
since we did not have headlights&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 210407.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 214111.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113202.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113217.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The replica of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grotte-cosquer.com/en/homepage/&quot;&gt;The Cosquer Cave&lt;/a&gt; in Villa Méditerranée offers an 
engaging audio guide in English for a 35-minute boat 
ride, during which visitors can explore over 400 works on the cave’s walls. Afterwards, there’s a documentary film in 
an amphitheater that chronicles the cave’s discovery by Henri Cosquer. Unfortunately, the film is in French, and English 
subtitles are provided on small TVs adjacent to the big screen, making it challenging to watch the film and read the text 
on the other screens simultaneously. Another disappointment awaited us in the next room, where short films depicted the 
step-by-step creation of the cave’s replica without any English subtitles. Additionally, a presenter explained the 
techniques used to replicate the original cave, but once again, only in French. This was similar to the rest of the 
text displayed on the gallery walls. Therefore, we felt as though we couldn’t fully experience what the museum is offering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/12/Marseille-France/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/12/Marseille-France/</guid>
        
        <category>France</category>
        
        <category>Marseille</category>
        
        <category>Calanques</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Peaceful Dutch countryside close to Belgium border</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;May holds a special place in my heart, not only because it marks my birthday but also because it offers plenty of long 
weekends, making it the perfect time for local trips. This year, we set our sights on the tranquil countryside surrounding 
Breda, a charming city in the Netherlands. As we left the highway, the landscape 
changed to large farmhouses with many horse and a tractors dotting the fields. Our adventure began right away as we 
admired the rural landscape while walking around the place we stayed. Natuurgebied Pannenhoef was our first destination, 
a green area on the map that turned out to be a nice place for walks and bird watching. We not only saw birds but also 
horses and sheep. It had really beautiful surroundings with many cycling routes and wooden bridges. Along the narrow paths, 
we discovered small benches strategically placed in the most breathtaking spots. These hidden resting spots offered the 
perfect opportunity to pause and enjoy the best views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230429_163700.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230429_165908.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230429_161342.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hetaardbeienterras.nl/&quot;&gt;The Strawberries Terrace&lt;/a&gt; was situated just several hundred meters from our rented house, so it was an obvious choice 
for the next day’s visit. The picnic area around the strawberry farm is great, with lots of toys for kids and bikes in 
different sizes. We were there at the very beginning of the strawberry season, and it was still not allowed to pick them 
ourselves, which is the biggest attraction of this place. Fresh strawberries were on sale, but you could taste the 
difference; they were not as sweet as we would have liked, but the really sunny days were just starting. Our main 
disappointment was regarding the food. We ordered waffles with whipped cream, and both were of very poor quality. 
Simply re-selling waffles from the supermarket is really not acceptable to us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_114407.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_114300.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_114314.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we know how much our daughter enjoys looking at animals, we found a perfect place to visit: a children’s farm called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://leijhoeve.nl/&quot;&gt;Kinderboerderij Leijhoeve&lt;/a&gt;. Well-maintained playgrounds, a small café with affordable prices, a 
mushroom forest, and especially a meadow with goats accessible for petting made this place so interesting. It’s really 
quiet there. You can just sit and enjoy the coffee while your kids are running around. You can keep a good eye on them 
from the terrace. The place is run by disabled people, and it looks like they do a very good job!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_145356.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_150442.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_151727.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_152056.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_145724.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying close to Breda was our intention to have some backup places to visit in case of bad weather, or mostly to have 
options for indoor playgrounds. However, the weather was so nice that instead, we walked through the city park, passed 
by the castle, and ended up at the Italian restaurant on the main market. Afterwards, we took a short walk on the 
shopping streets situated around the main church and then headed back to our place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_160527.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230430_174142.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our last day, after checking out early in the morning, we drove towards Grenspark Kalmthoutse Heide, a national park 
situated on the Belgian-Dutch border. The hiking trail “Dune” was our choice, leading through vast heathlands which are a 
popular attraction in late summer when the purple flowers bloom. At this time of the year, the landscape was quite monotonous, with green and 
brown dominating the scenery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, once we reached the dunes, it became more interesting, especially for our toddler who loved this giant sandbox. 
It was less enjoyable for me, as I was carrying her in the carrier, and the extra 12kg made my feet sink deeper into the 
sand. Oh, my calves were burning the next day! It’s worth noting that dogs are not allowed on this hike because it passes 
through a grazing area, even though we didn’t see any animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_113319.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_150355.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_113815.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_132917.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_121422.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May truly proved to be the ideal time for local trips, allowing us to immerse ourselves in nature’s embrace while creating 
cherished memories along the way. I found myself eagerly looking forward to my next adventure. This time, the excitement 
was amplified as it marked my first weekend trip without my daughter. It was a chance to immerse myself in the vibrant 
energy of Paris, accompanied by a friend. With a mere 36 hours in the City of Light, we were determined to make every 
moment count and create lasting memories. More details in upcoming post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We rented a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hoevenelleveld.nl&quot;&gt;cottage house on Airbnb close to Rijsbergen&lt;/a&gt;, only a 1.5-hour drive from 
Leuven. The house had an amazing playground for kids, and there were two horses, chickens, and a dog living on the farm. 
It was a very quiet area, perfect for cycling and running. Every morning and around sunset, we could see hot air balloons 
on the horizon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our hike in Kalmthoutse Heide park was about 8km. We parked next to the Kalmthout Visitor’s Center (free parking but 
  it’s better to be there early in the morning as it gets very crowded around lunchtime). We got a little bit lost around 
  the 4km mark, as you can see on the map. We turned left too quickly and ended up at the parking area, but we were actually 
  supposed to follow the long path through the park before turning left to reach the dunes. This part of the hike was not 
  marked clearly enough for us. It would have been much easier if maps of the trails were available in more places. We 
  didn’t take a photo of the trail at the entrance to the park, and that would have helped us greatly. You can find more 
  hikes with detailed descriptions on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://grensparkkalmthoutseheide.com/en/wandelroutes/0&quot;&gt;park’s website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/20230501_150346.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/Screenshot 2023-05-02 215019.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are several parking spaces around Natuurgebied Pannenhoef. We left our car once at Pannenhoef Parkeerplaats het 
Vaartven. This is not a proper parking lot, just some spaces between trees where you are allowed to park, and I can 
imagine it can be difficult to drive there after rain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every evening, I went for a run in the surroundings of the nature reservoir Pannenhoef and Rijsbergen city. Below 
are the maps of my runs, both around 8km. The first one, in the nature reservoir, was very nice, mainly exploring wetlands. 
On the second day, I headed towards the mini zoo that we visited, trying to use small paths that crossed the surrounding 
fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/Screenshot 2023-06-14 204244.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/IMG_20230429_195444_469.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/IMG_20230429_200134_380.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Breda/Screenshot 2023-06-14 204339.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/05/Breda-Netherlands/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/05/Breda-Netherlands/</guid>
        
        <category>Netherlands</category>
        
        <category>Breda</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tips to make travelling with the baby or toddler easier</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We had to change our way of travelling and adjust to the needs of our little one. People always say that you can keep travelling
even after you became a parent. Yes, it’s true, you can … but it will not be the same! Our holidays now are less intense, we are visiting
kids-friendly places where we can have realistic chances to relax and have a break. A bored, tired or frustrated toddler will 
not allow you to do so! We are travelling on regular basis from Belgium to Poland to visit my family. The first time we went 
to Poland when our daughter was 3 months old. We also managed to go twice for holidays in Europe: to Lisbon (at 6 months 
old) and Malaga (at 14 months). Both trips were very different because of the baby’s age, but also because we have 
learned a lot during the first trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are our tips for the flight itself?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take in consideration the time of the flight and if it will fit with yours baby daily routine. E.g. we don’t book flights
with departures time before 10am or after 4pm (which limits our options considerably!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always travel with the buggy and baby carrier (we switch to the carrier while boarding the plane). Do note that
even though you are allowed to take the carrier up to the plane, you are required to get a label for it before going 
through security from the check-in desk. In theory, you are allowed
to take 1 small bag when you buy infant ticket (under age of 2) but we always had a small additional cotton bag with all the 
little one’s food and drinks, no one ever complained (in case there would be an issue, all things would comfortably
fit in our luggage). In general, the less luggage you have the better. We have standard carry-on bags when 
traveling for a week (1 small backpack per person) and it’s really enough! Once you reach your destination, it’s time to 
find your buggy. Every airport have them in a different spot, usually together with oversized luggage but never next 
to the plane. This is why having a carrier can be extremely helpful as sometimes it’s a really long walk from the plane 
to the baggage reclaim. It’s also useful to have small blanket to cover the baby while boarding the plane, sometimes it’s very 
windy, and you never know how long you’ll have to queue outside to get into the plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take enough water and snacks for your baby. According to TSA (Transportation Security Administration), there are no 
restrictions of liquids when you travel with 
kid under age of 12. Water is allowed in reasonable quantities. We usually have a 1 L bottle of water, an extra sippy cup 
already filled with water, soy milk in cardboard (250 mL), and 2-3 jars of baby food. As well some sandwiches, fruits and
veggies. This might look like a lot, but it is good to have some extras in case of emergency (unexpected delays or 
flight cancellation). Keeping the water and food in a separate cotton bag, is convenient as you’ll need to show all baby 
liquids at the security. If your baby is still on breast or formula, it’s good to give the milk during takeoff and 
landing. Apparently, babies can’t pop their ears intentionally, but we can help them by encouraging them to swallow. 
Flight attendant will provide some hot water to make your formula upon request. If you are breastfeeding, a big scarf 
and special bra will be helpful to give you some privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also helps to have a new small toy for your baby, they will have a better mood and hopefully will be occupied with the
new gift for quite some time :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are specific hints about the airports we’ve used so far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zaventem, Belgium - amazing playing area for kids next to the food corner (entrance next to the Starbucks). There is 
a microwave, high chairs, changing stations, big table for parents to sit, perfect place to wait for the flight! Going 
through securing was easy with the baby, all baby food and water was checked so better keep it in a separate bag for easy 
access.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pyrzowice, Poland - we didn’t find any playing area for toddlers, there are changing rooms. Security here is
inefficient and needlessly long. E.g. this is one of the few airports where they require shoes to be taken off and scanned. 
Expect long queues without a no priority line for families with kids.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lisbon, Portugal - there is a single special land for security checks for elderly, people in wheelchair and parents with 
babies, but be aware that it could take even longer than going by regular line as all the “slower people” will be 
in the special queue! They discourage this because there are a few steps down to get to the regular security check, 
which shouldn’t be an issue when travelling with a buggy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands - it’s the best airport for parents with babies when it comes to the security checks. 
The staff ensures parents with kids can move through security swiftly, and their modern scanners allow you to keep 
most things inside your backpacks/suitcases. They just check all baby food and water afterwards in the special machine.
It is always for us very nice experience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Malaga (AGP), Spain - There was enough space to comfortably sit at the airport but the playing area we found was 
very small and closed off for unknown reasons. Going through security was a pleasant experience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the important criteria when looking for accommodation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Airbnb is our favourite platform when travelling. When we went for you first trip to Lisbon, we thought that having an 
apartment in the city center will give us flexibility.
We could come back to the apartment, it will be close to the shops and restaurants. BUT, we didn’t predict that houses in 
the old part of the city have paper thin walls. It was so laud that we couldn’t sleep and our baby had even more problems with 
sleep. It also happened few time around midnight and early morning that people were discarding glass bottles outside, waking up
everyone in the neighborhood. Next time, we checked the reviews of the apartments carefully, looking for any clues about 
the noise level. Our apartment in Benalmadena was much better! It had bigger bedroom that even with extra travel cot had enough space 
to be comfortably used. This time we also stayed in quiet area next to the park (with animals and playground), the beach and 
bus stops (this time we also relied on public transportation). Dark curtains to make the apartment dark for our baby nap, 
was another useful feature of the apartment. A small kitchen for making breakfasts and snacks is always a must for us. 
A bigger shower helped us a lot when it comes to the evening baths, especially after playing on the beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arrived at your destination? What to do next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It always makes sense to search in advance for playgrounds in the areas that you are going to visit. Sometimes they can 
be really nice, perfect for a break with a toddler. Once babies start to walk, it becomes impossible to keep them long
in their stroller, they need to run and explore :D It’s useful to have a small blanket or sport towel to use in the parks 
for a break. Even if your baby is very small, it’s good for them to have a break for tummy time or play with their toys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As public toilets with changing stations are rare, having a changing mat is a must. The waterproof layer can
also come in handy as an extra layer while sitting on grass. Keep in mind that even in some restaurants toilets can
be very small and lack a changing station, in those cases you’ll also be happy you have your own mat with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Lisbon, all tourists attractions had a separate line for families, so we didn’t have to wait much at all. Also in the shops, people 
were letting us ahead, even if we didn’t ask them for this and that was really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20220221_163710.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20220215_153807.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We travel with both a buggy and baby carrier. It gives us the flexibility needed for visiting different kind of places. 
For example, it would not be possible to visits city center of Lisbon, Moorish Castle in Portugal or Calamorro Mountain 
in Spain with the buggy. On the other hand a buggy comes handy for long walks along the see or while visiting some sites like the
Jerónimos Monastery in Lisbon (which is perfectly suited for a buggy). The easiest way to make a decision 
“buggy or carrier?” is to check the reviews on the trip advisor or on Google and look for any that describes how kids-friendly a particular tourist attraction is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dreambaby.be/e/fr/db/dreambee-essentials-poussette-canne-grey-melange-214187?utm_source=google&amp;amp;utm_medium=shopping&amp;amp;s_kwcid=AL!6321!3!!!!x!!&amp;amp;gclid=CjwKCAiAheacBhB8EiwAItVO2yQ7N_C6VWkn4sxHW_TIX8rNzywIH3wWZIyx8EqOYPPCespcWfD0HxoCK10QAvD_BwE&quot;&gt;Buggy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com.be/-/en/BABYBJ%C3%96RN-Carrier-Black-Cotton-White/dp/B07KPSS456/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2Q7TKLKF68UZ8&amp;amp;keywords=BabyBj%C3%B6rn+carrier+one&amp;amp;qid=1671045227&amp;amp;sprefix=babybj%C3%B6rn+carrier+one%2Caps%2C60&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Baby Bjorn carrier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nanabeebi.com/en/products/luiertas-rugzak&quot;&gt;Nanabeebi backpack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2022 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/12/Travelling-toddler-tips/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/12/Travelling-toddler-tips/</guid>
        
        <category>plane</category>
        
        <category>toddler</category>
        
        <category>baby</category>
        
        <category>Malaga</category>
        
        <category>Lisbon</category>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our top 3 half-day trips from Benalmadena </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Malaga, and Benalmadena specifically, are nice places as a home-base for doing small trips in this part of Andalusia. We had 
three days, and we decided to spend each of the afternoons exploring another destination. You can easily do everything 
in half the time, but we didn’t want to rush with the baby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mijas-village&quot;&gt;Mijas Village&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first (and the best!) destination was Mijas village. Beautiful,
small village on the slopes of the mountain, white houses decorated with flowers in blue pots. Many shops with leather 
goods, nougat, spices, honey and other delicatessen produced locally. Amazing view of the coast and the mountains!
Definitely check Parque La Muralla with church Iglesia Inmaculada Concepción and amazing views of the mountains and Alboran 
Sea. I would highly recommend to get lost in the narrow streets of this cute village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_164928.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_165256.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_162249.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_173539.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_173301.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_160725.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_162008.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_160657.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_160454.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_161834.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_152929.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-colomares-monument-butterfly-park-and-stupa&quot;&gt;The Colomares Monument, Butterfly park and Stupa&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our second destination, the Colomares Monument is a castle-style monument honoring Christopher Columbus and his discovery of the new world, America. 
This monument was built between 1987 and 1994 by Esteban Martin Martin and his two co-workers. A great place to take some interesting pictures! 
It’s not big, but it feels intense because of the number of ornaments.  It is a mix of many architectural styles and materials: brick, 
stone and cement. One part of the monument resembles of the stern from La Santa Maria, the largest of the three Spanish 
ships used by Christopher Columbus in his first voyage across the Atlantic Ocean in 1492.  You can love it or hate it. 
We had vastly different opinions, so check it yourself in what camp you’ll fall!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154146.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154729.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154519.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154713.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_160055.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a 30-minute walk along the main road, we reached the Butterfly Park and Stupa of Enlightenment. At the entrance you will receive
a small list of different butterfly species with names and photos to see if you can spot all of them. This place looks 
like a big greenhouse, very hot and humid with a lot of plants, not unlike being in a tropical forest.
The most spectacular species we spotted were &lt;em&gt;Greta Oto&lt;/em&gt;, a butterfly with transparent wings, the bright blue 
&lt;em&gt;Morpho pheleides&lt;/em&gt; and the black &lt;em&gt;Parides iphidamas&lt;/em&gt; with its big red dots on the wings. Besides the butterflies, you 
can see their small wallaby and very colorful, rainbow finches, both native to Australia. It’s a great place for older 
kids. Young toddlers can have difficulties to spot the butterflies and if they do, you need to be careful and not let 
them damaged the fragile butterflies as some do get very close to visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_164017.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_164638.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_165254.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_170245.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_164147.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_174647.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;el-calamorro-monte&quot;&gt;El Calamorro Monte&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El Calamorro Monte, panoramic view of Benalmadena. It has several access points, but we decided to take the Benalmádena Cable Car, 
which runs along its slope from Arroyo de la Miel (next to the old Tivoli amusement park) to the very top of the mountain 
(approximately 780 metres above the see level). There are a few beautiful view points and a show featuring birds of prey at the top.
You can also start hiking from there in various directions or even cycle downhill (you can take your bike by cable car, 
though you might need to detach a wheel to get it in the cabin). We were too late for last show with birds of prey 
(3:00 pm) but we enjoyed a small tour around the peak, remember to take some extra clothes, with wind and clouds 
accumulating around the peak, it can get chilly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_151532.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_154359.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_160116.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_160633.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_163236.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_161609.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Playground, Patio de Juegos, next to Parque La Muralla in Mijas. We spend there a lot of time, this amazing playground has
attractions for each age group. Our one-year-old baby loved it and it not so easy to find a playground that suits her age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_164100.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.castillomonumentocolomares.com/&quot;&gt;Castillo Colomares&lt;/a&gt;  - entry 3 euro per adult, 2 euro for seniors and kids&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Butterfly Park - we bought tickets online, 8.50 euro per adult, seniors 7.50 euro. The online ticket system was a 
little strange. After paying, you should get a code via mail that can be redeemed for the tickets at the reception… We never got that mail though.
As for the tickets with PayPal fortunately the order ID was also included in the PayPal order confirmation. You need to buy tickets at 
least one hour before the visit. More on the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mariposariodebenalmadena.com/en/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Benalmadena cable car - tickets bought on spot, 16.90 euro per adult, seniors 12.90 euro&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can check how to travel by bus by reading practical info section of my related &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2022/10/Benalmadena-Spain/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;
It took us 40 min from Benalmadena to Mijas (Butterfly park was half-way to Mijas) by line 121, 126&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/11/Benalmadena-trips/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/11/Benalmadena-trips/</guid>
        
        <category>Mijas</category>
        
        <category>Benalmadena</category>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Colomares</category>
        
        <category>Monument</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Banalmadena, perfect autumn destination for a sunny holiday!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After planning all our trips to Poland for the remaining of the year, we still had approximately a week of holidays left,
so we decided to find some nice, warm place to visit in Europe. After checking all possible flight connections 
from the nearest airport, we decided to go for the warmest option, the south of Spain. Our destination, Benalmadena, had 
everything we needed: easy connection by train from the airport, beach, mountains, many shops and restaurants, 
few tourist attractions nearby and plenty of options for the nice accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This city is located approximately 20 km from Malaga where you can get easily by the same train that goes to the airport. 
We were pleasantly surprise by the weather, it was more than 20°C with no rain, and it was the beginning of November! There 
was no need to rent a car since train connection was so convenient. I had a list of places to visit prepared in 
advance, and we actually managed to see all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day we spent on exploring the city, doing some shopping and buying bus card that would allow us to travel cheaper, 
more information in the section at the end of the post. We particularly liked the marina that surprised us by very 
original shape and style of the buildings. There are plenty of shops and restaurants. In the evening the main promenade turned into small
market with (fake?) shoes, clothes or purses of well known designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_093340.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_172138.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_171721.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_173429.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_174142.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_173641.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parque de la Paloma, full of green parrots, rabbits, ducks, seagulls and dogs was our favourite destination in the
early mornings when our daughter was full of energy and couldn’t stay any longer in the apartment. The entrance 
to the park was just in front of our hotel. We were going to the playgrounds, the succulent garden or just watching green 
parrots, fooling around. Can you see them on the last photo? They were perfectly matching the color of the grass :)
The park was very clean and well-maintained, turning into huge picnic area during the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_091520.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_092653.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_093145.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_093201.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_092936.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_100804.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During next the days, we were checking nearby tourist attractions, going everywhere by bus. There is a separate post
describing these small trips &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2022/11/Benalmadena-trips/&quot;&gt;around Benalmadena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent last day of our holidays on wandering in Malaga; the city where Pablo Picasso was born. Our main goal was visiting Alcazaba,
Moorish fortress with city view. On the way there, we stopped by the main cathedral in the city (Catedral de la Encarnación 
de Málaga) though we didn’t check the church inside. Once we noticed soon after an ancient Roman theater, we knew it’s already Alcazaba.
Firstly, we were not sure if it’s possible to even visit this place with the buggy but there was a sign pointing to the back entrance where you can take a  lift,
so we gave it a try. Once up there, the areas you can easily access with a buggy (or for visitors in a wheelchair) are limited. 
While the stairs were not huge, and could be taken with a buggy, repeating this over and over however made 
our walk down challenging. As our pram is light, we were able to fold it and carried it down with us while our daughter was walking, 
avoiding the trip back down with the elevator, but we would not recommend visiting the castle if
your baby can’t walk unless you take a carrier instead of a buggy. While I was walking amongst narrow streets of the 
old part of Malaga during Laura’s nap, Sebastian visited the Picasso Museum. Even in November, it was crowded inside (mostly 
because of the school trips). Downtown Malaga would be nice for shopping, eating some local specialties, but didn’t make much of an impression on us. 
The city was already decorated with Christmas lights and many poinsettia, but we can’t tell how it looked at
night since we left before it got dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_104452.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_103845.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_104558.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_113539.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_113827.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_114324.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_114023.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_142240.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_143907.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_150056.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t miss out on the opportunity to visit this vibrant and welcoming destination on your next European holiday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The airport has perfect connection with Malaga and nearby cities on the coast by train. Buying tickets was very easy,
someone from the train service told us to use one debet card and scan once for each person and then again while leaving 
the train station. Our card was charged exactly the price for signe ticket, 2.05 euro per person (20min ride). 
Train C1 Benalmádena-Arroyo de la Miel in Malaga (walking distance from to the old part of the city), 30min ride, 2.70 euro
More info about trains on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.malagaweb.com/transport/commuter-train-malaga.php&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We stayed at BenalBeach hotel, huge complex where many apartments were owned by private people and available on 
booking.com. We noticed that these apartment were renovated and had better reviews than ones still owned by the hotel.
There was a big garden in the middle part of the hotel complex and it was possible to walk through the garden to the gate 
leading directly to the beach (not accessible for the buggy). Huge amount of plants, water running in between and lights in
the evening surprised as a lot! You could feel like in the jungle, although the highest plants were really dusty.
Despite the fact that we were in the middle of the city, it was very quiet and nice area, next to the beach, many 
restaurants and most importantly, just next to the only big park in the city center, Parque de la Paloma. I can only imagine
how crowded it can get on the beach or in the city during summer since there are many huge hotels, often 10
floors high. We felt like our hotel was mostly empty and every restaurant was trying to get our attention since not so many
tourists were walking around.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_140608.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_175542.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Playground
 Pocoyo Parque de Juegos, next to the bus stop Rotonda García Lorca - great for toddlers 1-3 years, crowded in the afternoons&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Buses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheapest and most convenient way of travelling by bus is by buying green bus card in Tobacco shops. You will pay 1.80 euro
as card deposit (you will get the cash back while returning the card). Then you need to charge the card with the amount
of money you wish, minimum 5 euro. Remember, money left on the card will not be paid back but you can charge your card 
again. For example, it is 0.79 euro per ride to Mijas, Butterfly Park and any other closer bus stop (ticket directly from 
the driver is 1.60 euro). This card can be used by the group of people, you just need to tell the driver how many people 
enter the bus, and he will print the number of tickets accordingly (each ticket notes the amount of money left to use). 
Note that this card gives discounts only for bus tickets
(not trains). In front of our hotel, there were taxis parked with predefined prices, see photo below. We couldn’t figure 
out what was the departure time of the bus based on the information from the bus schedule on the bus stop. The QR code 
listed on the board was extremely useful, immediately redirecting you the website with departure time of all buses from
particulat bus stop, including delays in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_090914.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_085802.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Museo Casa Natal de Picasso, more than 200 works donated by the members of Picasso’s family (including really early work).
Don’t expect the most famous works, but a nice overview of how he grew into the artist we all know.
Audio guide included in the ticket price, only listening to details on works that appeal to you, you can see everything 
in less than an hour. If you listen to more details it can take much longer. No entrance to the museum with any food or drinks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/10/Benalmadena-Spain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/10/Benalmadena-Spain/</guid>
        
        <category>Malaga</category>
        
        <category>Benalmadena</category>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Colomares</category>
        
        <category>Monument</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lisbon with a Little One: Our First Family Trip Abroad</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As my maternity leave was coming to an end, my partner and I were in dire need of a getaway from grey and rainy weather 
in Belgium. We set our sights on finding a destination that would offer warmth without being scorching hot, a short flight 
duration, excellent airport connections, and a perfect blend of natural beauty and cultural attractions. Lisbon, here we come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During our first walk through the city, we followed the main shopping street until we reached the Rua Augusta Arch, a stone memorial arch-like historical building 
that leads to an open waterfront square. This square, known as Praca do Comercio, is one of the largest squares in Europe 
and features a statue of King José I. In the neighborhood, there is also the famous Elevador de Santa Justa, which feels 
like an unnecessary invention since the street leading to the top of the hill is only a couple of hundred meters away, 
and there are many other places where an elevator would be much more useful. Unfortunately, the viewpoint of the Santa 
Justa lift was closed, so we immediately went to check out the Archaeological Museum, which is located on top of this
hill and has a charming square in front of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_143359.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/P2202412.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220220_104431.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_143543.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_142325.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220215_113256.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Carmo Ruins and Archaeological Museum are definitely worth checking out! It’s now the ruins of the old Church of the 
Convent of Santa Maria do Carmo, which was destroyed during the 1755 Lisbon Earthquake, leaving it without a roof. 
Reconstruction works started but were quickly abandoned, leaving the impressive naves uncovered and the chapels incomplete. 
The skeletal remains of the huge church serve as a testament to the destruction caused by the earthquake. Inside, there 
are five rooms with exhibitions featuring pieces from various periods and cultures, such as a Peruvian mummy and a sarcophagus 
from the 4th century. Some walls are decorated with large and beautiful azulejos tiles. The outside area is beautiful and 
perfect for capturing interesting pictures. The entry fee is €5 per adult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220215_105004.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220215_110108.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220215_110618.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisbon has so many hills and steep stairs! However, this means that everyone will have a chance to find their favorite 
viewpoint as there are plenty to choose from. Jardim da Cerca da Graça, with a small park around it, was only a 5-minute 
walk from our apartment. It was a steep uphill walk, but the nearby area was filled with restaurants, small bakeries, 
and shops offering fresh fruits and vegetables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220213_104549.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_103645.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alfama is another interesting neighborhood full of narrow streets, stretching just below the castle and featuring a few 
viewpoints: Miradouro de Santa Luzia and Miradouro das Portas do Sol. Get lost in the maze of narrow and beautiful streets 
and try cherry ginja and “salami” (a kind of cookie) at one of the old bakeries. There are plenty of typical shops, cafes, 
bars, and restaurants to explore. Additionally, Alfama is one of the places in Lisbon where you can experience fado shows. 
We saw offers for evening shows in front of small, typical restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part of the city was the only district to survive the great earthquake of 1755 and subsequent fires. The epicenter 
was in the middle of the Atlantic Ocean, and shortly afterwards, the biggest tsunami hit Lisbon. Almost all buildings in 
the city collapsed, were flooded by the water, or burned in the fires. However, Alfama remained in good condition because of 
solid stone structures and location, high enough, to avoid the tsunami.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_115837.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_123549.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220219_133329.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220219_135832.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_120850.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_132530.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_141758.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our apartment was less than a 15-minute walk from the famous São Jorge Castle. There were many peacocks living in the 
castle grounds, perched on trees and strolling among the visitors, proudly displaying their impressive tail feathers. 
The shaded gardens surrounding the castle’s defensive walls were a great place to seek refuge from the strong midday sun. 
From the terrace along the ramparts, there was a stunning view of central Lisbon and the Tagus River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the castle, there was a small exhibition showcasing items found within its walls. The streets surrounding the 
castle were incredibly charming. We arrived quite early, around 10 am, and the queue was already growing long. However, 
we were able to use the family line, which was nearly empty, and it worked wonderfully throughout Lisbon. If you want to 
avoid waiting in line to purchase tickets at the ticket office, I recommend buying them online in advance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_112808.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_115243.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_110505.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220214_120836.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/P2142370.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saved the Jerónimos Monastery and Belém Tower, two of the most visited sites in Lisbon, for the last day of our stay. 
First, we had to go and queue at the ticket office, and then, with our ticket, proceed to the entrance of the monastery. 
It was confusing because it wasn’t the same entrance. There was also another line to enter the Church of Santa Maria de 
Belém, but fortunately, this queue moved quite fast. The entrance to the church is free, and it’s worth stopping by. 
Inside, you can see a few tombs, including that of Vasco da Gama, the first European to reach India by sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, we finally made our way to the monastery, and once again, we didn’t have to wait long thanks to the family 
queue. However, we were somewhat disappointed when, after about 30-40 minutes, we realized that there wasn’t much else to 
see. Aside from the famous inner courtyard of the monastery, there weren’t many exhibits explaining the history of the 
place. The main attraction was simply walking through the upstairs and downstairs corridors and admiring the architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget to queue again for the famous pastéis at the legendary Pastéis de Belém down the road. Though these are the
original pastéis, we did have better ones from a small local bakery in Lisbon centre. There is a small park nearby where 
you can take a rest on a bench in the shade of the 
trees. We also took a walk to see the Belém Tower, but unfortunately, it was closed for renovation. However, we had a 
delightful lunch at the nearby restaurant, Adega de Belém, which was the perfect way to end our day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220217_122957.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220217_123535.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220217_125039.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220217_125812.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220217_130648.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220217_153226.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220217_155702.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220217_160832.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View from view point Miradouro de São Pedro de Alcântara, above Rossion station from where trains to Sintra leave.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220215_141206.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The airport has a perfect connection with the city via the metro. We purchased a rechargeable card called the Viva 
Viagem Card, which we used for both of us on the metro, tram, and train. The cost of this card is 0.50 euro. The train 
fare to Cascais/Sintra/Estoril is only 1.90 euro per person for a one-way trip. A single metro ride costs 1.35 euro. 
The tram fare to Belem was around 1.50 euro, but if you buy the ticket from the machine on the tram itself, it will 
be 3 euro. It’s definitely very convenient to have this card. It’s important to have an idea of the prices for each 
ride and your destination because you cannot get a refund for any remaining balance on the card. Each time you scan 
the card, you can see how much money is left on it. This is how we kept track of the fare for each ride and then 
recharged the card with additional funds. You can also use this card for the ferry, with prices ranging from 1 to 2 
euro.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We made a mistake by staying in the city center due to the noise that persisted until late evening hours. There were 
instances when glass was being discarded after midnight, likely when restaurants were closing. We could hear every 
step and conversation from the apartment above. Our initial plan was to stay in the city center so that we could 
easily return to the apartment in the middle of the day for our baby to nap in the crib. However, our baby ended 
up napping in our soft-structured carrier (BabyBjorn, model Baby Carrier One). When you primarily use a baby carrier, 
we highly recommend having a good changing mat, preferably waterproof. This way, you can use it on the grass for tummy 
time and allow your baby to stretch properly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220215_161658.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Lisbon/20220215_153807.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People in Lisbon were very friendly, both in the restaurants and shops. We were pleased to find special lines for people 
with kids, which meant we didn’t have to wait at the entrance of any tourist attractions. However, it was almost impossible 
to find a restaurant with a baby changing station in the restroom. Furthermore, the restroom facilities were often small 
and cramped, making it challenging to change the little one’s diaper. Due to limited space in the city center, the restaurants 
had tables quite close to each other so sitting inside with the pram was almost impossible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/03/Lisbon-Portugal/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/03/Lisbon-Portugal/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>Lisbon</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Camping in the Ardennes, visiting caves and trekking around beautiful lakes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dinant, birthplace of saxophone inventor Adolphe Sax was our first destination on the way to the Ardennes. After a nice 20min walk
along the riverside from the car parking, we had reached the center of the city with the famous Citadel above our heads on the 
truly imposing rock. It is worth to walk first to the other side of the Meuse river over the Charles-de-Gaulle Bridge to have a look 
at catholic church Notre Dame de Dinant, which is located at the foot of the Citadel, from a different perspective. There are many colorful saxophones on the 
bridge, each represents different country through its unique colors and patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_115550_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_120603_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After purchasing tickets in the office
and climbing 408 stairs, we reached the top of the Citadel to enjoy beautiful view of the surroundings. There are 14 different
exposition rooms to visit but the view was the most impressive for us as we found the exhibitions not very modern and interesting.
The cable car can take you to the top within 2 minutes but walking on the stairs gives you a chance to see the view from few different
levels, each giving you unique perspective of the city and the river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_120555_edit.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_130253_edit.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_132406_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_132652_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_134553_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we left the Citadel, we passed a restaurant, graveyard and car parking where we turned right and followed hiking path, going 
all the way down to the city center, see map of our walk below. The path was mostly in the forest with one viewpoint of the city 
and river but the Citadel was almost not visible from there (photo of the city and river below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_134812_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_140313_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/Screenshot from 2021-09-05 14-22-00.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the afternoon, we planned walk starting next to Vêves Castle (9km from Dinant by car), which can be visited on weekends but as we 
were there on a Friday we couldn’t get a closer look at the castle. Our walk started in the forest but the path quickly entered yellow fields of rapeseed.
Once we reached the river Lesse, by going down a very steep path through the forest (around the 3km mark on the map below), we followed a narrow path 
running along the river banks which was the nicest part of the walk. This area was quite dark and lush with many kinds of ferns and
caves that were probably accessible for people who are familiar to caving. At one point we passed a small bar, La Flobette where
you could get from the parking car with a stroller so it’s a good ideal for a walk with kids. We discovered this car parking 
next to some small wooden hut that was office where you could buy a tickets to access the other parts of the park. The 
path we took had no entrance fee (big parking around 5km mark on the map below). There are plenty of other walking paths in this 
area (Walzin Castle further to the west) so it’s definitely a better idea to come to this parking and explore the beauty of 
Furfooz nature reserve. Unfortunately, I found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parcdefurfooz.be/index.php/en/welcome/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; with more details
about this place after our visit so take this opportunity and check all available attractions ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_174619.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/Screenshot from 2021-09-05 14-22-29.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the cold night, we happily left the camping in direction to Luxemburg, more precisely to the area of Lac de la Haute-Sûre.
It is the largest water reservoir in the country, built in the 1950s to meet Luxembourg’s drinking water and electricity needs.
There are so many hiking paths that it was difficult to choose one specific area! Finally we parked our car in Esch Sauer,
next to the floating bridge where we started our walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_114412.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_114231_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_122253_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We really enjoyed this walk! First along the waterside, next narrow path led us all the way up to Liefrange, small village with a lot
of campsites. Then, we kept going through the fields in direction of Kaundorf, where we started again getting closer to the 
lake. Once we passed that village, we quickly reached amazing viewpoints from where we could see far in a distance floating
bridge where we started in the morning. Path leading down from the viewpoint towards the lake was really steep so we were happy 
that we decided to do our walk in the opposite direction where uphill part was longer but not very steep. What we also liked
was the fact that there were many benches along the way so we could easily find nice place to have a rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/DSC07570.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_134450_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_141300_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/DSC07594.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_142209_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_154458_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/Screenshot from 2021-09-05 14-23-35.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we still had some time left in the afternoon, after a quick look at the map, we noticed the nearby village Esch-sur-Sûre 
is worth a visit and we were definitely right! We were lucky enough to find a parking spot along the river from where it
was not far to the castle. We just walked through narrow streets to the church and then by the stairs to the top of the hill. There
was no entrance fee (parking was also free) and we could admire from there stunning view of the river and steep hills surrounding 
this small city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_160341.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_160439.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We noticed another tower on the other side of the hill (photo below) but to get there we had to go all the way down to the village 
and then take another, much longer stairs uphill. My curiosity of the view was too strong and quickly won with fatigue after the 
whole day of activities. Luckily, it was worth it! The tower itself had few levels from where we could admire this beautiful 
region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_160800.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5291776_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5291777_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was our last day on the camping, we packed everything to the car after breakfast and headed to La Roche-en-Ardenne.
That day we had a reservation to visit Hotton cave in the early afternoon so we still had enough time to stop and visit La Roche.
It was definitely the most crowded place we visited during this longer weekend, we finally found a parking spot on the Av. 
du Hadja. To our surprise, the city was really crowded, mostly dominated by motorcyclists. We had a walk to Belvédère 
de La Roche, from where we could admire the view of the city and nearby hills. Then, we came back down to the river to check
city park and come back to the car, grabbing ice cream in the center. There is a castle and a 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.batarden.be/&quot;&gt;military museum&lt;/a&gt; in the city but we didn’t have time 
to check these out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/DSC07603_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301786_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301800_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301811_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/Screenshot from 2021-09-05 14-24-49.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our last attraction of the weekend was the visit in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grottesdehotton.be/eng/home.html&quot;&gt;Hotton Caves&lt;/a&gt;. We bought our tickets online for guided tour in English. 
The cave is well maintained but without light shows and underground boat ride, a more natural character is preserved. Probably
not as interesting for young kids, for them better option would be the &lt;a href=&quot;https://grotte-de-han.be/en&quot;&gt;Caves of Han&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lesgrottes.be/&quot;&gt;Caves of Remouchamps&lt;/a&gt;.
In general, we liked tha cave but we were hoping for more corridors open for the visitors as we feld that it was not enough 
what we saw. Maybe it’s just the matter of comparison to the big cave we visited in Georgia few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301837_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301835_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301833_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301831_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were so lucky with the weather, it was first few days with some sun after long, rainy weeks! It was definitely intense but
amazing weekend :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;De Citadel Dinant - 10 euro entrance fee, you can take a cable car or 408 steps get up to the top. Toilets on the top 
  but you have to pay 0.50 euro which is strange after paying for the entrance. There are big parking areas on the top of 
  the hill where you can buy entrance ticket so other option would be to leave the car here, visit Citadel and city (ticket 
  allows you to leave the citadel) and come back. Everyone was obligated to wear a mask in the whole area of the fortress 
  but also in the city center. More info on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.citadellededinant.be/en/&quot;&gt;official website of the Citadelle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Car parking in Dinant - we decided to park in the city center but not close to the Citadelle where it was diffucult to
  find free parking places, we parked on Rue Alexandre Daoust 46, 20 min. walking distance from the Citadelle (1.5km), many 
  spots available and most of them in the shadow of the trees what is always really helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Car parking in Luxemburg - 13 Lultzhausen, 9666 Esch-Sauer. The price was around 0.6euro/hour so very reasonable but 
  parking was not very big. We easily found a spot but it was not high season yet. There were many parkings in other parts
  of the lake that were much bigger. More information about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naturpark-sure.lu/en/&quot;&gt;this area&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We stayed at &lt;a href=&quot;https://pontbergueme.be/&quot;&gt;Camping Pont de Berguème&lt;/a&gt;, despite to be close to the highway, it was very quiet
  and nice area, next to the stream where kids could play in the water. Clean facilities, nice owners, very much recommended.
  Just keep in mind that nights in June are still pretty cold in Belgium, around 6-7 °C, take a warm sleeping bag if 
  you are camping with a tent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In La Roche-en-Ardenne, we parked the car on Av. du Hadja. Nearby parkings were completely full.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hotton Cave - entrance 10euro/adult, visiting time was about 45min, definitely worth to have sport shoes (slippery and dark inside) 
  and extra jacket if visiting in the summer because temperature in the cave is around 12°C. We bought our tickets
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grottesdehotton.be/eng/home.html&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2021/06/Belgium-Dinant/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2021/06/Belgium-Dinant/</guid>
        
        <category>Belgium</category>
        
        <category>Wallonia</category>
        
        <category>Dinant</category>
        
        <category>lake</category>
        
        <category>Luxemburg</category>
        
        <category>cave</category>
        
        <category>Hotton</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zima odnaleziona! Równica oraz Kotarz, okolica miejscowości Brenna</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Tego dnia pogoda była naprawdę wymarzona! Lekki mróz, zalegający nadal śnieg oraz bezchmurne niebo. Postanowiliśmy
tym razem wejść na Kotarz niebieskim szlakiem, który mija zalew Hołcyna a następnie udać się w przeciwnym kierunku niż 
poprzednio czyli wrócić do Brennej mijając Chatę Wuja Toma. Pomimo tego, że wchodziliśmy tą samą drogą, obecność białego 
puchu sprawiła, że widoki były zdecydowanie lepsze. Również ilość turystów i zaparkowanych wzdłuż drogi samochodów 
świadczyła o tym, że warunki tego dnia były naprawdę idealne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271503.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271507.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271520.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podejście nie sprawiło nam żadnych problemów i szybko osiągnęliśmy ponownie Halę Jaworową by od razu skierować się na sam szczyt.
Najpiękniejszym odcinkiem dzisiejszej trasy był zdecydowanie fragment szlaku czerwonego pomiędzy szczytem Kotarz a Beskidkiem 
(zaczęliśmy zejście w dół ścieżką chwilę za starym wyciagiem która prowadzi wzdłuż potoku Węgierski aby uniknąć popularnej drogi 
asfaltowej, która prowadzi do Chaty Wuja Toma). Nie spotkaliśmy tam prawie nikogo, było cicho a białe drzewa na tle niebieskiego 
nieba wyglądały bajecznie! Gdy tylko doszliśmy do drogi w dzielnicy Brenna Jurkula, ujrzeliśmy mnóstwo samochodów, które były 
zaparkowane dosłownie wszedzie i taka sytuacja miała miejsce aż do parkingów przy Karczmie Pod Skalicą. Do Brennej zjechała 
się tego dnia taka ilość ludzi, że cieżko było w to uwierzyć. Na szczęście my już kończyliśmy naszą wędrówkę podczas gdy inni dopiero 
ją zaczynali co nas bardzo zdziwiło bo do zmroku pozostało jakieś 1.5 godziny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271524.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271525.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271536.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po kilku dniach dojadania świątecznych potraw, czuliśmy ogromną potrzebę ponownego wyjścia w góry i dlatego ruszyliśmy na Równice.
Początkowo podążalismy przez 3km wzdłuż potoku Brennica, aby następnie odbić w kierunku Leśnicy (na skrzyżowaniu stacja paliw), gdzie
wzdłuż drogi widoczne było już oznaczenie zielonego szlaku prowadzącego na szczyt. W pewnym momencie odbija on ostro w prawo i
zaczyna wznosić coraz wyżej, mijając ostatnie domy i wkraczając do lasu. Po dłuższym odcinku przechodzącym przez las, szlak
ten lączy się z niebieskim prowadzący na Równicę. Z racji tego, że już bylismy tam wcześniej a nie planowaliśmy postoju w 
schronisku, lepszą opcją wydało nam się odbicie na niebieski szlak i udanie sie w kierunku szczytu Beskidek, Orłowa i zejście 
w dół jedna ze ścieżek do ulicy Leśnica. Niestety w tym regionie śniegu było już bardzo mało, zrobiło się w wielu miejscach nawet dość
mokro przez topniejący śnieg, ale wciąż znalazłam oszronione liście, które były świetnym materiałem do zabawy z makrofotografią.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011550.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011555.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011557.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011567.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011570.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Przed wyjazdem postanowiliśmy jeszcze spróbowac znaleźć Krzyż Zakochanych o którym dużo słyszałam i widziałam drogowskaz
w to miejsce na głownej drodze prowadzącej przez Brenna, ale nigdy nie było okazji, aby się tam wybrać. Na skrzyżowaniu z 
ulicą Osiedlową ustawiony jest drogowskaz z napisem “Szlak Wspomnień” i to właśnie tam zaczyna się ścieżka która szybko 
zamienić się w leśną ścieżkę. Prowadzi ona cały czas dość stromo pod górkę (2km długości, wzniesienie ok 300m), aby w 
końcowej części się wypłaszczyć i tam właśnie zauważamy krzyż. Jest tam również tablica informacyjna opowiadająca historię 
zakochange w zamożnej pannie, ubogiego młodzieńca i ich ostatnie wspólne chwile zanim zostali rozdzieleni. Miejsce to
osłonięte jest drzewami więc nie ma co liczyc na jakieś specjalne widoki, chyba że podejdzie się na nieco wyżej położoną 
polanę. Podążaliśmy dalej jak prowadziły nas oznaczenia aby w końcu dotrzeć do Lach Dolnych. Niestety zejście nie należało 
do przyjemnych ponieważ ścieżka została okropnie zniszczona przez wycinkę drzew, która w tym miejscu również się odbywa.
Wszędzie było mnóstwo głębokiego błota więc było bardzo ciężko tam przejść, nie topiąc sie w nim bardzo głęboko. Przykro 
patrzeć jak negatywnie na nasze lasy wpływają prowadzone obecnie wycinki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1021592.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1021593.edit.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1021594.edit.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1021600.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nocowaliśmy u moich rodziców, którzy wynajmują pokoje gościnne, dlatego chciałabym je polecić, gdy sytuacja epidemiologiczna 
  poprawi się na tyle, że możliwe będą weekendowe wyjazdy w góry z noclegiem &lt;a href=&quot;https://kimanko-pod-sosnami.eu/galeria/&quot;&gt;Kimanko pod sosnami&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mapki poniżej pokazują dokłandie naszą trasę, nie zawsze był to oficjalny szlak bo nie chcieliśmy kilkukrotnie iść tą samą trasą i 
  szukaliśmy szukaliśmy alternatywnych opcji.
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Kotarz-Hata Wuja Toma.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Rownica.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Krzyz_zakochanych.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2021/01/Swieta-Brenna2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2021/01/Swieta-Brenna2/</guid>
        
        <category>Polska</category>
        
        <category>Brenna</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>góry</category>
        
        <category>Kotarz</category>
        
        <category>Blatnia</category>
        
        <category>zima</category>
        
        <category>snieg</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>W poszukiwaniu oznak zimy na szczytach Błatnia oraz Kotarz, okolica miejscowości Brenna</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;W tym roku zdecydowaliśmy się spędzić Święta u moich rodziców w Polsce. Jako, że od marca oboje pracujemy zdalnie, przed wyjazdem
odbyliśmy kwarantanne i na lotnisko pojechaliśmy własnym samochodem, aby jak najbardziej zminimalizować ryzyko zachorowania na Covid, a co
gorsza zarażenia mojej rodziny. Więc jedynie podczas przebywania na lotnisku oraz samego lotu czuliśmy się najbardziej narażeni na złapanie wirusa,
ale szczęśliwie nie zachorowaliśmy ani nikt z naszej rodziny (co było sprawdzone dwoma testami pcr w Belgii, po powrocie z Polski jak nakazują tego obecne zasady).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niestety Brenna nie przywitała nas wymarzonym białym puchem, ale mocno wierzyłam, że przez dwa tygodnie sytuacja na pewno się zmieni :D
Gdy tylko przestało padać i wiatr ustał, postanowiliśmy dłużej nie zwlekać i kolejnego dnia ruszyć w poszukiwaniu zimy w wyższe partie gór.
Udając się na Kotarz, chcieliśmy sprawdzić ścieżkę, którą kiedyś tam biegłam, zaczynającą się na ulicy Nostrożny (niedaleko karczmy Solisko). 
Podążaliśmy ulicą, która po pewnym czasie zmieniła się w ścieżkę leśną (tam gdzie kończy się asfalt znajduje się rozwidlenie i trzeba wtedy zacząć podążać po prawej stronie
strumienia). Po przejściu niewielkiego odcinka należy ponownie skręcić w prawo co widać na mapie (okolice 3 km) umieszczonej na końcu postu, w sekcji
praktyczne informacje. Niestety na tej wysokości ścieżka ta był mocno rozjechana, prawdopodobnie przez ciężkie samochody używane przy wycince drzew co niestety
zauważyliśmy rownież podczas wypadów w kolejne dni na inne okoliczne szczyty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211345.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211314.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dalej podążaliśmy cały czas tą samą ścieżką aż doszliśmy do rozwidlenia na którym skręciliśmy w lewo, podążając dalej 
na Halę Jaworową, przez którą prowadzi niebieski szlak (opis w kolejnym poście), zaczynający się przy zbiorniku wodnym Hołcyna.
Na Hali Jaworowej wiał bardzo zimny i silny wiatr a widoczność była bardzo słaba, także szybko stamtą uciekliśmy na szczyt Kotarz a następnie
odbiliśmy na czerwony szlak prowadzący na Grabową. Oszronione drzewa i krzewy oraz niewielka ilość śniegu to jedyne ślady zimy jakie tego
dnia znaleźliśmy, ale i tak było warto wybrać się na ten dłuższy spacer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211324.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211336.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211341.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schronisko na Grabowej było otawrte, ale oferowało tylko jedzenie oraz napoje na wynos. Po minięciu Starego Gronia zrobiło się już na prawdę wiosennie,
przynajmniej ze względu na słońce i błekitne niebo bo temperatury tych wiosennych nadal nie przypomniały. Do samej Brennej podążaliśmy cały czas
zielonym szlakiem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC201308.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kilka dni poźniej w Brennej spadło niewiele śniegu, ledwo pokrywając trawę w ogrodzie ale okoliczne szczyty wyglądały już na bardziej białe
i dlatego od razu zdecydowaliśmy wybrać się na kolejny spacer, tym razem na Błatnią. Jako, że byliśmy na tym szczycie już kilka razy, szukałam
jakiegoś alternatywnego wejścia, żeby ponownie nie iść głównym zielonym szlakiem. W aplikacji MAPS.ME zauważyłam ścieżkę zaczynającą się na końcu ulicy 
Chrobaczy (bardzo niedaleko domu moich rodziców), która powinna nas zaprowadzić w okolice szczytu nad schroniskiem, przechodząc przez Bukowy Groń.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261464.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faktycznie tak było, ścieżkę znależliśmy bez problemu. Najpierw była ona dość wąska z krzewami i niskimi drzewami dookoła co sprawiało wrażenie, że 
podążaliśmy w tunelu. Ku naszej radości, już w tym miejscu bylo sporo śniegu! Biały krajobraz od razu wprowadził nas w wyśmienite nastroje :) Nieco wyżej
natrafiliśmy na kilka drewnianych domków do których prowadziła szersza ścieżka pozwalająca na dojazd terenowym samochodem, którą w pewnym momencie przecieliśmy. 
Szlak cały czas prowadził pod górkę, aż wyszliśmy na bardziej wypłaszczoną łąkę gdzie ujrzeliśmy więcej ludzi w oddali którzy podążali żółtym szlakiem z Błatniej w stronę Klimczoka lub 
Chaty Wuja Toma (trzeba w pewnym momencie odbić ze szlaku w prawo, idąc cały czas w dół kamieniską ścieżką).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261472.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261482.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261488.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po wejściu na sam szczyt góry Błatnia, udaliśmy się do Schroniska PTTK, gdzie rozgrzaliśmy się kawą i gorącą czekoladą (niestety jakość pozostawiała 
wiele do życzenia, ale ciepły napój to zawsze miły akcent wycieczki). Następnie ruszyliśmy w dół ze schroniska szlakiem zielonym, odbijając na ostatnim 
odcinku na szlak czarny prowadzący do Brennej. Oszronione krzewy, pokryte śniegiem drzewa wyglądały naprawdę cudownie i jedyne czego nam wciąż brakowało
to odrobina słońca, ale i to wkrótce się zmieniło o czym będzie kolejny post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261501.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nocowaliśmy u moich rodziców, którzy wynajmują pokoje gościnne, dlatego chciałabym je polecić, gdy sytuacja epidemiologiczna 
  poprawi się na tyle, że możliwe będą weekendowe wyjazdy w góry z noclegiem &lt;a href=&quot;https://kimanko-pod-sosnami.eu/galeria/&quot;&gt;Kimanko pod sosnami&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kawa, gorąca czekolada, grzane piwo na wynos w schronisku Błatnia to koszt 8-9zł&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mapki poniżej pokazują dokłandie naszą trasę, nie zawsze był to oficjalny szlak bo nie chcieliśmy kilkukrotnie iść tą samą trasą i 
  szukaliśmy alternatywnych opcji.
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Kotarz-Stary Gron.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Blatnia.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2021/01/Swieta-Brenna/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2021/01/Swieta-Brenna/</guid>
        
        <category>Polska</category>
        
        <category>Brenna</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>góry</category>
        
        <category>Kotarz</category>
        
        <category>Blatnia</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
