<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Going beyond the known</title>
    <description>A travel blog by Monika Suchoszek.
</description>
    <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2019 20:31:48 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2019 20:31:48 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>A day hike to Monte Resegone</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lecco, a small city located on the southern tip of Lake Como turned out to be a fantastic base for hiking lovers. We could have actually stayed here longer than we did as we still had plenty of ideas for day hikes or just regular sightseeing. More about the city itself in the next post :) Our host in Lecco knew a lot about the mountains surrounding this region and suggested us two of the most demanding hikes and we enthousiastically followed her ideas :D The weather predictions were really good so we decided not to wait long and do the most demanding hike to Monte Resegone (1875m) the next day. It was not the distance which made this hike challenging but the altitude gain of around 1500m. We started the hike from the place where we stayed in Lecco (Acquate district) and we made our way up to hiking path number 1 which we followed to rifugio Luigi Azzoni near the peak of Monte Resegone. This path starts at the bottom of the cable car in Versasio and it first leads through the forest on a nice, wide,rocky path. Then it passes a small group of houses (Frazione Costa) and a shelter Rifugio Antonio Stoppani. From there we could already admire the stunning view of Como lake and Lecco city. The path was clearly marked with red-white-yellow stripes with number one written in the middle. Marks were placed on the rocks or trees, so no worries to get lost (of course you need to pay attendion on the crossings with other paths e.g. with MTB trails or paths leading to via ferratas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06629.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was eager to reach the higher parts of the trail, above the tree-line and enjoy the impressive rock formations. I got super excited when I saw the first chains, that meant the path was about to get more interesting! :D In many places it was necessary to use hands, it was more like a scrambling than normal hike but these parts I just loved. Not everyone would be so excited (including my boyfriend) but I was climbing for 7 years so that part of me will always love the feeling of rocks and being in the exposed terrain. We had amazing weather but be aware that this path is difficult and many accidents happens there when it’s icy or rainy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06646.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06663.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06682.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06677.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06692.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06699.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view from the peak was really cool, mountains all around, when clouds moved out of the way we could see distant peaks and of course Como lake which, all together, create a spectacular experience! We stood there for a while admiring the mountain peaks. With over 30 peaks on the horizon, I found it really useful to look at the metal plate with points to all off them indicating their names and heights. There is a shelter next to the peak so you can grab some snacks, sandwich or even a simple hot meal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_121345847.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-45&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to try another hiking path and go back to Piani d’Erna by trail number 10 (passing a few peaks, Punta Stoppani, Manzoni &amp;amp; Dente) which is less popular and unfortunately had way more loose rocks which actually makes it quite difficult to walk down as there was a high probability of falling down. Our muscles were constantly tense and got really tired after the first difficult part with some chains and falling rocks. Also, it got very foggy, the visibility was really low as shown on the photos below. If you really don’t like to do twice the same path then I would recommend to go up to the peak by the route number 10 and go down with number 1 which is still difficult but has less loosy rocks which are especially annoying while going down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_134055691.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06705.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_134052323.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06703.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are afraid that this is gonna be too much for you but you still want to enjoy the spectacular views, then taking cable car to Piani d’Erna is a good idea. It will shorten the hike meaningfully, then it’s “only” about 550m of altitude gain to Monte Resegone. On the map below you can see our hike and the distance. It took us almost 4h to get there and almost the same (including breaks) to get back. We were not rushing, just enjoying the day. As always, navigation app MAPS.ME was very useful to double check our position and to find a shortcut to our room in Lecco. You can just simply download maps of the region where you stay for an offline use (maps of more than 100 countries in the world ready to download!). It worked even in Marocco when we did 10 days hike in Atlas Mountains where the paths were not really marked and difficult to find. We hightly reccomend this app for hiking but also for sightseeing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/maps-me-offline-map-nav/id510623322&quot;&gt;MAPS.ME app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/Screenshot 21-47-52.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path was clearly marked with red-white-yellow colors and number one written in the middle. No worries to get lost, just look carefully for the marks on the rocks or trees. It is a popular destination for Italians and we met many of them on the hiking trail (or maybe it was crowded because it was Saturday). We did the hike in our trail running shoes (Salomon Speedcross 4 and Salomon SENSE RIDE) but high-cut hiking boots would be definitely recommended here. We are used to hike with lighter types of shoes and it works for us. Use gear you are comfortable with, this is not the place for experimentation ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_090851298.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many activities happening in Lecco that weekend, besides the climate change meeting, there was an obstacle run which took place the day we went to Monte Resegone. On the way back we saw the participants struggeling to cross a big wall and climbing an obstacle with many ropes. We participated a few times in obstacle runs in Germany and Belgium and we highly recommend this kind of activity as a great adventure :) Check this link &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scigamatt.com/site/index.php/&quot;&gt;Scigamatt in Lecco&lt;/a&gt; in case you want to try something unusual during your next holidays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06718.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//travel/2019/09/14/Monte-Resegone.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//travel/2019/09/14/Monte-Resegone.html</guid>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>italy</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A trip to Little Switzerland</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Visiting Berdorf in Luxemburg? Why not! We couldn’t miss our chance to finally check one of the options for a weekend trip when you live in Belgium. The initial idea was to do the whole Mullerthal trail route 2 which is around 37km. However, life is unpredictable and we had to modify our plans a little bit. Since we left Leuven on Saturday morning and arrived to Berdorf (the starting point of a trek) at 10.30 am there was not enough time to do the complete route so on the way we decided to skip one loop and took a shortcut to the next village. The first part (around 6km) from Berdorf to Mullerthal led along big rocky walls, the further we got from the car parking, the quieter it got with less and less hikers on the way. The large, high rocks situated close to each other started to create narrow passages, darker and colder inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05267.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;The part from Berdorf to Mullerthal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05277.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;The part from Berdorf to Mullerthal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05278.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Narrow passage between big rocks&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mullerthal village offers a camping site, some places to buy drinks and fast food. We passed the village quite fast, constantly following wooden poles with the name of the route (and distance to the next village). After some time we saw Schiessentümpel Cascade, famous waterfalls atracting many tourists but I need to admit, after having seen waterfalls in Iceland and Laos, they are rather small ;) The shape and style of the wooden bridge above made a bigger impression on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05295.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;The part from Berdorf to Mullerthal2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit further, close to the viewpoint Burgkapp, we had a chance to shorten our hike and go straight ahead to the village Consdorf, skipping the loop to the south and cutting off a few km. We passed Burgkapp, La Pineda camping site, Consdorf (there is a bakery close to the church) to finally reach Scheidgen where we picked up Mullerthal trail route 2 again. The part from here to Echternach was a bit borring. Beautiful, old forest but less groups of rocks which you can explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05317.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Berdorf viewpoint&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05316.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-45&quot; alt=&quot;Berdorf viewpoint&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view of village Echternach where we had a dinner and ice cream :) Visiting this touristic place required us to walk down a steep path to the village and come back the same way what means steep uphill parts as well but it was worth it. On the photo below you can clearly see St. Willibrord Basilica, which dominates the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05325.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Village Echternal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day we explored the area nearby our camping in Berdorf. Amazing viewpoints where you can admire the hills sourrounding the area are a great spot for many tourists to relax. Numerous narrow passages between the rocks attract children with head lights, exploring them without any fear. We really got lost amongst narrow corridors, it feels like being in a labyrinth! Good shoes are highly recommended since the rocks and steps can be quite slippery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05378.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Berdorf viewpoint&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05389.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Berdorf viewpoint&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05396.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-45&quot; alt=&quot;Narrow passage between big rocks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area has a lot to offer not only for hikers, runners or cyclists but also for sport climbers! Around 1km from the camping Martbusch you can find this little but very interesting area with sandstone rock. Most of the climbing routes are rated between 5 and 6. The beautiful forest surrounding this spot makes it colder, something every climber appreciates during the hot summer :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05414.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Climbing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mullerthal trail route 2 - 31km, we skipped around 7km part in south, taking a shortcut from Consdorfer Millen parking to Scheidgen where we again started to follow Mullerthal trail 2 until Berdorf, see the map below for details&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/Map from runkeeper 2019-08-06.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stayed at the Camping Belle-Vue 2000 (around 8euro/person, steel fire bowl and portion of wood - 12 euro) in Berdorf. There are many camping sites in the area of Mullerthal trail route 2 so it is definitely possible to split the whole track into a few parts and explore the area a bit more. There are really plenty of places to check, beautiful rock formations, view points and caves which are difficult to really explore if you do the whole trek in one day like we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05353.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Village Echternal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.campingbelle-vue2000.com/&quot;&gt;Camping Belle-Vue in Berdorf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//travel/2019/08/06/luxembourg.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//travel/2019/08/06/luxembourg.html</guid>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>luxembourg</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Prometeus cave and canyons - day trip around Kutaisi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We had almost three full days planned in Kutaisi bafore taking an early flight back to Berlin. That was enough time to explore Kutaisi, do shopping in a local market and check out few natural monuments nearby the city. With the host of our guesthouse acting as our personal driver we were able to visit the Prometheus cave and two canyons: Martivili and Okatse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached the cave in less than one hour and were really happy to see just a few other cars on the parking lot. Indeed our group counted approx. 20 people which, in comparison to the high season when each groups can reach up to 200 people, was really comfortable! Thanks to the small group our guide was able to stop in the main chambers and tell us additional details about this astonishing cave :) The total length of the corridors is 1400m and include around 800 steps reaching 80m beneath the surface, so it was a good exercise for the legs (our traveling companion has a different opinion :p). The temperature in the cave stays around 14ºC throughout the year and provides the stable conditions required for different cave formations to be created. However, this process is extremely slow, around 100 years are needed for a stalactite to grow 1 cm! The cave was discovered in 1984 but it is open to visitors only since 2012. There were underground lakes and rivers surrounded with incredible stalagmites and stalactites. A variety of lights installed along the walking route highlight the spectacular shapes of different cave formations. Near the exit of the cave you can take an optional boat ride starting from an underground river leading out the cave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_0550.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_0580.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_0584.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_0551.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_0593.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had chosen Okatse canyon as a next place to visit. According to the model presented close to the entrance, we should be able to enjoy wonderful view of the canyon from the platform installed on the slope of the mountain. Our walk is in total 7 km long (could be shortened almost by half by taking a taxi on the way back). The majority of the walk is on a good path which leads through a forest inhabited by a family of cute piglets and … you guessed it … cows. Just at the end there is a 780 meters long walkway suspended from the edge of the cliff allowing you to walk  with open air underneath the feet … which could make some people breath faster :) When we looked down the long slope from the extended view platform there was a stream visible in one spot besides endless numbers of trees. Unfortunately, we were somewhat disappointed with the view after our hikes around Mestia (probably just a matter of comparison).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_0615.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Okatse canyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_0618.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Okatse canyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_0631.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Okatse canyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martvili canyon was the last, but not the least, place we visited that day. Interesting limestone formations, water cascades and lush vegetation create a landscape which we really marveled. The setting sun  made the scenery pure magic, a fulfilling end of the trip :) Also here, it was possible to take a boat trip (extra fee). Though pretty small, worth stopping by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_161728940.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Martvili canyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Prometeush_cave/IMG_161454431.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-45&quot; alt=&quot;Martvili canyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entrance fees for the different sites:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prometheus cave - 20 lari (students 5 lari) with the guide (50 min) + boat trip inside the cave - 15 lari (approx 10 min)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Okatse canyon - 15 lari (students 5 lari)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Martvili canyon - 15 lari (student 5 lari)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//travel/2017/10/22/Georgia-Prometeush-cave.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//travel/2017/10/22/Georgia-Prometeush-cave.html</guid>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>georgia</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hike from Mestia to Zardlashi and Murshkeli villages</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sunny days finally arrived and we used our chance for another trek, this time it was first part of 4-days trek to Ushguli. At the beginning, the path passes Hotel Tetnuldi, where we could already seen stunning view of Mt.Ushba in a distance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_0374.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparison to the last day, a perfectly clear sky gave us a chance to see multiple mountain ranges. After a while, we have seen wild herd of horses who did not pay attention to us at all. They look magnificent with the mountains and Mestia village in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_0383.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_0375.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_0381.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wide path guided us few kilometers through the fields until it reached wooden sign marking the direction to the near villages. We kept going straight, path became very narrow, muddy and steep. Branches of the trees and dense bushes made this part the most difficult. After that part path again became easy and pleasant, branching into few variants which were leading into the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_0376.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_0390.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could see in a distance the only road leading to Ushguli with heavy trucks on it. Few villages in the valley looked pretty old and destroyed, however the characteristic for this region towers were still on their places. At on point we decided to start heading back to Mestia, from curiosity choosing the way through one of the villages located in the lower part of the valley. Buildings seemed to be abandoned and  we haven’t seen anyone there, besides one, barking dog. We got trapped in 10 cm deep mud while passing the narrow paths in the village, luckily no one fall into it! We decided to return mostly the same way as we came to avoid more muddy and unpleasant surprises :) We have met only few tourists, horses and a dog during this really nice, 20 km walk on that bright and warm day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_0401.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_0421.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Inside of the Prometeush cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_0430.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Okatse canyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always we finished the hike in one of the restaurants in Mestia, waiting for a great meal to compensate the toils of the day. This time as a appetizer zucchini rolls with garlic-walnut paste as a filling, served cold :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG_185037198.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Okatse canyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the map below you can see our hike and the distance. It took us almost 3h to get there and almost the same (including breaks) to get back. We were not rushing, just enjoying the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/Screenshot-08-30-26.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Okatse canyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Georgia/Murshkeli/IMG-20171027-murshkeli2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Okatse canyon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//travel/2017/10/10/Georgia-Murshkeli.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//travel/2017/10/10/Georgia-Murshkeli.html</guid>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>georgia</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
