<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Going beyond the known</title>
    <description>A travel blog by Monika Suchoszek.</description>
    <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 18:14:36 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 18:14:36 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Funchal - great starting point for visiting the island of eternal springtime</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When it came time to choose a destination for our honeymoon, we wanted something special. This trip was a rare opportunity—our 
toddler stayed at home, so for once, we could travel as we did before starting a family. We dreamed of a place that offered 
breathtaking hiking trails, delicious food, and unspoiled nature. No need to worry about playgrounds or keeping the little 
one entertained. Madeira checked every box. We’d heard great recommendations about this Portuguese island from friends and family.
Our plan was simple: spend the first and last nights of our trip in Funchal, the island’s charming capital, and use the remaining 
five days to explore the rest of Madeira by car. And it turned out to be the perfect decision!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long flight, we needed to rest, stock up on groceries, and figure out parking for the days ahead. And wow, what 
an introduction to the city! The streets in Funchal are unbelievably steep, and by the time we reached our apartment after 
exploring the city, I was already sweating—not from the heat but from imagining myself navigating those narrow, inclined 
streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather on our first day in Madeira wasn’t exactly ideal. It quickly confirmed what we’d heard about how unpredictable 
Madeira’s weather can be. Our main goal for the day was to visit the famous Monte Palace Madeira botanical garden. After a 
short ride with a crazy local bus driver, I was very happy to get off the bus and finally breathe some fresh air. I was 
starting to feel motion sickness after all the sharp turns the bus made during the last 15 minutes. Be prepared for a wild ride!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to the botanical garden, we passed the Igreja de Nossa Senhora do Monte, a charming hilltop church. The monument 
in front of the church is a statue of Emperor Charles I of Austria (Karl I), honoring the last emperor of the Austro-Hungarian 
Empire. He lived his final days on this island and is buried in the church. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_110240_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just at the bottom of the stairs leading to the church, a famous tourist attraction can be found: the wicker toboggans. 
The 2-kilometer ride down the steep streets of Funchal begins here. When we passed this spot at around 10 a.m. on a Sunday 
morning, there was no one operating the toboggans.
These traditional sled-like vehicles are made of wicker baskets mounted on wooden runners and are used to transport 
visitors downhill from the village of Monte to the lower streets of Funchal. The journey covers about 2 kilometers 
and can reach speeds of up to 30 km/h. The drivers, called “Carreiros”, stand behind the sled and use their 
strength, balance, and rubber-soled boots to steer and control the speed as the toboggan glides down the hill.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08450.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lush greenery, exotic plants, and serene atmosphere made us feel like we’d stepped into a tropical rainforest. The 
Monte Palace itself was originally built as a luxurious hotel in the late 19th century. However, the hotel faced financial 
struggles over the years and eventually closed in the mid-20th century.
In the late 1980s, José Berardo purchased the property and decided to repurpose it as a botanical garden and cultural site. 
After its transformation, the gardens opened to visitors in the early 1990s, showcasing a stunning collection of exotic 
plants, minerals, and contemporary art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08565.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08483.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08523.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent about 2.5 hours wandering through the garden, though we had to take a few breaks to shelter from the rain. The 
unpredictable weather gave the whole place a moody, almost mystical vibe, making the experience even more unforgettable.
The garden offers breathtaking panoramic views of Funchal, the bay, and the Atlantic Ocean. But what surprised me most was 
the mineral exhibition. I wasn’t expecting to be impressed by rocks, but the creative display truly captivated me. Most 
specimens were from Brazil, Portugal, and South Africa, and they were absolutely stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_113302_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_113133_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_113038_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08539.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08529.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08467.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the minerals, there were pavilions showcasing modern and contemporary art, adding an element of surprise 
to the garden’s natural beauty. The Asian-inspired section of the garden, with its striking red elements, stood out 
beautifully against the lush green forest background. Another highlight was the succulent garden, where a variety of species 
were arranged in an incredibly artistic and visually appealing way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08553.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08555.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to walk back to Funchal as the weather was improving, and we wanted to explore the city at our own pace. We 
started on the street beneath the cable car, next to the parking lot of the upper cable car station. From there, we turned 
left just before the cemetery, following a charming path that ran behind some houses until we reached Caminho do Lombo street.
The road quickly became so steep that our calves started burning almost immediately! The area was a lovely residential 
neighborhood, but despite seeing bus stops along the way, there were no detailed schedules, and we didn’t spot a single 
bus. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08597.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08596.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some effort, we finally reached Miradouro da Tabaiba, a viewpoint offering fantastic vistas of Funchal, the 
bay, and the cable car route to Monte. It’s said to be one of the best spots to watch the famous New Year’s Eve fireworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08598.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued down Caminho do Lombo, passing underneath the express road. The next part of the walk was the trickiest—there 
was no sidewalk or safe space for pedestrians for about 200 meters, and the sharp turns made it feel unsafe. We quickly 
jogged through this stretch to get it over with. Eventually, we reached Rua Pedro José de Ornelas, a street that led us 
safely toward the city center of Funchal with 
proper sidewalks. By the time we arrived at our destination—the harbor—we had covered 6 kilometers, descending a total of 
550 meters. The sun had come out, and the view of the cruise ships and the shimmering water was absolutely beautiful.
Before heading for dinner, we walked through Parque de Santa Catarina, a peaceful spot in the city. It was there we 
noticed the CR7 Museum, a must-visit for football fans, with its famous statue of Cristiano Ronaldo outside—a statue that, 
as everyone jokes, looks nothing like him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08605.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this demanding walk, we rewarded ourselves with a well-deserved dinner at a local restaurant.
I couldn’t resist ordering one of the island’s signature dishes—black scabbardfish with banana.
At first, the combination felt exciting and unique, but as I made my way through the dish, the banana’s sweetness became 
a bit overwhelming. Still, it was an experience worth trying and a true taste of Madeira’s culinary creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also discovered Brisa Maracujá, a popular soft drink made with real passion fruit juice. Its refreshing and sweet 
flavor perfectly captures the tropical essence of Madeira’s famous passion fruit. Later, we came across the sugar-free 
version of the same drink, which turned out to be surprisingly tasty—even for someone like me, who doesn’t usually enjoy 
sugar-free beverages.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_152841_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to go for an evening run to explore the city before sunset. It was challenging to find a route that wouldn’t 
involve a demanding ascent, but I eventually chose Fortaleza de São João Baptista do Pico as my destination. The run to the 
fortress was tough (luckily, also short!), with steep streets that made for a great workout.
When I reached the fortress, I found it wasn’t in the best condition. The section offering the best view of the city was 
under construction, which left me feeling a bit disappointed. However, the effort of running uphill was rewarding in itself. 
Despite the fortress’s abandoned appearance, the nearby playground and café were full of life, families and 
children enjoying the evening.
From there, I ran towards the harbor and along the waterfront to Forte de São Tiago. The brightly lit streets and lively 
atmosphere made this part of the run especially enjoyable. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_183150_01.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_183451_01.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
However, after passing the fortress, the streets became darker 
and emptier, so I decided to turn back. I headed uphill toward our apartment, passing many restaurants filled with people 
enjoying their dinners.
It was the perfect way to end such an adventurous day—combining exercise, exploration, and the vibrant energy of Funchal in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explored &lt;strong&gt;Rua de Santa Maria&lt;/strong&gt;, one of the oldest streets in Funchal, during our evening walk the other day. In 2010, 
the government launched an initiative called “Art of Open Doors” as a way to revitalize the street and bring new life to 
the Old Town area. Local and international artists were invited to paint the doors of the buildings, transforming the 
street into an open-air art gallery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth walking down this street both in the morning and evening, as different places might be closed or open, 
revealing interesting paintings like The Little Prince, The Mermaid Door, grape harvest scenes, Funchal’s history and 
culture, or depictions of the sea life surrounding the island. The street is full of souvenir shops, restaurants, cafés, 
and bars, and it becomes especially lively in the evenings when locals and tourists gather for dinner and drinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241101_192208_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09549.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can explore Funchal by foot, taxi, cable car, and even tuk-tuks. These three-wheeled vehicles are a popular and 
eco-friendly way to navigate the city and its surroundings, as they can easily maneuver through the narrow streets of 
the Old Town. Tuk-tuks in Funchal are operated by various companies and drivers, often offering guided tours to help 
visitors discover key attractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re an excellent option for people with mobility issues or for those who find it challenging to walk up the city’s 
steep streets. While taking a break at the Lazareto viewpoint, we noticed a couple who had arrived by tuk-tuk. They paused 
for about five minutes as their driver gave them an explanation about the city before heading off to their next destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09553.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09545_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fortress Forte de São Tiago, with its striking bright yellow color, stands out beautifully against the blue waters 
of the Atlantic and the green hills of Madeira. I particularly enjoyed visiting this spot during my evening run for its 
peaceful vibe, where visitors can soak up the atmosphere, watch the sunset, or observe cruise ships and fishing boats in 
the harbor. During the day, the fort offers spectacular views of the ocean, the city, and the surrounding mountains. Inside, there is 
a restaurant that provides a unique dining experience, and the fort is also used for events, exhibitions, and other 
cultural activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09559.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were absolutely amazed by the variety of fruits available in shops, even in supermarkets, which tasted so much better 
than the ones in Belgium. Fruit shops, called “Frutaria,” caught our attention every time we passed them. Our favorite 
fruit was the local papaya.Our last day was reserved for shopping, and one of the places we were eager to visit was Mercado 
dos Lavradores. This famous market offers an impressive array of exotic fruits, such as passion fruit, annona (custard apple) , and the 
intriguing banana-pineapple hybrids. Vendors often let you sample their offerings, but prices can be significantly higher 
than elsewhere—so be cautious about overpaying, as prices can easily be double those at street stalls or in frutarias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the market is popular among locals, some parts, particularly the fruit stalls, are more geared toward tourists. We 
visited on a Saturday, one of the liveliest days when locals and tourists alike gather. The energy and vibrant atmosphere 
added to the market’s charm, despite the crowds. Stalls displayed beautifully arranged fruits, dried herbs, peppers, and 
flowers, creating a feast for the eyes! For those who prefer a quieter experience, visiting earlier in the morning or 
on a weekday might be a better option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we weren’t planning to buy fruit at the market due to the high prices, we discovered that the ground floor is an 
excellent spot to purchase flower bulbs. The flower stalls were especially colorful, showcasing tropical blooms like the 
famous strelitzias (bird-of-paradise). Women dressed in multi-colored striped dresses selling these flowers added a touch 
of tradition to the experience. Just by the entrance, stunning azulejos (traditional tiles) depict how the market looked 
in the past, giving visitors a glimpse into its history. If you’re a gardening enthusiast, make sure to check out the ground 
floor, where you can buy flower bulbs to take home. Strelitzia bulbs, in particular, make for a unique souvenir that’s sure 
to remind you of Madeira long after your trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09540.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09512.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09535_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most fascinating sections of the market is the seafood area. Here, you’ll find a variety of fish you might 
never have seen before. The star attraction is the black scabbardfish, or “espada,” a deep-sea species that has been a 
staple of Madeiran cuisine for centuries. Its long, slender body, black skin, and sharp teeth give it an almost mythical 
appearance. Found at depths of up to 1,500 meters in the North Atlantic, this fish is caught by skilled local fishermen 
using traditional methods. Despite its unusual look, the flesh of the black scabbardfish is tender, mild, and white, 
making it perfect for a range of delicious dishes—from the classic espada with banana to other creative preparations 
you’ll find in Madeiran restaurants. Interestingly, the black scabbardfish is found only around Madeira and near Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09526.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09541.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC09528.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent yesterday afternoon exploring another side of the coastline, heading toward Câmara de Lobos. My second run took 
me to the Doca do Cavacas Natural Pools. The entire route followed a pleasant sidewalk, passing several large hotels with 
swimming pools and stunning ocean views. Along the bustling road, there were also restaurants and souvenir shops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doca do Cavacas Natural Pools were a smaller version of the ones we visited in Porto Moniz. On the way, I also passed 
another set of outdoor pools called “Ponta Gorda Lido.” Both locations displayed the same information board with prices, 
so they must be part of a chain of swimming pools. These pools also had sections designed for toddlers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_161407_02.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_155924_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transportation: We used &lt;a href=&quot;https://bolt.eu/nl-be/&quot;&gt;Bolt&lt;/a&gt; to get from the airport to Funchal in the evening for 19 euros.
In the morning, we paid more (29 euros) because fewer cars were available, and we also reserved one for a specific time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Accommodation: We rented our apartment on Airbnb, and it was the best one we’ve ever stayed in! The address was R. Elias Garcia 15.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/625124896734414040?source_impression_id=p3_1737231851_P3iFToGbXtka81Qm&quot;&gt;Top floor/ocean view 1Bdr condo walk to downtown 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Car Rental: we rented a car via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wyspamadera.pl/auto&quot;&gt;Wyspa Madera&lt;/a&gt; from the Adratica rental company. 
The cost for a class A car rented for five days was 185 euros, plus extra insurance for tires, windows, and side mirrors 
at 5 euros per day. We were lucky to receive a Nissan Micra Turbo (class C), which was perfect for the steep streets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parking: We left the rented car at the nearby underground Parking Santa Luzia every night (Rua 5 de Outubro, São Martinho, 
9000-216 Funchal, Portugal). We always paid 4.5 euros (cash only). Note that many spaces are reserved and clearly labeled 
with banners hanging above them. Only once did we need to drive to the bottom level, as the ground floor was full (this 
was after 20:00). Parking a small car is fine, but larger vehicles might be challenging to maneuver.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_103435_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241027_103345_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more details about wicker toboggan rides along Carreiros do Monte Street, check &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carreirosdomonte.com/v3/en/index.php&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/DSC08446.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://montepalacemadeira.com/en/&quot;&gt;Jardim Monte Palace Madeira&lt;/a&gt; official website for details.
Ticket price: 15 euros per person.
We took a local bus from the R 31 Janeiro Finanças (9C) bus stop, line 21 (line 20 also goes the same direction). The 
ride took about 13 minutes and cost 1.95 euros from the driver.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We decided not to try the &lt;a href=&quot;https://madeiracablecar.com/en/&quot;&gt;Funchal Cable Car&lt;/a&gt; because the price was quite high. Since we’ve experienced cable cars in other 
countries, we didn’t consider it an essential attraction.
We also heard that Madeira offers so many amazing views that this one can be skipped. Every time we passed the bottom 
station of the cable car, there was a long queue. Plus, the 13-minute bus ride was exciting, as it navigated narrow 
streets full of cars. The local driver’s skill in maneuvering sharp turns was impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restaurants we visited:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.informalfoodexperience.com/&quot;&gt;Restaurante Informal&lt;/a&gt;: We arrived 15 minutes before opening and barely 
managed to get a table. This place doesn’t take reservations, so if you miss the first wave of seating when it opens, your 
name will be added to a list, and you’ll need to return about 1.5 hours later.
We stayed for 1 hour and 20 minutes, and by the time we left, there were already people waiting outside for a free table.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_184011_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_184007_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Reidaponcha&quot;&gt;Rei da Poncha&lt;/a&gt;: The Nikita drink was our favorite (mix of pineapple juice, beer
and vanilla ice cream)!
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_192527_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_192727_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rota23.pt/&quot;&gt;Rota 23 Hamburgueria&lt;/a&gt; The only place still open after 10 p.m. near our apartment when we 
arrived from the airport. It turned out to be a very nice spot.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bar “O Avô” -Tasty scabbard fish with banana and Espetada de Frango. Fair prices and great service. However, seeing 
two cockroaches on the way to the toilet was not a pleasant experience.
Address: R. Da Praia 49A, São Martinho, 9000-643 Funchal, Portugal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Casa do Bolo do Caco -  delicious bolo do caco sandwiches as a great alternative for quick lunch or snack, great way
of using the bolo do caco. Essentially, the traditional Bolo do Caco flatbread is sliced 
in half and filled with a variety of savory ingredients to create a sandwich, we tried one with beef.
Address: Rua Dr. Fernão de Ornelas 26, 9050-021 Funchal, Portugal
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_123638_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shops:
Frutaria Seminário - Frutas, Verduras e Legumes - A nice place to buy fruit. Be sure to check whether the fruit is local 
or imported if you want to try Madeiran produce. They sold tasty local papaya (in small pieces), but by the evening, almost everything was gone.
Address: R. do Seminário 16, 9000-053 Funchal, Portugal&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Useful websites:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ifcn.madeira.gov.pt/pt/atividades-de-natureza/percursos-pedestres-recomendados/percursos-pedestres-recomendados.html&quot;&gt;official list of open and closed hikes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipma.pt/en/otempo/prev.localidade.hora/index.jsp#Madeira&amp;amp;Funchal/Lido&quot;&gt;weather forecast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netmadeira.com/webcams-madeira&quot;&gt;online cameras&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh fruits, alcohol, plant bulbs, cork items… and, of course, memories!
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/20241102_200353_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Doca do Cavacas Natural Pools: entrance fee 5,70euro for adults. Children below 6 enters for free, 7-17y pays only 1.90euro.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Details of the runs:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run in the old city center - 7km, 236m ascent
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/Screenshot_20250128_213104_Suunto_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
Run along the coast line - 11km, 187m ascent
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Madeira/Funchal/Screenshot_20250128_212556_Suunto_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/01/Funchal/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2025/01/Funchal/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>city</category>
        
        <category>Madeira</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Exploring the Natural and Cultural Wonders of Gerês-Xurés: A December Adventure in North of Braga</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Gerês-Xurés Transboundary Biosphere Reserve (&lt;strong&gt;Reserva de la Biosfera Transfronteriza Gerês-Xurés&lt;/strong&gt;) stretches across 
Galicia (Spain) and the North Region (Portugal). With its highest peaks, Nevosa (1,646m) and Fontefría, located in the 
heart of the Serra Gerês-Xurés mountains, it was recognized as a UNESCO Biosphere Reserve in 2009. A rare but iconic 
predator in this area is the Iberian Wolf. More commonly, you can encounter Garrano Horses, semi-wild horses native to 
northern Portugal. They roam freely in the reserve and symbolize the area’s cultural and natural heritage. Pyrenean Oak 
dominates the reserve’s forests, providing essential habitats for wildlife. We also noticed many eucalyptus trees, but 
this depends on the part of the vast reserve you’re exploring. I particularly admired the rock formations visible in the 
higher parts of the mountain range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_111108_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our hike began at &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro da Ermida&lt;/strong&gt; in the village of Ermida, where we left our car. We embarked on a short loop of 6.5 km 
(Miradouro da Ermida – Miradouro Fraga do Justo – Cascata da Rajada – Miradouro Silhas – Miradouro da Vela – Miradouro da Ermida), 
navigating with Organic Maps and partially following the trail marked as the “PR14 Alternativo” loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_113004_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_114348_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_113627_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we followed signs toward &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro Fraga do Justo&lt;/strong&gt;. From this viewpoint, you can see the entire surrounding valley of 
the Arado River, with its fast-flowing waters running between rocks before turning into Rajada waterfall visible below. 
&lt;strong&gt;Cascata da Rajada&lt;/strong&gt; was our main goal—a picturesque waterfall at the end of an enjoyable hike with plenty of shade. The 
trail becomes a bit rocky at the end but isn’t particularly technical. According to Google reviews, there’s less water 
in August, but in early December, the stream was abundant. Some visitors climb the rocks at the end to reach the base of 
the waterfall. Be cautious, as the rocks can get very slippery. You can also find a larger, deeper lagoon for swimming in 
summer. The surroundings of Cascata da Rajada are a pleasant spot to take a break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_122953_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_130642_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_130539_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Close to the waterfall, you can find additional viewpoints on natural rocks, such as &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro Silhas&lt;/strong&gt;. The views from both 
sections of the viewpoint are stunning. It’s worth exploring to find paths leading to both parts, though they are not always 
obvious and require walking between trees and bushes. We then continued our way back to Ermida village, stopping at another 
viewpoint, &lt;strong&gt;Miradouro da Vela&lt;/strong&gt;. This viewpoint is very accessible, with a clear path leading to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearby, we noticed part of the forest had been recently burned. Large parts of central and northern Portugal are covered 
by eucalyptus, a highly flammable tree. Eucalyptus thrives and regenerates after wildfires, making it controversial in Portugal. 
Introduced in the 1850s, eucalyptus is now the most common tree in the country. While it’s valuable to the pulp industry 
for its fast growth and high yield, it depletes soil and water and spreads wildly on unmanaged lands. Its flammable leaves 
and bark exacerbate the wildfire risk. The photos below, clearly show how quickly eucalyptus can recover after late summer
fires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_132806_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_132959_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_133009_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_133028_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After visiting this viewpoint, we continued our relaxing walk to explore the village and its rural surroundings. One 
striking feature of the area is the presence of hórreos, traditional granaries found near almost every house. These structures, 
built from wood or stone and elevated on pillars ending with flat stones, prevent rodents from accessing stored grain. 
They are typically square or rectangular with slits in the walls for ventilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_135700_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, we visited the nearby &lt;strong&gt;Cascata do Arado&lt;/strong&gt;. We parked near the roundabout where the paved road ends (coordinates: 
41.715924, -8.132380) and walked 15 minutes along the dirt road (approximately 850m), which is manageable for children. 
You can also drive closer, as the dirt road is in good condition with ample parking. Cascata do Arado is a beautiful, 
small waterfall that’s easy to access. In summer, visitors often swim in its pools. To reach the base of the waterfall, 
you need to navigate an unmarked trail and wade through the river, as the official path leads only to the top viewpoint. 
Be cautious—there are warning signs about accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_141901_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_142332_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_143209_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_142402_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I hiked to a viewpoint (&lt;strong&gt;Viewpoint Rocas&lt;/strong&gt;) near the parking area. The climb is steep and unmarked, taking about 
five minutes. While there isn’t a clear path, the ascent involves scrambling over rocks, with the last section featuring 
artificial stairs. Though the climb is tricky and involves some trial and error, it was more interesting than the panoramic 
views at the top which is nice but not the best we have seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_145115_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gerês-Xurés Reserve is a remarkable destination for nature enthusiasts, offering opportunities for hiking, wildlife 
observation, and cultural exploration. Spending just one day in this park convinced me it’s a place worth returning to 
for a longer adventure. Especially when days become longer and more daylight would allow for longer hikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://turismo.cm-terrasdebouro.pt/aventura/&quot;&gt;The Geres-Xures Transboundary Biosphere Reserve&lt;/a&gt; website contains 
description of hikes from this region, PR1-PR15 and longer ones GR34 (34km loop), GR50 (187.5km linear). There is pdf file
with all detail for each hike that can be downloaded but it’s not really useful to find your route, it’s nice general 
overview though. We used Organic Maps app to navigate and all trails were marked in this app so we didn’t have any issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/Screenshot_20241219_101439_Suunto.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/Screenshot_20241219_101449_Suunto_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://turismo.cm-terrasdebouro.pt/listings/pr14-trilho-do-sobreiral-da-ermida/#en-pr14&quot;&gt;Details of PR14&lt;/a&gt; can be found 
on the official website. Trail is marked with yellow and red horizontal stripes. Where a route changes direction, the 
red stripe will be L-shaped showing which way to turn (below example means that we should turn left). More detailsed explanation
is included in pdf available under above link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_134714_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_125642_1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were signs on each viewpoint (below Miradouro Silhas) &lt;strong&gt;“Se vir Incendo, ligue 117”&lt;/strong&gt; what can be translated to 
&lt;strong&gt;“In case of fire, call 117”&lt;/strong&gt;. 
 &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241208_130529_02.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Geres/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Geres/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Heritage and Holidays: A Magical Visit to Braga and Guimarães</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While visiting friends in Pedralva, exploring Portugal’s third-largest city was a must. Our journey began with a 
bus ride, and we arrived near the beautiful Park Avenida Central, where a charming Christmas market awaited us. The park 
was adorned with festive decorations, immersing us in the holiday spirit. We decided to return to the same place after 
dark to experience the market illuminated by Christmas lights. That turned out to be a great decision because, that evening, 
the market hosted a live music performance as part of the 29th edition of CELTA at Theatro Circo. Themed “Urban CELTA,” 
the event brought together over 400 artists from various universities. It was my first time experiencing this type of music, 
and I thoroughly enjoyed it. As I later learned, a “tuna” is a group of university students from Spain, Portugal, or Latin 
America who perform traditional music in traditional university dress. Originating in the 13th century, these groups once 
played to earn money or food. Today, they continue the tradition for fun, travel, and meeting new people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_135837_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_134853_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_135937_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are about 35 churches in the city of less than 200-thousand residents. The “Santa Maria de Braga” Cathedral, with small 
museum, isn’t even the most famous one, but more about other places will follow in the next part of this post. The area 
around the cathedral is a great spot for finding unique souvenirs, with plenty of shops to browse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_170817_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other highlights of the historical city center include:
&lt;strong&gt;The Arch of the New Gate&lt;/strong&gt; (top left photo below). This triumphal arch marks the western entrance to the city’s medieval 
wall. It is located at the start of R. Dom Diogo de Sousa, the main shopping street. Strolling down this street is worthwhile, 
as it is lined with beautiful buildings adorned with blue-tiled facades. It’s also where locals gather on Christmas Eve 
to eat bananas and drink Muscat wine in the hours before Christmas dinner. This tradition, started over three decades ago 
by the owner of Casa das Bananas, still attracts thousands of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_141826_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_172508_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_172404_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_172344_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Braga City Hall&lt;/strong&gt;: An 18th-century building housing the local government.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_171734_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_155837_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City Market&lt;/strong&gt; (Mercado Municipal): Recently renovated with a modern wooden roof, this market features stalls selling 
flowers, vegetables, fruits, cheese, coffee, and more. Although we visited late in the afternoon when many stalls were 
closed, we still managed to buy some delicious mandarins from a local vendor. December is also a great time for spotting 
orange and mandarin trees on many streets during our walk. The best oranges are typically in season from late fall through 
early spring, with peak freshness often occurring between December and March.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_150618_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_145406_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_151501_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Santa Barbara Garden&lt;/strong&gt; This stunning garden, located next to the Archiepiscopal Palace, was a highlight of our walk. The 
colorful flower beds, beautiful central fountain, and well-maintained design made it a visual delight. The garden also 
offers views of the medieval and Baroque wings of the palace, including a section damaged by fire in 1834. Next to 
the garden is the public library and district archive, housed in the palace’s Baroque wing. The area is Very well maintained,
and I was surprised to find such a beautiful spot in the heart of a busy city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_152556_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_152447_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241206_152818_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, we planned to visit two famous sanctuaries near Braga. Before setting off, we decided to fuel up with a 
popular local dish. Taberna Belga is renowned for its francesinhas—a unique take on the traditional Portuguese dish that 
differs from the famous Porto version. They don’t take reservations, so be prepared to wait for a table. Francesinha is a 
type of sandwich originating in Porto, made with thick slices of white bread, Portuguese ham, sausage, cheese, and steak. 
The version in Braga is creamier and more buttery. It includes bread, wet-cured ham, linguiça, fresh sausage like chipolata, 
steak or roast meat, and is topped with melted cheese and a thick, spiced tomato sauce. This sauce, which resembles a 
tomato cream soup, is poured over a croque madame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first stop was the Sanctuary of Our Lady of Sameiro, which offers panoramic views of the city, surrounding mountains, 
and the River Minho. Located over 350 meters above Braga, it’s a serene and spiritual site visited by Pope John Paul II 
in 1982. This is the second-largest sanctuary dedicated to the Virgin Mary in Portugal, with Fátima being the largest 
Marian sanctuary, and was built in the 19th century. The main Marian festivities take place on the first Sunday of 
June and the third Sunday of August, drawing thousands of pilgrims from across the region. Pilgrims recite prayers and 
sing hymns dedicated to the Virgin Mary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_135553_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_135943_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_140353_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just 2 km from Sameiro is the Sanctuary of Bom Jesus do Monte, a UNESCO World Heritage Site since 2019. In the 19th century, 
the area surrounding the church and its grand stairway was transformed into a park. The water-powered funicular, built in 
1882, connects the bottom of the hill to the sanctuary and is the oldest funicular in the world operating on this system. 
This was also the first funicular built on the Iberian Peninsula and remains in use today. The sanctuary is famous for 
its Baroque-style staircase, consisting of 577 steps. It welcomes over one million visitors annually, including pilgrims, 
tourists, and locals. Walking down the stairway is a must to fully appreciate its architectural beauty and design (you can 
take the funicular back up to the church).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_142138_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_142622_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_145611_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_143251_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sanctuary itself is free to enter and features a large park with tall trees and paved walkways, perfect for leisurely 
strolls or quiet reflection. Benches are scattered throughout, offering places to rest and enjoy the peaceful surroundings, 
with designated picnic areas. A small artificial lake provides boat rentals, making it an ideal spot for relaxation. The 
basilica is stunning, and the views of Braga from the top are spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_144436_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_144114_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_141832_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the afternoon, we planned to drive to Guimarães, often referred to as the birthplace of Portugal because it is where 
Afonso Henriques, the first king of Portugal, was born. After finding a parking spot, we started our walk to the historic 
center of the city. The first medieval-looking building we encountered was Torre da Alfândega, with the words “Aqui nasceu 
Portugal” (“Portugal was born here”) written on its walls. This tower was recently renovated and can be visited to enjoy 
views of the city, though we didn’t know about this on the day of our visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_155357_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_155429_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guimarães was founded in the 4th century and became the first capital of Portugal in the 12th century. We fell in love 
with the small cobblestone streets, medieval architecture, and vibrant squares of the city center. The cobblestone streets 
are easy to walk through, offering the chance to discover great little shops and restaurants. Its historic center, a UNESCO 
World Heritage Site since 2001, was truly beautiful, and it was evident that there were more tourists here compared to 
Braga. The streets in this city were also decorated with lights and Christmas ornaments, though they were less spectacular 
than those in Braga. We also passed by a flea market offering a variety of antiques and collectibles, located under the 
columns of the Old Town Council Chambers (Antiga Câmara Municipal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_160048_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_160015_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_160410_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main landmarks of the city is the 10th-century castle, located on a hill overlooking the town. The primary role 
of the castle was to protect the nearby monastery and its residents from Moorish and Norman invasions. It is believed to 
be the birthplace or early residence of Afonso Henriques, who declared the country’s independence after the Battle of São 
Mamede in 1128, which took place near the castle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_162443_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explored the interior courtyard, climbed the towers, and walked along the eight towers, which offer panoramic views of 
Guimarães. The sunset view was stunning, and we could also see the Sanctuary of Penha, located on a nearby hill. According 
to my friends, it’s a lovely place to visit if you have more time, popular for weddings because the view from there is 
spectacular. The sanctuary, built in the 1930s, is an example of modernist architecture. Monte da Penha is covered in 
forests and massive granite boulders, making it a perfect spot for nature lovers and hikers. Located at an altitude of 
around 617 meters, the sanctuary offers breathtaking panoramic views of Guimarães and the surrounding countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_163805_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_162154_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_164457_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This castle is not just a fortress—it is a symbol of Portugal’s national identity and independence. Its well-preserved 
structure, combined with its historical importance, makes it a must-see destination for anyone exploring the roots of 
the Portuguese nation. It is also part of the UNESCO World Heritage Site designation for the Historic Centre of Guimarães.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From Pedralva, take a local bus to Braga for just €2 (around 40 minutes, tickets available from the driver) or opt for 
an Uber ride for €14 (20 minutes).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Santa Maria de Braga Cathedral: Entry ticket €2, includes a small museum.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sanctuary of Our Lady of Sameiro: Large, free parking area located just below the church.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bom Jesus do Monte: Upper parking costs €1, located next to the church. Funicular tickets are €2 for a single trip or 
€3 for a round trip.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restaurants we visited:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tíbias de Braga: A pastry shop offering local delights like tibias. These light, slightly crunchy pastries are filled 
with soft pastry cream and sprinkled with sugar. I tried the lemon-flavored one, which was tasty but a bit too sweet for my liking.
Address: Av. São Miguel O Anjo 5, 4700-210 Braga, Portugal.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Casa das Natas: A pastry shop offering amazing Pastel de nata, just next to the main city bus station.
Address: 4, Pç. da Galiza 8, Portugal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tabernabelga.pt/&quot;&gt;Taberna Belga&lt;/a&gt; Known for its francesinhas. This place doesn’t accept reservations, so 
there’s often a queue even before opening time. A waitress waits outside to take down names and the number of people. 
Once the restaurant opens, names are called systematically to avoid chaos. We arrived just before opening time and 
waited 20 minutes to get in. By the time we left, the queue was significantly longer, so arriving early is a good idea.
This dish was way too heavy for me because of the amount of sauce, even when taking half of the portion!&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rotiveminho: Serves traditional Portuguese dishes. Very popular, we arrived just before opening time and there were no 
free tables 20minutes later (most of them were with reservation). We tried salmon and it was very tasty.
Address: R. do Raio 301, 4710-924 Braga, Portugal.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/IMG-20241206-WA0020_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_124150_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guimaraes: We parked on Av. Dom Afonso Henriques street (coordinates: 41.436881, -8.295615), which offers free parking. 
A nearby side street, Rua da Indústria, also has many new parking spots (both streets are one-way).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guimarães Castle: Entry ticket €2 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pacodosduques.gov.pt/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Learn more here&lt;/a&gt;. There is a huge parking area 
behind the castle, which might be a good spot to park your car while visiting the city.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Palace of the Dukes of Braganza (Paço dos Duques de Bragança): Located next to the castle, entry ticket €6. We didn’t 
have time to visit the palace, but according to Google reviews, it’s really worth checking out. This medieval estate was 
built in the 15th century and served as a noble residence for the Dukes of Braganza until the 16th century. The palace 
was restored in the 20th century and converted into a museum with a fascinating collection that includes 15th- and 
16th-century furniture, ceramics, medieval arms, Portuguese art, and many artifacts related to the history of the 
Braganza dynasty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241207_162213_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Braga/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Braga/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>Braga</category>
        
        <category>city</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Rainy Day Adventure in Porto</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My journey started with a morning flight to Porto. With an evening train to Braga planned, I had the perfect opportunity 
to spend the day exploring Porto’s historic heart. After a quick 30-minute metro ride, I arrived at Bolhão station. As I 
stepped out, a light drizzle greeted me, turning my first mission into a hunt for an umbrella. Luckily, ALE-HOP, my 
daughter’s favorite shop, came to the rescue with a cheerful selection of umbrellas. 
My next stop was the nearby Mercado do Bolhão, as my stomach started to rumble, and this place has a roof, which was 
especially useful in such unpleasant weather. This market was first established as an open-air market, but in 1914, the 
current neoclassical building was opened. The place was re-opened in 2022 after a major renovation, and you can clearly 
see the changes—it’s modern, well-organized, and clean. It has a glass-covered roof, allowing natural light to reach the 
vendors who sell fresh flowers, vegetables, fruits, meat, cheeses, olives, and seafood. Stalls with traditional handicrafts 
add to the market’s charm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_133924_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_134147_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also find authentic Portuguese dishes at the market, from francesinha (a Porto sandwich) to fresh pastries like 
Pastéis de Nata. These iconic Portuguese pastries originated from the Mosteiro dos Jerónimos in Belém, Lisbon, in the early 
19th century, where Catholic monks developed the first recipe. I’ve had the pleasure of visiting the monastery and Fábrica 
de Pastéis de Belém, the birthplace of these pastries, &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2022/03/Lisbon-Portugal/&quot;&gt;during our first trip to Lisbon&lt;/a&gt;. These are definitely my favorite pastries in Portugal, 
and I would never get bored of eating them.
It’s very interesting to learn why monks created this pastry, which is rich in egg yolks. Monks and nuns used large 
quantities of egg whites to starch clothes, such as habits. The leftover egg yolks were creatively repurposed into desserts. 
Brilliant, right?
The pastry shell should be really crispy—you should clearly hear it when biting into a piece—and the rich, creamy custard 
center creates the perfect contrast in textures and flavors. They’re best when eaten warm and fresh. I tried one at the 
famous bakery Manteigaria, next to the market, and it did not disappoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_140403_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_140313_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearby, the Chapel of Souls is definitely worth a quick stop. Its unique exterior, entirely covered in blue and white 
azulejo tiles, is visible from a distance. These stunning ceramic tiles depict scenes from the lives of saints and were 
added to the chapel in 1929. Located on Porto’s main shopping street, Rua de Santa Catarina, the blue azulejos cover an 
impressive area of about 360 square meters. This chapel is a perfect example of beautiful and unique architecture that 
deserves a visit when exploring the vibrant Bolhão area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_140835_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_141036_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_141054_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued my walk toward Gaia and the iconic Luís I Bridge. This remarkable structure features two levels, each serving 
distinct purposes: the upper deck for trams and pedestrians, and the lower deck for vehicles and pedestrians. Designed by 
Théophile Seyrig, a student of Gustave Eiffel, and completed in 1886, the bridge reflects the rapid industrialization and 
urban development of Porto during that era.
Walking along the upper deck offers breathtaking panoramic views of the Douro River, Porto’s historic Ribeira district, 
and the wine cellars of Vila Nova de Gaia. Its unique two-level design is both functional and visually stunning, making 
it one of Portugal’s most photographed landmarks. I particularly enjoyed the misty weather, which added a magical touch 
to the views of the river and surrounding green hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_150555_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_150709_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_150642_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_151913_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_153140_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mosteiro da Serra do Pilar, a 16th-century monastery and UNESCO World Heritage Site, provides one of the best panoramic 
viewpoints over Porto and the Douro River. After visiting the viewpoint near the monastery, I continued my journey into 
the Gaia district, passing through Jardim do Morro. Gaia is well-known for its Port wine lodges, where visitors can learn 
about the production of this iconic wine and indulge in tastings. A cable car connects the riverside with the upper part 
of Gaia, offering scenic views of the city and the river below. I chose to walk down the narrow streets beneath the cable 
car and along the riverside promenade. This vibrant area is lined with restaurants, cafés, and shops, all offering stunning 
views of Porto and the Luís I Bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_153459_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_153727_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many urban areas in Portugal, Gaia faced economic challenges during the 20th century, resulting in periods of neglect. 
As industries declined and people moved to modern housing developments, many buildings were abandoned. Restoring these 
historical properties can be costly, and owners often lack the resources to renovate, especially when complex ownership 
or legal disputes are involved. This issue is similar to what is happening in Funchal, Madeira.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the rise in tourism has brought renewed interest in revitalizing Gaia. Projects like the WOW (World of Wine) 
district have transformed abandoned spaces into vibrant cultural and leisure destinations. As seen in the photo below, 
some rooftops remain collapsed, but efforts are ongoing to restore the area and breathe new life into its historical charm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_152535_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porto São Bento train station, another place where stunning azulejo tilework can be admired, over 20,000 azulejo tiles! 
It is not just a transport hub but also a cultural and architectural gem that attracts countless visitors. It has very 
convenient location, just in the heart of Porto. Scenes from Portugal’s history,traditional rural life, including festivals, 
markets, and customs can be spotted on the walls. Name of this station originated from former Benedictine monastery. 
Despite its historical charm, São Bento is a fully operational railway station, serving regional and intercity trains, 
including train to Braga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_145023_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_145300_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jardins do Palácio de Crista, well-maintained park with fountains, sculptures was a perfect destination for a leisurely stroll.
However, I would not recommend this place if you have only 6h to visit the city and weather is not great :) At the heart 
of the gardens stands the Pavilhão Rosa Mota, also known as the Super Bock Arena. This multipurpose venue hosts concerts, 
sports events, and exhibitions. I have noticed some  peacocks there but they were all hiding under the roof of the pavilion.
The gardens were originally designed around the Crystal Palace, that was destroyed in 1951 but park kept the same name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_164132_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to the park, I noticed vintage tramcars, symbol of the city’s history and charm. Operated by STCP (Sociedade 
de Transportes Colectivos do Porto), these historic trams are one way to explore its streets. There are only still 3 lines 
that are operating through Porto’s most picturesque areas. The trams are beautifully restored and retain their original 
wooden elements and classic design. If you’re interested in the history of Porto’s tram network, visit the Museu do Carro 
Eléctrico (Tram Museum) and its collection of vintage tramcars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_162405_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was already getting dark when I passed the Christmas market in Jardim da Cordoaria. Though small, it was a pleasant place 
to explore. The streets nearby were filled with the smoky aroma of roasted chestnuts, sold by many vendors using traditional 
carts with small coal ovens. The smoke from the carts created a cozy, festive atmosphere as people walked by. Roasted chestnuts 
are typically sold on the streets during the autumn and winter months, from October to January, making them a seasonal favorite. 
I first tried this healthy snack a few weeks ago on Madeira and really liked them! They’re quite filling and are served in 
small paper cones, perfect for enjoying on the go. The towering structure near the Christmas market turned out to be the 
Clérigos Church, an iconic landmark in Porto. Unfortunately, I couldn’t enter without a ticket as the Spiritus Light Show 
was ongoing at the time. All the Christmas decorations started to light up on the streets, and despite the rainy weather, 
the atmosphere in the city was cheerful. Igreja do Carmo church was another one in the area of the Christmas market that 
caught my attention, visible on the top photo below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_171304_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_180607_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_180859_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to the train station to catch my train to Braga, I realized I hadn’t visited Porto Cathedral! With an hour left 
before my train’s departure, I quickly rushed to the Batalha neighborhood, where the cathedral is located.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching from Avenida Dom Afonso Henriques, the cathedral’s fortress-like appearance immediately caught my attention. 
There were also Christmas stalls along this part of the street, adding to the festive atmosphere of the city. I explored 
the almost deserted area around the cathedral and walked a bit downhill, wandering through narrow streets. 
By then, it was already dark, so unfortunately, there were no views of the Douro River or the Luís I Bridge from the 
cathedral square. The cathedral is a significant stop on the Camino de Santiago pilgrimage route, and it’s common to 
see pilgrims beginning their journey here. While my visit was brief, it was still fascinating to experience this historic 
and iconic landmark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_182435_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_182421_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_182837_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my day in Porto came to an end, I couldn’t help but smile at how much I managed to see and experience in just a few 
hours. From the lively Mercado do Bolhão to the stunning azulejo tiles at São Bento station, the city had a way of surprising 
me at every turn. The Christmas lights glowing in the drizzle and the smoky aroma of roasted chestnuts made the streets 
feel so cozy, even in the rain.&lt;br /&gt;
As I hopped on the train to Braga, I knew one thing for sure—I’d be back to explore even more someday&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Metro ticket was 2.85 euro (2.25euro zone Z4 + Andante card 0.60euro). Andante card can be re-chargeable. On the ticket machine, 
there was a sticker with all metro station names and next to the, there was a zone that applies when you go there from 
the airport. I went to Bolhão metro station so it was Z4. You can also check &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.metrodoporto.pt/pages/391&quot;&gt;more details&lt;/a&gt;
however when I check connection Aeroporto – Bolhao, price for single ticket was 2euro so website is not showing correct 
ticket fare (zone was correct though).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Restaurant in Porto PAPO CHEIO - A Tasca de Cedofeita, the restaurant has a small surface inside and tables outside and
serves delicious local dishes. Superb value and very friendly service.
Address: R. de Cedofeita 95, 4050-166 Porto, Portugal&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Portugal/Porto/20241205_173014_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Manteigaria – &lt;a href=&quot;https://manteigaria.com/&quot;&gt;Fábrica de Pastéis de Nata&lt;/a&gt; sells fresh and hot Pastel de Nata with tasty and very soft
cream. Pastries are prepare and baked on spot (€1.30 a piece).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Train from Porto to Braga was 3.95 euro (3.45euro ticket + 0.50euro SIGA card). This card is reusable and has contactless 
technology to carry up to 31 single tickets that can be used in either direction. Using the ticket machine was a bit 
challenging, as even when switched to English, the translation was inaccurate. It took a few attempts and a bit of trial 
and error to figure out how to purchase the correct ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Porto/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/12/Porto/</guid>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>city</category>
        
        <category>Porto</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Family’s Guide to Valencia: Ocean Adventures, Culture, and Scenic Escapes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We paired our stay in Platja de Gandia with a one-day trip to Oceanogràfic, an 
oceanarium located within the stunning Gardens of Turia in the heart of Valencia. More details on how we traveled there 
can be found in the practical section at the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for an unforgettable experience with marine life, Oceanogràfic in Valencia should be at the top of your list. As 
the largest aquarium in Europe, it’s the kind of place where you can easily spend an entire day. From dolphins and 
beluga whales to sharks, penguins, turtles, and an incredible variety of fish, this destination captivates visitors of 
all ages while promoting sustainability and environmental awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so much to explore, plan to spend at least 4–5 hours (or more) to fully enjoy everything. The park is cleverly 
divided into zones, each representing different marine habitats from around the world. One of the standout features is 
the underwater tunnels, where you’re surrounded by breathtaking views of sharks and rays gliding gracefully overhead. 
These tunnels are pure magic but can get crowded since they are one-way only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_115942.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_143015.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A personal highlight? The beluga whales. These charming creatures are as adorable as you can imagine and an absolute must-see.
Oceanogràfic rescued two belugas from the horrors of the war in Ukraine in June of this year. It is the only facility on 
the continent that houses belugas and was able to assist with this very challenging rescue operation. Currently, the new 
belugas are undergoing recovery and acclimation in separate areas that are not accessible or viewable by the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jellyfish tanks were almost hypnotizing visitors with their graceful, harmonic movements. While 
there’s no shortage of fascinating animals, don’t be surprised if some exhibits, like the crocodiles, are a bit 
underwhelming—we only managed to spot one during our visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_145010.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_133136.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_125537.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For families with kids, the dolphin show is the star attraction. There are typically three shows per day, and we 
recommend arriving at least 20–25 minutes early to secure good seats. For us, this was enough time, but some reviews 
mention that the shows can fill up even with that much time in advance. The show itself lasts less than 20 minutes and 
is both fun and educational, with English subtitles on a big screen for 
non-Spanish speakers. Watching the trainers interact with these intelligent creatures was a delight, and the focus on 
environmental issues rather than elaborate tricks made it all the more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/P8273833.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_154023.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_153437.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pick up a map at the reception near the entrance—it’ll save you time and make exploring easier. The layout is intuitive, 
but there is a lot to see, and a map ensures you don’t miss any of the highlights. Additionally, you can enter the 
underground aquariums in one place and exit in a completely different part of the park, which left us a bit confused and 
disoriented at times. If your toddler uses a pram, you’ll need to locate elevators for each underground zone and leave 
it in a small designated storage area while attending the dolphin show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oceanogràfic has a variety of food stands and restaurants (most with poor reviews), but be prepared for 
higher-than-average prices. While the no-outside-food policy might seem strict, many visitors managed to sneak in some 
snacks. Alternatively, bring sandwiches and enjoy them before entering the park—this was our strategy, and it worked 
perfectly (though we still had small snacks inside, not entirely following the rule). Once inside, vending machines 
with drinks are convenient for a quick refresh. If you’re looking for a special treat, the submarine restaurant offers 
a unique dining experience, but be sure to book ahead as it fills up quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After our long visit to Oceanogràfic, we only managed to walk back to the train station on foot, admiring along the way 
the beautiful Turia Gardens, which now stretch more than 8 km and were developed on the dry riverbed of the Turia 
River. The row of uniquely designed buildings—including the Science Museum, Art Center, and IMAX Theater—is stunning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science Museum is particularly well-known, but we would have needed another day to visit it, and it might not be 
the best choice for our almost-three-year-old toddler. The Art Palace of Queen Sofia is Valencia’s Royal Opera House 
and also a venue for music, ballet, and theater performances. It can be visited with a guided tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_165324.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240827_165824.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visiting the rest of the city was something we saved for the last day before our flight back to Belgium. We booked one 
night in the city center, close to the Turia metro station, so we could easily reach the airport early the next morning. 
After dropping off our luggage at the apartment, we headed straight to the city center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first stop was the spectacular food market, &lt;strong&gt;Mercat Central de València&lt;/strong&gt;. This beautiful market offers a diverse 
selection of food—meats, seafood, baked goods, spices, and cheese—as well as ready-to-eat meals and drinks, allowing 
you to enjoy your food right there. Opened in 1928, it features a unique blend of iron, glass, and ceramics, with its 
central dome reaching nearly 30 meters high! It’s definitely worth a visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_132220.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_125403.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_125502_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_125349_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just opposite the market, you’ll find the Silk Exchange (La Lonja de la Seda), the historic marketplace that once 
thrived during Valencia’s booming silk trade. Recognized as a UNESCO World Heritage Site, it showcases stunning late 
Gothic architecture. Although we didn’t visit it ourselves, our friends highly recommended it, highlighting the 
beautiful ceiling and the twisting columns in the grand hall as standout features. There’s also a charming courtyard 
with a small garden of orange trees at its center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_125002.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next stop was Plaça de l’Ajuntament, home to Valencia’s City Hall, the Main Post Office, and several historic, 
beautiful banks. This square is a popular meeting point for both locals and tourists, as it serves as a hub for many 
bus routes. Flower stalls and a fountain add extra charm to this large, lively space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_133019.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading toward the main cathedral, we passed an intriguing building that turned out to be the &lt;strong&gt;Museu Nacional de 
Ceràmica i de les Arts Sumptuàries González Martí&lt;/strong&gt;, home to a vast collection of ceramics and artworks. Its stunning 
Baroque facade immediately caught our attention. Although we didn’t have time to explore the interior, it appears to 
be budget-friendly, offering free entry on weekends and discounts for certain visitors. With excellent reviews, 
it seems well worth a visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_134351.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were pleasantly surprised upon reaching Plaça de la Reina to discover misting water sprays that offered a refreshing 
cool-down on hot days. Situated right next to the iconic Valencia Cathedral, the square has been recently renovated 
and is surrounded by cafes, restaurants, and shops, making it a perfect spot to grab a bite or enjoy a drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_145242.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Valencia Cathedral, also known as the Cathedral of the Holy Chalice, is one of the city’s most iconic landmarks. 
Most visitors come to see the cup believed to have been used by Jesus at the Last Supper, which is kept in a dedicated 
chapel. Various architectural styles can be observed, a result of its long history of renovations since construction 
began in the 13th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_145643.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_150144.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Túria Fountain on Plaza de la Virgen, located right in front of the Basilica de la Mare de Déu, is a clear 
representation of the Túria River. The fountain features eight sculptures of women, symbolizing the eight main 
irrigation canals (acequias) that distribute water from the Túria to the surrounding fields. The square itself is 
stunning, surrounded by historic buildings, including the Basilica and the nearby Valencia Cathedral. Its vibrant 
atmosphere and rich history make it a must-visit spot in the heart of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_150552.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re searching for a peaceful escape from Valencia’s busy city center and the scorching afternoon sun, the Botanical 
Garden (Jardí Botànic) is the perfect oasis. Tucked away like a hidden gem yet still within walking distance, this 
tranquil park offers a refreshing change of scenery and a chance to reconnect with nature in the heart of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During our late-August visit, the garden wasn’t bursting with blooms, but it still showcased an incredible variety of 
plants, ranging from towering trees to delicate succulents. The old arboretum is another standout feature—its tall 
trees, planted decades ago, have grown to enormous sizes, with some even piercing through the roofs of nearby 
structures. Walking through this area feels like stepping into a magical forest. This spot is perfect for escaping 
Valencia’s summer heat. With plenty of shaded seating areas beneath sprawling tree 
canopies, you can sit back, relax, and enjoy the calm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_162025.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_160726.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_161559.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_155826.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Valencia/20240830_162311.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing this blog post after the catastrophic floods that hit the eastern Spanish region of Valencia at the end of 
October. It’s truly heartbreaking to see pictures and videos of people trapped in vehicles, buildings, and underground 
parking garages, caught completely off guard as the streets were transformed into rivers within moments. The root of this 
devastating event was a record-breaking downfall: a year’s worth of rain unleashed in just eight hours. When I visited 
Valencia a few months ago, the thought of such a disaster never even crossed my mind. The city seemed so 
vibrant, sunny, and resilient. Yet, nature had other plans, and I now realize how unpredictable things can be. This tragedy 
underscores the growing impact of climate change, with extreme weather events becoming alarmingly more 
frequent and intense. One can only hope that authorities will take this as a call to action, improving early-warning 
systems to prevent such a loss of life in the future. The destruction went beyond human tragedy, with infrastructure, 
bridges, and public buildings heavily damaged, leaving scars that will take years to repair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re arriving at Valencia’s Airport (Aeroport), it’s an easy trip to the city center. Metro lines 3 and 5 will take you from Aeroport to North Station (Xàtiva) in just 21 minutes, covering Zone AB+. The fare is €5.80 per person.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve already described how to get from Valencia to Platja de Gandia—you can find the details in a &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2024/10/Gandia_Cullera/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. From the North Train Station (near the Xàtiva metro stop), we took the metro to Ayora and then walked about 2 km on foot. It wasn’t the fastest way to get to the Oceanarium, but we enjoyed the walk nonetheless. For a more convenient option, the tram stops right in front of the Oceanarium and takes around 15 minutes to reach the city center. It might be a better alternative for those who prefer a quicker journey.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Children under 10 may travel free of charge when accompanied by an adult with a valid transport ticket. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.miivomobility.com/en/blog/Tarjeta-SUMA-ventajas&quot;&gt;SUMA 10 for 10 rides&lt;/a&gt; Zona A - €8, currently €4 due to a discount (single ticket €1.50 in Zone A). It can be used to make up to 15 simultaneous trips by people traveling together.&lt;br /&gt;
Note: The temporary partial reduction of 50% applies to SUMA 10, SUMA Monthly, SUMA Monthly Jove, TuiN tickets, and temporary Metrovalencia season tickets until January 31, 2025. We bought a SUMA 10 card and used it for all four of us, which was considerably cheaper than buying single metro tickets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://oceanografic.experticket.com/en&quot;&gt;Oceanogràfic&lt;/a&gt; - €34.70 per adult, booked online a few days in advance for a specific time slot. This means you will only be able to access the Oceanogràfic from the time selected during the purchase process, and you may stay in the aquarium until closing time. We bought tickets with a time slot at 10:00 a.m. and entered before 11:00, but there were people next to us who couldn’t enter with a ticket for the 12:00 slot, so it’s important to select your time wisely. Prices vary depending on the day, holiday week, etc. We took a train from Gandia as described in my other post, and then metro from Xàtiva to Ayora, with the last part on foot (almost 2 km).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Pro Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; If you’re visiting during peak summer months (July/August), plan to arrive right when the park opens at 10:00 a.m. The first dolphin show around 11:00 a.m. is less crowded, so it’s worth catching early in the day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;La Lonja de la Seda de Valencia - €2 admission fee, quick visit (a few rooms and the main hall, small courtyard).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://visit-cullera.es/guia/castillo-de-cullera/&quot;&gt;Botanical Garden&lt;/a&gt;, entrance fee €3, free for babies and toddlers. If you’re fast, you can be done in 30 minutes, but if you take your time, I would plan for 2 hours. It’s a relatively small garden compared to others around the world, but definitely a must-see at a very cheap price! It wasn’t crowded during our Friday afternoon visit. Clean restrooms are available.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/11/Valencia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/11/Valencia/</guid>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Valencia</category>
        
        <category>Oceanarium</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Coastal city Platja de Gandia, great destination for holidays with kids</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to combine relaxation on the beach with some city exploration, a stay in Platja de Gandia paired with a trip to 
Valencia is a perfect choice. It’s just a quick 1-hour and 15-minute train ride from Valencia’s city center to reach the 
charming seaside town of Platja de Gandia. During our trip, we also ventured to Cullera, another coastal gem, and explored the 
fascinating Oceanogràfic, situated within the stunning Gardens of Turia in Valencia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Platja de Gandia truly surprised us! With its 3-kilometer-long promenade, this beach was more than we expected. Our apartment 
was conveniently located just a street away, right next door to a cozy fruit shop, a small local bakery, and a spot offering coffee, 
warm chocolate, and freshly made churros (churreria). The beach itself is expansive, with soft, fine sand and wooden walkways that make 
access to the shore easy, especially for families with strollers or those with limited mobility. The beach is well-equipped 
with free restrooms, plenty of space for sunbathing, and most importantly, it was never overly crowded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_194625_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights of Platja de Gandia is its lively promenade, which comes alive in the evenings. It’s lined with shops, restaurants, 
and cafes, making it the perfect place for an evening stroll. Street vendors add to the vibrant atmosphere, selling handmade 
jewellery, sunglasses, football shirts, and plenty of souvenir trinkets. You’ll even find people offering henna tattoos or 
creating colorful braids for children. The promenade is wide, allowing sufficient space for pedestrians, cyclists, and scooters, 
though shade can be a bit hard to come by.One thing to note: the local council has banned 
dogs on the beach, so if you’re traveling with pets, you’ll need to make alternative plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Platja de Gandia is relatively unknown to international tourists. With most visitors being Spanish, English 
isn’t as common as one might assume and therefore, so we did encounter few issues in the restaurants when trying to find a 
table or make a reservation. Though knowledge of a few basic words in Spanish goes a long way!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/P8243643.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240824_125726_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240824_193443_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/IMG-20240829-WA0030_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights of our time at Gandia’s beach was the dedicated kite-flying area. Every afternoon around 5 PM, the 
local kite-club would gather to set up an array of colorful kites right on the beach, almost directly in front of our favorite 
ice cream spot, Cognigni. This group, known as “Cometas Gandia,” brings a playful, lively energy to the beach with their 
kites, many featuring fun characters like Tom and Jerry—an absolute hit with the kids! You can even follow them on Instagram 
for updates on their kite displays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_185700.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_185216.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a refreshing break from the beach, we did a day trip to Cullera by train, to visit the impressive Cullera Castle. The castle, 
built in the 10th century, sits atop a hill and offers stunning panoramic views of the city, the Mediterranean Sea, and 
the surrounding coastal area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The well-preserved fortress is a beautiful blend of Moorish, Gothic, and Romanesque architectural styles, showcasing its 
historical evolution over the centuries. Originally, the castle had several towers and walls, many of which have been restored, 
allowing visitors to experience its grandeur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most notable feature is the Torre del Racó de Sant Antoni, a tower that rewards you with breathtaking views of the 
landscape. Attached to the castle is the Sanctuary of the Virgen del Castillo, a quaint Gothic-style chapel built in the 
19th century. Inside the castle, there’s also a small museum with exhibits that highlight the history of the fortress and 
the region. You can explore ancient artifacts, including weapons, pottery, and medieval tools, giving you a fascinating 
glimpse into life during the castle’s active years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_104252.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_111407.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_111356.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_114637_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_115355.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After visiting the castle, we walked back down to the city and had a delicious lunch in 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/HaTVLGfD6GLiKt8J7&quot;&gt;Aroma de Grecia&lt;/a&gt;. There was also a lovely &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/ZhDGhQPShJEZgABs9&quot;&gt;bakery La Delicia&lt;/a&gt;
that served the most amazing savory spinach dumplings—definitely worth a try! We didn’t have time to follow the shore and
check the resto of the city and just had a break on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/9amFPqWC5wau2kJp9&quot;&gt;playground&lt;/a&gt; near the beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the city is a hidden gem, perfect for a family-friendly escape. An ideal spot to unwind, enjoy the sun, and 
soak up the local atmosphere! For an exciting day trip, hop on a train to nearby Cullera or Valencia or take a bus from nearby
Gandia to Alicante (buses leaving from Gania bus station, back side of the train station). In our opinion, wonderful alternative 
to tourist-heavy beach destinations—perfect for families looking to relax and experience something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re arriving at Valencia’s Airport (Aeroport), it’s an easy trip to the city center. Metro lines 3 and 5 will take 
you from Aeroport to North Station (Xàtiva) in just 21 minutes, covering Zone AB+. The fare is €5.80 per person.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From Valencia North Station, catch the C1 train to Gandia. Trains run every 30 to 60 minutes, and the journey takes 
about 1 hour and 15 minutes. A one-way ticket costs €6.30, but you can save €0.50 per trip by recharging your ticket, 
reducing the cost to €5.80. While most trains stop at Gandia, only a few continue on to Platja de Gandia. If your train 
terminates at Gandia, you can take bus L2 to the beach. The bus runs every 20 minutes and costs €1.60 (or €1.70 on Sundays). 
Tickets can be purchased directly from the driver.
The Platja de Gandia train station is quite basic, with just one platform and a ticket machine. However, the machine’s 
translations can be confusing for non-Spanish speakers, as not all options are fully translated. After purchasing your 
ticket, remember to validate it at a separate area on the platform before boarding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The beach near Platja de Gandia is well-equipped, offering public bathrooms every few meters, beach bars, and recycling 
bins to keep the area clean. There are also opportunities for sports like football and volleyball, plus exercise stations 
along the promenade. The beach is spotless, with public showers, toilets, and a first aid station available, making it 
family-friendly. Lifeguards and police on quads keep an eye on the beach, adding to the sense of security.
One thoughtful touch: beside each wooden walkway leading to the beach, there’s an information board with a map clearly 
marking all the nearby amenities.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240829_130608.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_192333_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/P8233575.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240824_094550_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240823_194758_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our favourites places to eat are listed below with amazing ice cream place that was our place to be every afternoon!
Note that most restaurants are closing in the early afternoon and reopening around 8pm where the whole city comes alive.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/2zBJ8acASm4TmJSK8&quot;&gt;Cognigni&lt;/a&gt;: Amazing Argentinean icecream&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/MqcaPoHHPfbn2Lqd7&quot;&gt;INDIAN RASOI&lt;/a&gt;: Indian Food - Try the Goan Chicken !&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/ixtKCKtX8iJ115bXA&quot;&gt;Restaurante Boga&lt;/a&gt;: Local project to provide jobs to people with intellectual disabilities and promote social integration - Menu changes daily&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/sesQQSkJVCbdM6NeA&quot;&gt;Restaurante Casa José&lt;/a&gt;: A wide variety of sea-food and local dishes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240826_153143_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240826_180430_01.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cullera &lt;a href=&quot;https://visit-cullera.es/guia/castillo-de-cullera/&quot;&gt;Castle&lt;/a&gt;, is a great spot for a family outing, with entry
tickets priced at just €3 for adults, and kids seem to 
get in for free (at least we weren’t asked to pay for our toddlers). While none of the towers or the different sections 
of walls surrounding the castle were open during our visit, the overall experience was still worth it because of the views.
You can either drive right up to the castle and park there or walk from the Mercat de Cullera (which also has public 
toilets). There seems to be some confusion in reviews about an elevator to the castle—just to clarify, the lift only 
takes you from the parking area to the castle entrance, which is just a few meters up, and there’s another one after 
the ticket office to the main entrance.
Since we arrived by train and had our prams with us, we decided to start our ascent by foot from the market. If you’re 
walking with strollers, we recommend taking Carrer del Calvari to avoid any stairs. Our stroll through the picturesque 
Barri del Pou area wasn’t too difficult, with only a few steps here and there. It was absolutely worth it though—the 
charming white stairways, stone walls, and lush plants growing along the narrow, clean streets made the walk feel magical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_105123.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Gandia/20240825_114809.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/10/Gandia_Cullera/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/10/Gandia_Cullera/</guid>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Valencia</category>
        
        <category>Gandia</category>
        
        <category>Cullera</category>
        
        <category>castle</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Odkrywanie tajemnic holenderskich tulipanów</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;W Holandii kwiecień jest najlepszym miesiącem na podziwianie pięknych tulipanów. Zaplanowaliśmy wycieczkę do Keukenhof, 
przejażdżkę rowerową przez pola tulipanów oraz obchody Dnia Króla, a wszystko to podczas długiego weekendu. W dalszej części 
tekstu, dowiesz się kilku ciekawych szczegółów o tych słynnych kwiatach!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tulipany pochodzą z północnych regionów Himalajów, z Azji Centralnej, i były po raz pierwszy uprawiane w starożytnej Persji 
już w X wieku jako symbol wdzięku i piękna. Stamtąd tulipany rozprzestrzeniły się na zachód, docierając w końcu do Stambułu, 
co otworzyło im drzwi do Europy. W drugiej połowie XVI wieku podróżnicy przywieźli cebulki i kwiaty do różnych krajów, znajdując 
szczególnie entuzjastyczną publiczność w Holandii. To zapoczątkowało holenderską uprawę tulipanów, a ważne odmiany pojawiły 
się zaledwie kilka dekad później, na zawsze kształtując historię tego pięknego kwiatu. Nasz plan podróży obejmował wizytę na 
farmie tulipanów, przejażdżkę rowerową wzdłuż pól tulipanowych oraz zwiedzanie słynnych ogrodów Keukenhof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_170101.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naszą przygodę rozpoczęliśmy od przejażdżki rowerowej przez pola tulipanów, tworząc pętlę z Leiden do Sassenheim, Hillegom, 
Lisse, Voorhout i z powrotem do Leiden, pokonując prawie 50 km pierwszego dnia (szczegółowa mapa trasy na samym końcu postu). 
Wyposażeni w uchwyty na telefon na naszych rowerach i dobrze oznakowaną trasę na Google Maps, bez trudu odnajdywaliśmy się
w terenie i nasza przejażdżka była czystą przyjemnością (pomijając przelotne opady deszczu). Holenderskie ścieżki rowerowe są 
niesamowicie intuicyjne i świetnie oznaczone. Nasza wycieczka zbiegła się z Dniem Króla, narodowym świętem przypadającym na 26 kwietnia, 
kiedy każde małe miasto ożywa dzięki ulicznym imprezom, a ludzie ubrani w jaskrawe odcienie koloru pomarańczowego, świętują urodziny króla. 
Ku naszemu wielkiemu zaskoczeniu, większość pól tulipanowych została już ścięta, co – jak później się dowiedzieliśmy – miało miejsce 
w tym roku dwa tygodnie wcześniej niż zazwyczaj. Pomimo to, bardzo podobała nam się nasza wycieczka, to mogliśmy sobie tylko wyobrazić,
jak cudownie muszą wyglądać te pola w pełnym rozkwicie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_160322.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC07901.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_175205.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_162953.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_165150.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W okolicy tej znajduje się sporo farm, na których można obejrzeć male pola pokazowe wielu gatunków tulipanów,&lt;br /&gt;
z konkretnymi nazwami i numerami, których cebulki można potem zamówić online. Jest to świetna okazja, aby zobaczyć różne 
odmiany i wybrać te, które najlepiej będą pasować do Naszego ogrodu!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_175129.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_170210.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC07868.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_150613.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farma Tulipanów “De Tulperij” to uroczy, rodzinny biznes, który rozpoczął działalność w 1927 roku. Syn właściciela postanowił 
przejąć farmę i wkrótce rozpocznie nią zarządzać jako już czwarte pokolenie tej rodziny. Farma znajduje się w pobliżu ogrodów 
Keukenhof i jest otwarta w tym samym czasie, co ogrody. Goście, którzy zapisali się na specjalne zwiedzanie farmy, są 
osobiście witani przez właściciela i jego żonę.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_150031.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134648.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_142701.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ponieważ dołączyliśmy do takiej wycieczki z przewodnikiem, otrzymaliśmy kilka bezcennych wskazówek o tym, jak skuteczniej 
uprawiać tulipany w naszych własnych ogrodach. Jedną z kluczowych decyzji jest sadzenie tulipanów w piaszczystej glebie z 
wysokim poziomem wód gruntowych. Na ten farmie woda gruntowa znajduje się zaledwie 65 cm poniżej powierzchni, co eliminuje 
potrzebę dodatkowego nawadniania, a potencjalny nadmiar wody jest kierowany do systemów odprowadzających wodę. Dowiedzieliśmy się 
również, jak ważne jest rotowanie cebulek tulipanów w różnych miejscach ogrodu każdego roku, aby zapobiec rozwojowi 
chorób bakteryjnych i wirusowych wokół cebulek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otrzymaliśmy również szczegółowe wyjaśnienie procesu uprawy tulipanów krok po kroku. “De Tulperij” to farma zajmująca się 
uprawą cebulek, w przeciwieństwie do farm zajmujących się uprawą kwiatów, co oznacza, że nie uprawiają tulipanów przez 
cały rok. Natomiast inne farmy uprawiają tulipany nieprzerwanie, zimą jedynie w szklarniach. Co ciekawe, 80% tulipanów produkowanych w 
Holandii pozostaje w kraju, a jedynie 20% jest eksportowanych.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W “De Tulperij” cała praca rozpoczyna się między październikiem a grudniem, kiedy cebulki tulipanów są sadzone i ochraniane 
sianem przed mrozem. Potrzebują one niższych temperatur przez kilka miesięcy, aby zakwitnąć na wiosnę, najlepiej około 9°C. 
Gdy nadchodzi wiosna i tulipany zaczynają kwitnąć, hodowcy starannie sprawdzają, czy wirusy nie zaatakowały ich upraw, 
usuwając wszelkie pojedyńcze rośliny, które odstają swoim wyglądem od pozostałych, czy to innym ubarwieniem płatków lub brakiem
części liści.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dowiedzieliśmy się, że moment ścinania kwiatów, który zazwyczaj ma miejsce w pierwszej połowie maja, w tym roku 
miał miejsce 2 tygodnie wcześniej. Ścinanie kwiatów pomaga zmniejszyć aktywność owadów wokół tulipanów i zapewnia, że energia 
z rośliny jest kierowana na rozwój cebulek, a nie na utrzymanie kwiatów i dalszą produkcję nasion. Po ścięciu kwiatów cebulki pozostają w ziemi przez kolejne 
6-8 tygodni, aż liście zżółkną. Następnie cebulki są zbierane, ręcznie czyszczone (proces zwany “obieraniem”), suszone i 
przechowywane w ciemnym, wentylowanym miejscu do następnego sezonu kiedy ich sadzenie zacznie się od nowa. Z jednej cebulki 
matecznej można spodziewać się do pięciu małych cebulek potomnych.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niewielka część cebulek jest nadal sprzedawana na aukcjach. Duże cebulki przeznaczone na rynki międzynarodowe są dokładnie myte, 
aby wyeliminować wszelkie bakterie lub grzyby. Mniejsze cebulki są przechowywane i ponownie sadzone jesienią. Cebulki 
potomne potrzebują dwóch do trzech lat, aby urosnąć na tyle, by można je było przeznaczyć na sprzedaż.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NFarma De Tulperij od 2001 roku posiada nowy kolor tulipanów, pomarańczowy, który jest naprawdę rzadki i kosztuje o 30% 
więcej niż czerwone tulipany. Najbardziej powszechnymi kolorami są czerwone, żółte i fioletowe tulipany a wprowadzenie 
nowej odmiany na rynek zajmuje średnio 20 lat. Te nowe odmiany mogą powstawać przypadkowo poprzez losowe mutacje, jak 
miało to miejsce w przypadku pomarańczowego tulipana na tej farmie, lub poprzez celowe krzyżowanie. Hodowcy starannie 
izolują cebulki o niezwykłych kolorach, a kiedy w następnym roku zakwitną one w takim samym kolorze, to wiedzą, że jest 
to stała mutacja i wtedy mogą zacząć powiększać liczbę cebulek, aby w końcu móc zacząć je sprzedawać co jest wieloletnim procesem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134800.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134734.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Każda nowa odmiana tulipanów otrzymuje certyfikat od Banku Genów, świadczący o jej wyjątkowości i tożsamości. Od samego 
początku tulipany były nazywane imionami znanych osobistości lub hodowców. Najbardziej znany z tulipanów to “Semper Augustus”, 
nazwany na cześć cesarza rzymskiego Augusta w XVI wieku.
Jedną z ciekawostek, której nauczyliśmy się od rolnika z De Tulperij, był unikalny proces uprawy hiacyntów. W przeciwieństwie 
do tulipanów przy ich uprawie używa się specjalnej techniki, w której rolnicy ręcznie uszkadzają dolną część cebulek. Ten 
zaskakujący etap powoduje szybkie ich ponowne namnażanie się, produkcję 20-30 nowych cebulek w zaledwie 2-3 miesiące. 
Następnie każda nowa cebulka jest starannie oddzielana ręcznie i musi rosnąć przez trzy lata, zanim będzie wystarczająco 
duża, by wydać kwiaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ostatni nas dzień poświęciliśmy wizycie w słynnym Keukenhof, który został założony w 1949 roku (dokładnie 75 lat temu!). Na 
zdjęciu poniżej widać dawne wejście do parku, które nadal jest jedną z jego cech charakterystycznych. Ogród 
początkowo został otwarty, aby pokazać najlepsze cebulki kwiatów, jakie holenderski przemysł kwiatowy miał do zaoferowania
w tamtych czasach, i od tego momentu stał się jednym z największych i najbardziej znanych ogrodów kwiatowych na świecie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_101110.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_101832.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_102448.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090529.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jedną z głównych atrakcyjnych Keukenhof jest jego uroczy wiatrak, pierwotnie wyprodukowany w Groningen w 1892 
roku i ofiarowany przez firmę żeglugową. Z platformy na szczycie wiatraka zazwyczaj można podziwiać zapierające dech w 
piersiach widok na kolorowe póla tulipanów, gdy są one w pełnym rozkwicie. Jednak podczas naszej wizyty otaczające pola 
pozbawione już były kwiatów.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 milionów cebulkowych roślin wiosennych, tworzy żywy katalog aż 100 prezentujących swoje odmiany hodowców oraz firm na ponad 
20 wystawach kwiatowych na terenie tego ogrodu. Na początku sezonu można podziwiać w pełnym rozkwicie krokusy, żonkile, 
hiacynty oraz wczesne tulipany. W miarę postępu sezonu ogród przekształca się, pojawiają się coraz większe tulipany i 
inne kwiaty. Osoby sadzące i projektujące ten ogród dbają o to, aby każdego tygodnia kwitły inne rośliny, co daje nam gwarancję, 
że będzie tam zawsze pięknie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keukenhof to obowiązkowe miejsce dla każdego miłośnika kwiatów, zapewniające spektakularne widowisko piękna 
natury. Warto jednak zauważyć, że park może być dość zatłoczony, nawet w poniedziałkowe poranki. Choć doświadczenie jest 
niewątpliwie magiczne, nie jest to coś, co chciałbym powtarzać co roku ze względu na ogromną liczbę odwiedzających. Niemniej 
jednak Keukenhof pozostaje rajem dla miłośników kwiatów, który należy zobaczyć przynajmniej raz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090751.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08099.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08066.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08102.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.easyfiets.nl/en/&quot;&gt;Easy Fiets in Leiden&lt;/a&gt; Personel był bardzo miły, a nawet mogliśmy oddać rowery po godzinach otwarcia, 
jednak rowery były dość małe, a jazda nimi przez 50 km nie była łatwa.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/Screenshot 2024-05-02 223301.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tulipstore.eu/nl/service/tulip-store-showtuin/&quot;&gt;Tulip Store Showgarden&lt;/a&gt; 
To ogród pokazowy tulipanów z dużymi polami tulipanów, do które można wejść bez opłaty. Inne miejsce z pięknymi 
polami znajdowało się obok firmy Vernooij VOF, nie będącej farmą tulipanów, ale mającą piękne pola które były także łatwo dostępne.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Podczas naszej wycieczki rowerowej, podążaliśmy głównie trasą rowerową wyznaczoną na stronie &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/cxvXKUircv5tzJJw6?g_st=aw&quot;&gt;Flowermap.nl&lt;/a&gt;.
Można ją otworzyć i zostanie się natychmiast przekierowany do Google Maps, co sprawia, że korzystanie z tej mapy jest bardzo 
łatwe. Następnie wystarczy śledzić znaczniki na mapie. Pominęliśmy jedną pętlę, która prowadzi nad morze, ponieważ 
pogoda była niestabilna, a my nadal musieliśmy wrócić do Leiden. Nasze koleżanki pokonały ten fragment i potwierdziły, 
że krajobraz zmienia się drastycznie, a wydmy prezentują się zachwycająco nawet przy wietrznej i burzowej pogodzie.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tulip Farm &lt;a href=&quot;https://detulperij.nl/&quot;&gt;De Tulperij&lt;/a&gt; w Voorhout - można dołączyć do wycieczki po polach tulipanów
(3 wycieczki każdego dnia, po angielsku i niderlandzku). Jest także szklarnia kwiatowa z kawą, herbatą i holenderskim 
goframi, pięknie udekorowana. Można również kupić wiele pamiątek związanych z tulipanami oraz słynną porcelaną z Delft. Podczas naszej 
wizyty nie było możliwe zakupienie żadnych cebulek, ale można je wybrać online i zostaną wysłane później pod wskazany adres. 
Jeśli kiedykolwiek znajdziesz 
się w pobliżu Ogrodów Keukenhof, wizyta w De Tulperij to konieczność dla każdego miłośnika kwiatów! Wizyta trwała 
prawie godzinę i obejmowała 20-minutowy film oraz czas na zdjęcia na polach, które nie są dostępne dla każdego 
odwiedzającego. Na tej farmie można również zobaczyć dalie – od początku sierpnia do początku października, kiedy farma 
ponownie jest otwarta dla zwiedzających. Należy jednak zauważyć, że choć każdy może zobaczyć ogród pokazowy tulipanów, 
aby robić zdjęcia na polach, należy zarezerwować wizytę z przewodnikiem.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134831.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://keukenhof.nl/nl/&quot;&gt;Keukenhof&lt;/a&gt; To prawdopodobnie najczęściej odwiedzane miejsce w Holandii podczas tych kilku tygodni, gdy jest 
otwarte. Liczba dużych autokarów turystycznych na parkingach, które mijaliśmy w sobotę podczas jazdy na rowerze, była 
oszałamiająca, nie wspominając już o liczbie samochodów zaparkowanych na różnych parkingach wokół słynnych ogrodów. 
Byliśmy zadowoleni, że zarezerwowaliśmy bilety na poniedziałkowe przedpołudnie o 8:30 rano. Jedynym problemem, z którym 
się zetknęliśmy, to znalezienie właściwego parkingu. Wszędzie było tak pusto rano, że nie byliśmy pewni, gdzie się udać. Skończyło się na tym, 
że pojechaliśmy na dwa różne parkingi, zanim ktoś w końcu nas skierował do właściwego, tracąc prawie 20 minut. Wydaje się, 
że wyznaczony parking zmienia się w ciągu dnia, więc jeśli przyjeżdża się z samego rana, to zdecydowanie trzeba udać się na główny parking 
(współrzędne: 52.268923, 4.551555). To ten sam parking, gdzie można wynająć rowery.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do godziny 11:00 rano liczba odwiedzających w parku była rozsądna. Po tej godzinie zaczęło się robić naprawdę tłoczno. 
Zauważyliśmy coraz więcej dużych grup, co utrudniało poruszanie się po niektórych obszarach. Ponieważ odwiedzaliśmy 
park po ścięciu pól tulipanów, nie warto było spieszyć się do wiatraka, ponieważ widok nie był już tak spektakularny bez kolorowych 
pól otaczających to miejsce. Zamiast tego polecamy udać się do Ogrodu Historycznego, który jest popularnym miejscem do robienia zdjęć selfie, 
jak później zauważyliśmy. Po zwiedzeniu parku udało nam się jeszcze przejść do centrum miasta Lisse na lunch 
(mniej niż 20 minut pieszo) i potem wróciliśmy na parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090553.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2024/05/Lisse-Tulipany/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2024/05/Lisse-Tulipany/</guid>
        
        <category>Holandia</category>
        
        <category>Keukenhof</category>
        
        <category>rower</category>
        
        <category>tulipany</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discovering the secrets of tulips in the Netherlands</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, April is the best month to view Holland’s beautiful tulips. We packed a trip to Keukenhof, cycling 
through tulip fields, and King’s Day celebrations into a single long weekend. Read on to discover what we learned about 
these iconic flowers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tulips originated north of the Himalayas, in Central Asia, and were first cultivated in ancient Persia as early as the 
10th century as a symbol of grace and beauty. From there, tulips spread westward, eventually reaching Istanbul, which 
opened the door to Europe. By the second half of the 16th century, travellers had brought bulbs and flowers to various 
countries, finding a particularly enthusiastic audience in the Netherlands. This marked the beginning of Dutch tulip 
cultivation, with important varieties emerging just a few decades later, forever shaping the history of this beautiful bloom. 
We started our weekend trip with the main goal of understanding tulip cultivation better and admiring the stunning 
variations growing in the fields around Lisse. Our travel schedule included visiting a tulip farm, cycling along tulip 
fields, and exploring the famed Keukenhof gardens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_170101.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started our adventure by cycling through the tulip fields, creating a loop from Leiden to Sassenheim, Hillegom, Lisse, 
Voorhout, and back to Leiden, covering nearly 50 km on the first day (detailed map in practical info section). Equipped 
with phone holders on our bikes and a 
well-marked route on Google Maps, navigation was a breeze. Dutch cycling paths are incredibly intuitive, and we didn’t 
get lost once. Coinciding with our trip was King’s Day, a national celebration on April 26th, where every small city 
burst into street parties with people dressed in vibrant orange, celebrating the King’s birthday. To our surprise, most 
of the tulip fields had already been cut, which we later learned happened two weeks earlier than usual this year. Despite 
this, we thoroughly enjoyed our tour and couldn’t help but imagine the sheer beauty of the fields in full bloom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_160322.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC07901.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_175205.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_162953.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_165150.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We passed few tulip farms where we could see small show gardens with many types of tulips with specific names 
and numbers to make it very easy to order them online. A great chance to see different types and choose the one that 
will fit your garden best!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_175129.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_170210.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC07868.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240427_150613.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tulip Farm De Tulperij is a charming family-run business that started in 1927. The son of the owner decided to take over 
the farm and will start the 4th generation in the near future. Visitors are welcomed personally by the owners, the farmer, 
and his wife. It’s located near Keukenhof Gardens and is open during the same time as the gardens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_150031.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134648.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_142701.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we joined a guided tour, the owner generously shared invaluable tips on how to grow tulips more effectively in our 
gardens. One key takeaway was to plant tulips in sandy soil with a high level of groundwater. On their farm, the groundwater 
sits just 65 cm below the surface, eliminating the need for additional watering as any excess is channelled into irrigation 
systems. We also learned the importance of rotating tulip bulbs to different spots each year to prevent bacterial and 
viral diseases that can develop around the bulbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also received a step-by-step explanation of the tulip cultivation process. De Tulperij is a bulb grower’s farm, unlike 
flower growers’ farms, meaning they don’t grow tulips year-round. In contrast, other farms cultivate tulips continuously 
in greenhouses. Remarkably, 80% of tulips produced in the Netherlands remain in the country, with only 20% being exported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tulip cycle at De Tulperij begins between October and December, when bulbs are planted and protected with hay. They 
require lower temperatures for a few months to bloom in spring, ideally around 9°C. As spring arrives and tulips start to 
emerge, the grower meticulously checks for viruses, removing any plants that look different, such as those lacking leaves 
or displaying a mosaic pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned that the timing of flower cutting, which typically occurs during the first two weeks of May, happened 2 weeks 
earlier this year. Cutting the flowers helps reduce insect activity around the tulips and ensures that energy is directed 
toward bulb development rather than seed production. After cutting, the bulbs remain in the ground for another 6-8 weeks 
until the leaves turn yellow. Then, the bulbs are harvested, cleaned by hand (process is called “peeling”), dried, and 
stored in a dark, ventilated place until the next planting season. Up to five small bulbs can be expected to grow out 
of the mother bulb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small part of the bulbs is still sold at auctions. Large bulbs destined for international markets are washed to eliminate 
any bacteria or fungi. The smaller bulbs are stored and replanted in the autumn, with bulblets taking two to three years 
to grow large enough to sell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De Tulperij farm has a new tulip color from 2001, orange, which is really rare and costs 30% more than red tulips. While 
red, yellow, and purple tulips are most prevalent, it takes, on average, 20 years to introduce a new variety to the market. 
These new varieties can emerge by chance through random mutations, as was the case with the orange tulip, or through 
intentional crossbreeding.
The orange tulip at De Tulperij was a lucky find, emerging from a random mutation. The growers carefully isolated the bulb, 
and when it bloomed the same vibrant color the following year, they knew they had something special. This permanent mutation 
marked the start of their efforts to cultivate and increase the number of these unique orange bulbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134800.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134734.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right next door to De Tulperij, there’s a neighbor with an impressive collection of 7,000 different tulip types, including 
virus-resistant varieties. Each new tulip variety receives a certificate from the Gene Bank, a testament to its uniqueness 
and identity.  From the beginning, tulips were named after famous personalities or breeders. The most famous one is 
“Semper Augustus,” named after Roman Emperor Augustus in the 16th. century.
One fun fact we learned from the farmer at De Tulperij was about the unique process of growing hyacinths. Unlike tulips, 
the cultivation of hyacinths involves a deliberate technique where farmers manually damage the bottom of the bulbs. This 
surprising method causes the bulbs to multiply rapidly, producing 20-30 new bulbs within just 2-3 months. Afterward, each 
new bulb is carefully separated by hand and then needs to grow for three years before it’s large enough to produce flower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last day was dedicated to visit famous Keukenhof that wes established in 1949 (exactly 75 years ago!). On the photo below you can see the former 
entrance to the park that is still one of the features of the park. The garden was initially opened to showcase the best 
flower bulbs the Dutch floricultural industry has to offer, and it has since become one of the largest and most well-known 
flower gardens in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_101110.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_101832.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_102448.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090529.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights of Keukenhof is its charming windmill, originally produced in Groningen in 1892 and donated by a 
cruise company. From the platform at the top of the windmill, you can usually admire breathtaking views of the colorful 
tulip fields at the peak of the season. However, during our visit, the surrounding fields had already been cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keukenhof’s main attraction is its focus on the 7 million spring-flowering bulbs, showcasing a living catalog for the 
100 participating companies. Over 500 flower growers present an impressive variety of cut flowers and pot plants at more 
than 20 flower shows. Early in the season, you can enjoy crocuses, daffodils, hyacinths, and early tulips in full bloom. 
As the season progresses, the garden transforms with larger tulips and other flowers making their appearance. Keukenhof 
is a must-visit destination for any flower enthusiast, providing a spectacular display of nature’s beauty. However, it’s 
worth noting that the park can get quite crowded, even on a Monday morning. While the experience is undoubtedly magical, 
it’s not something I would repeat annually due to the sheer volume of visitors. Nonetheless, Keukenhof remains a floral 
paradise that should be experienced at least once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090751.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08099.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08066.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/DSC08102.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.easyfiets.nl/en/&quot;&gt;Easy Fiets in Leiden&lt;/a&gt; Very friendly stuff, and we could give them back even after 
opening hours, but the bikes were quite small and cycling 50 km with these, was not idle. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/Screenshot 2024-05-02 223301.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tulipstore.eu/nl/service/tulip-store-showtuin/&quot;&gt;Tulip Store Showgarden&lt;/a&gt; is a tulip show garden with big fields with tulips that you can enter without 
a fee. Another spot with beautiful fields was next to Vernooij VOF, not a tulip farm but nice fields with easy access.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During our bike ride, we mostly followed the route outlined on &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/cxvXKUircv5tzJJw6?g_st=aw&quot;&gt;Flowermap.nl&lt;/a&gt; 
You can open it, and it will redirect you immediately to Google Maps, making it very easy to use. Then you can just follow 
the marks on the map. We skipped one loop that goes to the sea because the weather was unstable, and we still had to 
get back to Leiden. Our colleagues did this part, and they confirmed that the landscape changes dramatically, with 
the dunes looking stunning even in windy and stormy weather.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tulip Farm &lt;a href=&quot;https://detulperij.nl/&quot;&gt;De Tulperij&lt;/a&gt; in Voorhout - you can get a guided tour through the tulip fields (3 tours every day, English 
and Dutch). There is also flower greenhouse with a coffee, tea and a Dutch waffle, beautifully decorated. You can also 
buy many tulip and Delftware related souvenirs. During our visit, it was not possible to buy any bulbs but these can be
purchased online and shipped later to your home address. It’s incredible to see the dedication and time that goes into 
growing bulbs. If you ever find yourself near Keukenhof Gardens, a trip to De Tulperij is a must for any flower lover! 
The visit lasted almost one hour and included a 20-minute movie and free time for pictures in the fields that are normally 
not open to every visitor. On this farm, you can also see dahlias – beginning of August to beginning of October when farm is 
open for visitors again. Note that while everyone can see the tulip show garden, to take photos on the fields, you 
need to book guided tour.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_134831.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://keukenhof.nl/nl/&quot;&gt;Keukenhof&lt;/a&gt; is probably the most visited place in the Netherlands during the few 
weeks it’s open. The number of large tourist buses in the parking lots we passed on Saturday while cycling was astounding, 
not to mention the number of cars parked in various lots around the famous gardens. We were glad to have booked our ticket 
for Monday morning at 8:30 am. The only issue we encountered was that the parking lots were so empty in the morning that 
we weren’t sure where to go. We ended up driving to two different lots before someone finally directed us to the correct 
one, wasting almost 20 minutes. It seems the designated parking lot changes during the day, so if you arrive in the morning, 
definitely head to the main parking lot (coordinates: 52.268923, 4.551555). It’s also the same lot where you can rent a bike.
We approached Keukenhof from another direction, so look for temporary signs on the roundabout that indicate where to turn. 
The sign simply said “Keukenhof,” which was confusing. It would be more helpful if it included the word “open” and a 
parking pictogram as well.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until 11:00 am, the number of visitors in the park was reasonable. After that time, it started to get really crowded. 
We noticed more and more large groups, making it difficult to navigate some areas. Because we visited after the tulip 
fields had already been cut, it wasn’t worth rushing to the windmill first since the view wasn’t spectacular without 
the colorful fields. Instead, we recommend heading to the Historical Garden, which is great for selfies and, as we noticed 
later, a popular spot in the park. After visiting the park, we had a walk to city center of Lisse for a lunch
(less than 20min walk) and then came back to the car parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/TulipTrip/20240429_090553.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/05/Lisse-Netherlands/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2024/05/Lisse-Netherlands/</guid>
        
        <category>Netherlands</category>
        
        <category>Keukenhof</category>
        
        <category>cycling</category>
        
        <category>tulips</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weekend w Marsyli, najstarszym mieście Francji.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mały park z pozostałościami archeologicznymi obok Muzeum Historii Marsylii to miejsce, gdzie rozpoczęła się historia tego miasta. 
To właśnie tutaj, w tym konkretnym miejscu, pierwsi greccy osadnicy z Focji tchnęli życie w to miasto około 600 roku p.n.e., 
zakładając podwaliny pod to, co miało stać się tętniącym życiem portem Marsylii. Nadal można tam zobaczyć łódź w rzeczywistym 
rozmiarze, używaną przez Greków do żeglugi po wzburzonym Morzu Śródziemnym, aby dotrzeć do tej naturalnie spokojnej zatoki, 
doskonale chroniącej przed wiatrem i oferującej schronienie przybyszom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_112904.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niedaleko stąd, nowoczesny port tętni życiem. Widoczny z punktu widokowego “Mirador de Saint-Jean”, znajdującego się blisko 
fortyfikacji miasta, która prowadzi statki do wejścia do portu. Na końcu portu, nabrzeże Quai des Belges ożywa każdego poranka, 
gdy rybacy oferują tu swoje najświeższe połowy. W tym miejscu znajduje się również tablica upamiętniająca pierwszych przybyszów z Grecji.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103113.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103082.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103080.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103077.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dzielnica „Le Panier” znajdowała się w bezpośrednim sąsiedztwie naszego apartamentu, więc kilkakrotnie przechodziliśmy 
obok tego miejsca i zawsze gubiliśmy się w wąskich uliczkach, odkrywając nowe graffiti, kolorowe alejki i urocze butiki z 
mydłem marsylskim. W rzeczywistości oryginalne mydło marsylskie wygląda dość niepozornie, jest to po prostu duża kostka (300g) 
zielonkawego mydła o subtelnej woni. Jednakże tego właśnie potrzebuje twoja skóra, 72% oliwy z oliwek z pewnością 
odpowiednio ją nawilży oraz ukoi. Nie daj się zwieść wszystkim pięknym mydłom pełnym 
barwników, perfum czy syntetycznych dodatków. Oprócz uroczych małych sklepów, można w tej dzielnicy znaleźć rowniez małe galerie i 
interesujące kawiarnie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103093.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_125351.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103108.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_172204.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Przestrzeń przed Centrum Charytatywnym, opustoszała w listopadowym chłodzie, według naszego przewodnika, w miesiącach 
szczytu sezonu byłaby trudna do przejścia, gdy wszystkie restauracje i kawiarnie wystawiają tutaj swoje stoliki. Pod 
koniec jesieni, podobnie jak reszta dzielnicy La Panier, ten obszar pustoszeje, sklepy zamykają się a okolica ucicha, 
oczekując na wiosne po ktorej następi kilka pracowitych miesięcy. Jeszcze kilka lat temu można było w tej dzielnicy mieszkać, 
podpisując długoterminową umowę najmu, ale teraz większość domów jest oferowana tylko na Airbnb. Wynajem krótkoterminowy, nawet 
tylko pzrez kilka miesięcy, okazuje się znacznie bardziej opłacalny. Zauważyliśmy często na murach budynkow napis 
“Airbnb dehors”, co oznacza “precz z Airbnb”. Jasno podkreśla to, że lokalni mieszkańcy nie są zadowoleni ze zmian zachodzących 
w tej dzielnicy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103136.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103135.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ta wspaniała bazylika, Katedra La Major, została zbudowana w XIX wieku blisko fundamentów oryginalnego portu Marsylii. 
Kolory ścian są oszałamiające, szczególnie gdy podkreślone światłem zachodzącego słońca, które akcentuje różne kamienie 
żyte podczas budowy, która trwała ponad 40 lat. Nasz apartament znajdował się zaledwie kilkaset metrów od tej bazyliki, 
więc łatwo było nam do niej trafić, ponieważ 60-metrowa wieża bazyliki jest widoczna z wielu miejsc miasta. Okolica ta 
jest świetnym miejscem na wieczorny spacer podczas zachodu słońca, oferując piękne widoki na port, MUCEM i Cosquer Méditerranée 
tuż obok. Podłoga bazyliki zasługuje również na uwagę, gdyż ozdobiona jest wspaniałymi mozaikami.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_170032.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103065.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_130617.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gorąco polecamy wizytę na dachu Muzeum Cywilizacji Europy i Śródziemnomorza (MUCEM), do którego można dotrzeć przechodząc 
przez kładkę z Fortu św. Jana lub przez samo muzeum. Muzeum to ma fascynującą architekturę, przypomina z daleka ogromną 
gąbkę lub koralowce głębinowe. Będąc na dachu, który oferuje wolny dostęp, możesz rozkoszować się rozległymi widokami na 
miasto oraz port przez azurowe, zewnętrzne ściany budynku. To idealne miejsce na przerwę, aby podziwiać widoki! Kontrast 
między starożytnymi budowlami fortu a nowoczesnym muzeum jest widoczny, ale oba obiekty pięknie się uzupełniają. Kontynuując, 
eksplorowaliśmy wąskie ścieżki i ogrody na fortyfikacji miasta, odnajdując spokój i ciepło słońca w ustronnych zakątkach, 
gdzie nie docierał chłodny wiatr. Wiele punktów widokowych pozwoliło nam podziwiać zarówno Bazylikę Notre-Dame de la Garde, 
jak i Katedrę La Major. Obszar ten kryje wiele niespodzianek, znaleźliśmy tutaj urokliwy plac z fontanną, mural kobiety 
oraz mnóstwo roślin, które czynią to miejsce naprawdę wyjątkowym. Jest to miejsce warte odwiedzenia, jeśli szukasz ucieczki od 
zgiełku miasta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103117.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141649.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_135459.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103111.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bazylika Notre-Dame de la Garde, oferująca panoramiczny, 360-stopniowy widok na miasto, jest niewątpliwie miejscem, które 
koniecznie trzeba odwiedzić. Mimo że nie spędziliśmy wiele czasu wewnątrz kościoła, nie mogliśmy nie zauważyć fascynujących 
dekoracji, w tym statków zawieszonych na suficie, które podkreślają głębokie związki miasta z morzem. Koniecznie spójrz w 
górę – sufit zapiera dech w piersiach! Z zewnętrznego obszaru możesz podziwiać rozległą panoramę Marsylii, w tym nowy port 
dla statków wycieczkowych, położony w bardziej przemysłowej części miasta, która znajduje się kilka kilometrów od starego 
historycznego centrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141834.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_162108.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_161130.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103129.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Z tyłu kościoła roztacza się widok na Endoume, najbardziej prestiżową dzielnicę miasta, gdzie domy są ciasno zgrupowane, 
otoczone z jednej strony morzem a z drugiej górami. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103128.jpg&quot; /&gt;
Stadion Orange Velodrome i duże kompleksy mieszkalne zdecydowanie wyróżniały się wśród budynków po tej stronie miasta, 
z zapierającym dech w piersiach Parkiem Narodowym Calanques w tle, który był naszym celem na następny dzień.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103130.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kochamy naturę i wędrówki, więc zawsze staramy się łączyć krótkie wycieczki miejskie z przynajmniej jednym dniem spędzonym 
na łonie natury. Park Narodowy Calanques, położony między Marsylią a Cassis, był oczywistym wyborem po przejrzeniu mapy 
okolic miasta. Główne aktywności dostępne w tym parku narodowym to piesze wędrówki, wspinaczka skalna, pływanie i kajakarstwo. 
Ostre, białe klify i czysta woda u ich podnóża tworzą wspaniały widok, który można podziwiać wędrując szlakiem. “Calanque” 
to unikalny typ formacji geologicznej z wapienia znajdującej się wzdłuż wybrzeża Morza Śródziemnego. Pierwsze zdjęcie 
poniżej pokazuje główny punkt widokowy, Sugiton, który jest najbardziej dostępnym miejscem, znajdującym się około 2,5 km 
od przystanku autobusowego. Stamtąd można również zejść na plażę (dodatkowy 1 km) lub przedłużyć spacer o kilka-kilkanascie 
kilometrów w stronę Cassis, podążając głównym szlakiem GR. To była nasza decyzja i wcale tego nie żałowaliśmy! Ścieżka 
była bardzo kamienista i wymagająca, z wieloma stromymi i wąskimi odcinkami, ale fantastyczne widoki w pełni wynagrodziły 
wysiłek. Niestety, musieliśmy wrócić tą samą drogą, ponieważ nie byliśmy pewni, dokąd prowadzą inne ścieżki; Google Maps 
tym razem nie było zbyt pomocne, a poleganie wyłącznie na oznaczeniach na skałach nie wystarczało do nawigacji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113218.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113224.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113148.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113215.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_152147.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113195.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podczas naszego drugiego wieczoru odwiedziliśmy muzeum repliki Jaskini Cosquer (Villa Méditerranée), znajdujące się zaledwie 
kilkaset metrów od naszego apartamentu. W 1985 roku jaskinię odkrył Henri Cosquer, entuzjasta nurkowania, który znalazł jej
wejście prowadzące do ogromnej zatopionej galerii. Ten niemal 175-metrowy korytarz odsłonił prawdziwy skarb datowany na 
30 000 lat, zawierający ponad 480 dzieł, w tym malowidła i grawery przedstawiające pingwiny, jelenie, kozice, bizonów, 
jak również odciski dłoni i ślady ogniska. W tamtym czasie poziom morza był około 120 metrów niższy niż dzisiaj, a wody 
znajdowały się kilka kilometrów dalej. Jednak z powodu podnoszenia się poziomu morza to prehistoryczne miejsce jest zagrożone 
zatopieniem, niektóre malowidła są już częściowo poniżej poziomu wody. Pilne zatem stało się zachowanie oraz udostępnienie 
tego niesłychanego odkrycia światu. Obecnie jaskinia nie jest dostępna dla publiczności, a jej wejście zostało zamknięte 
dla jej ochrony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wynajęliśmy apartament na Airbnb w dzielnicy La Joliette, zaledwie kilka budynków od Katedry Marsylskiej, znajdujący 
się na 6. piętrze bez windy. Zauwazylismy wiele podobnych ofert wynajmu. To może nie być najlepsze rozwiązanie dla osób z dużą 
ilością bagażu lub dla rodzin z dziećmi. Kiedy ruch morski przekroczył pojemność Starego Portu, założono nowy, a nasz 
apartament znajdował się tuż przy wejściu do tego ogromnego portu. Dworzec kolejowy ‘Saint-Charles’ jest w odległości 
15-20 minut spacerem, więc nawet nie rozważaliśmy korzystania z transportu publicznego.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wycieczka z przewodnikiem &lt;a href=&quot;https://marseillefreewalkingtour.com/&quot;&gt;Marseille Free Walking Tour&lt;/a&gt; trwala ok 2.5 godziny i bardzo polecamy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delicious patisserie La Pâtisserie des Marseillais &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lapatisseriedesmarseillais.fr/&quot;&gt;Pascal Guglielmi&lt;/a&gt; zdecydowanie warta odwiedzenia!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Autobus numer 60, od przystanku Capitainerie do Bazyliki Notre-Dame de la Garde, oferuje prawie 20-minutową jazdę. 
Wstęp do kościoła jest bezpłatny. Spędziliśmy tylko około 15 minut w okolicy kościoła z powodu silnego, zimnego wiatru, 
a następnie wróciliśmy tym samym biletem, który był ważny przez 1 godzinę. Gdy ponownie wsiedliśmy do autobusu, 
zeskanowaliśmy nasz bilet, ale nie został on obciążony, i mogliśmy z niego skorzystać następnego dnia w metrze. Każdy 
zakupiony przez nas bilet był ważny na 2 przejazdy, ale maszyna oferuje wiele opcji przy wyborze liczby przejazdów. 
Dla osób z dziećmi świetną opcją jest skorzystanie z małego pociągu ze Starego Portu (znajdującego się naprzeciwko 
ratusza w Marsylii), który podjeżdża pod samą bazylikę!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Korzystając z linii metra 2 z Joliette do Castellane, a następnie z autobusu B1, po 30-40 minut jazdy w kierunku 
Campus de Luminy, dotarliśmy do przystanku Luminy – PN des Calanques. Nasza wędrówka po Parku Narodowym Calanques, 
około 16 km, trwała 5-6 godzin z przerwami. Na poniższej mapie, która pokazuje naszą trasę, widoczna jest małą odnogą 
wskazującą punkt widokowy Belvédère de Sugiton, popularne miejsce wśród wielu odwiedzających. Jest łatwo dostępny, 
gdyż widzieliśmy ludzi z psami i niemowlakami w wózkach, jednak solidne koła będą niezbędne. Teren jest bardzo skalisty, 
więc noszenie butów trekkingowych jest zdecydowanie zalecane. Należy uważnie patrzeć na oznaczenia szlaku, ponieważ kilka 
razy przypadkowo zaczęliśmy wspinać się na skały niebędące częścią szlaku (oznaczenia szlaku nie zawsze były jasne i 
wiele z nich było uszkodzonych). Pogoda była niesamowita, piękny słoneczny dzień w listopadzie z przyjemnymi temperaturami. 
Jednak dalej musieliśmy wziąć pod uwagę wczesny zachód słońca o tej porze roku, aby uniknąć problemów, ponieważ nie 
mieliśmy czołówek.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 210407.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 214111.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113202.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113217.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replika Jaskini &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grotte-cosquer.com/en/homepage/&quot;&gt;The Cosquer Cave&lt;/a&gt; w Villa Méditerranée oferuje zwiedzanie 
tego miejsca słuchając audioprzewodnika w języku angielskim podczas 35-minutowej przejażdżki łodzią, podczas której 
zwiedzający mają możliwość odkrycia ponad 400 dzieł na ścianach jaskini. Następnie, w amfiteatrze pokazywany jest 
film dokumentalny opowiadający o odkryciu jaskini przez Henri’ego Cosquer. Niestety, film jest po francusku, a angielskie 
napisy na małych telewizorach obok dużego ekranu, bardzo utrudniają jednoczesne oglądanie filmu i czytanie tekstu na 
innych ekranach. Kolejne rozczarowanie czekało na nas w następnym pomieszczeniu, gdzie krótkie filmy przedstawiały krok 
po kroku tworzenie repliki jaskini, bez napisów w języku angielskim. Ponadto, prezentujący wyjaśniał techniki używane 
do replikowania oryginalnej jaskini, ale ponownie, tylko po francusku. Dlatego czuliśmy, że nie mogliśmy w pełni 
doświadczyć potencjału muzeum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2023/12/Marsylia-Francja/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2023/12/Marsylia-Francja/</guid>
        
        <category>Francja</category>
        
        <category>Marsylia</category>
        
        <category>Calanques</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weekend in Marseille: Exploring the Oldest City of France</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The small park with archaeological remains next to the Marseille History Museum is the place where the story of Marseille began. 
It was here, in this very spot, that the first Greek settlers from Phocaea breathed life into the city around 600 BC, 
laying down the roots of what would become the bustling port of Marseille. You can still see the 
real-size boat used by Greeks to sail on rough Mediterranean Sea to get to this naturally tranquil bay, offering 
excellent protection from the wind and providing shelter to outlanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_112904.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a stone’s throw away, the modern port buzzes with activity, visible from the “Mirador de Saint-Jean,” viewpoint close to 
city fortification that is guiding ships to the entrance of the port. 
At the port’s end, the Quai des Belges comes alive each morning as fishermen hawk their freshest catch. Here also stands 
a memorial honoring those first adventurous Greek settlers, commemorating their foundational role in the city’s history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103113.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103082.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103080.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103077.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The district of ‘Le Panier’ was in direct neighborhood to our apartment, so we found ourselves wandering through this area a few times,  always 
getting lost in the narrow streets, while discovering some new graffiti, colorful alleys and charming boutiques with Marseille soap. Actually 
the original Marseille soap looks very boring, just large cube (300g) of greenish soap that has subtle scent. However, this is exactly
what your skin needs, 72% of olive oil will definitely moisturize your skin properly and a true panacea for the skin. Don’t be 
attracted by all beautiful soaps
full of colouring, perfume or synthetic additives. Besides cute little shops, you can also find here small galleries and 
interesting cafés.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103093.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_125351.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103108.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_172204.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Old Charity Center’s forecourt, deserted in the chill of November, our guide assured us, would be difficult to pass 
during high season months when all restaurants and cafés put their tables out here. In late autumn, much like the rest of the Le Panier district, this area empties out, with shops closing and the neighborhood 
quieting down, awaiting the vibrancy of spring and several busy months to follow. A few years ago, it was still possible 
to live there, signing a long-term lease, but now the majority of homes are listed on Airbnb. Short-term rentals, even 
just for a few months, prove to be far more profitable than renting to permanent city residents. We noticed often “Airbnb 
dehors” spray-painted on the walls, which translates to “Airbnb go away”. A clear statement by locals who cherish 
living here, but find it less and less affordable to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103136.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103135.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This magnificent basilica, the Cathedral of La Major, was built in the 19th century near the foundation of the original 
Marseille port. The colors of the walls were stunning, especially when highlighted by the sunset light that accentuated 
the different stones used in the construction, which lasted more than 40 years to complete.
Our apartment was just a few hundred meters from this basilica, so we never got lost as its 60-meter-high tower was very 
easy to spot. The surrounding area is a great place for an evening walk during the sunset, offering lovely views of the 
port, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mucem.org/&quot;&gt;MUCEM&lt;/a&gt;, and Cosquer Méditerranée just next to it. The floor of the basilica is adorned with magnificent mosaics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_170032.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103065.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_130617.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We highly recommend visiting the rooftop of the Museum of Civilizations of Europe and the Mediterranean (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mucem.org/&quot;&gt;MUCEM&lt;/a&gt;), which 
you can reach via a catwalk from Fort St. Jean or through the museum itself. This museum has fascinating architecture, 
resembling a huge sponge or deep-water corals from a distance. Once on the rooftop, which offers free access, you can 
soak in the expansive views of the city, harbor, and fort through the intricate outer metal walls. It’s the perfect spot 
for a break to enjoy the views! This contrast between the fort’s old buildings and the modern museum complements each 
other beautifully. As we continued, we explored the narrow paths and gardens, finding the tranquility and warmth of 
the sun in secluded corners where the wind couldn’t reach us. Multiple viewpoints allowed us to admire both the Basilica 
of Notre-Dame de la Garde and the Cathedral of la Major. Our exploration was full of surprises, from hidden squares with 
fountains to murals of women and an abundance of plants that made this place truly unique. It’s a must-visit if you’re 
looking to escape the city’s bustle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103117.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141649.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_135459.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103111.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Basilica of Notre-Dame de la Garde, offering a 360-degree view of the city, is undoubtedly a must-visit destination. 
Although we didn’t spend much time inside the church, we couldn’t help but notice the fascinating decorations, including 
ships suspended from the ceiling, which emphasize the city’s deep connection to the sea. Make sure to look up—the ceiling 
is breathtaking! From the outdoor area, you can take in the extensive panorama of Marseille, including the new cruise port 
situated in a more industrial part of the city, which lies beyond walking distance from the old historic center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_141834.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_162108.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231110_161130.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103129.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the back side of the church, the view opens up to Endoume, the city’s most prestigious neighborhood, where houses are 
densely nestled together, surrounded by the sea and mountains&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103128.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Orange Velodrome Stadium and big apartment complexes were definitely standing out among the buildings on this side of 
the city with the stunning Calanques National Park in the backdrop, our destination the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB103130.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We love nature and hiking, so we always try to combine short city trips with at least one day spent in nature. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.calanques-parcnational.fr/en&quot;&gt;Calanques 
National Park&lt;/a&gt;, located between Marseille and Cassis, was the obvious choice after examining the map of the city’s surroundings. 
Hiking, rock climbing, swimming, and canoeing are the primary activities available in this national park. The sharp, white 
cliffs and the clear waters at their base create a magnificent view that you can enjoy along the hiking path. A ‘calanque’ 
is a unique type of geological formation made of limestone found along the Mediterranean coast. The first photo below shows 
the main viewpoint, Sugiton, which is the most accessible one at approximately 2.5 km from the bus stop. From here, you can 
also descend to the beach (about an extra 1 km) or extend your walk by several more kilometers toward Cassis, following the 
main GR trail. That was our choice, and we didn’t regret it at all! The path was very rocky and demanding, with many steep 
and narrow parts, but the fabulous views were well worth the effort. Unfortunately, we had to retrace our steps because we 
were unsure of where the other paths led; Google Maps wasn’t very helpful this time, and relying solely on the markers on 
the rocks wasn’t sufficient for navigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113218.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113224.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113148.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113215.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/20231111_152147.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113195.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our second evening, we spent time at the Cosquer Cave replica museum, located just a few hundred meters from our apartment. 
In 1985, the cave was discovered by Henri Cosquer, a diving enthusiast, who found the entrance leading to an immense submerged 
gallery. This nearly 175-meter-long passage unveiled a real treasure dating back 30,000 years, featuring over 480 
pieces including paintings and engravings of penguins, deer, ibex, bison, as well as hand prints and traces of a fireplace. 
At that time, the sea level was about 120 meters lower than it is today, and the shoreline was several kilometers 
distant. However, due to rising sea levels, this prehistoric site is at risk of vanishing, with some artworks already 
partially submerged. The urgency to preserve and share this unparalleled discovery with the world has become urgent. 
Currently, the cave is not accessible to the public, and its entrance has been sealed for its protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We rented an apartment on Airbnb in the La Joliette neighborhood, just a few buildings away from Marseille Cathedral, 
located on the 6th floor without an elevator. There were many similar rental offers. This might not be the best solution 
for people with a lot of luggage or those with children. When maritime traffic exceeded the capacity of the Old Port, 
a new one was established, and our apartment was situated right at the entrance to this vast port. The ‘Saint-Charles’ 
train station is within a 15-20 minute walk, so we didn’t even consider using public transportation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guided tour &lt;a href=&quot;https://marseillefreewalkingtour.com/&quot;&gt;Marseille Free Walking Tour&lt;/a&gt; for about 2.5hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delicious patisserie La Pâtisserie des Marseillais &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lapatisseriedesmarseillais.fr/&quot;&gt;Pascal Guglielmi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bus number 60, from the Capitainerie bus stop to the Basilica of Notre-Dame de la Garde, offers an almost 20-minute ride. There is no entrance fee for the church. We only spent about 15 minutes in the area around the church due to the strong winds 
and cold weather, and we returned using the same ticket, which was valid for 1 hour.
When we boarded the bus again, we scanned our ticket, but it wasn’t charged, and we were able to use it the next day for the metro. 
Each ticket we bought was valid for 2 rides, but the machine offers multiple options when selecting the number of rides. For 
those with children, taking the small train from the old port (located directly across from the city hall in Marseille) 
is a great option!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take Metro line 2 from Joliette to Castellane, and then catch bus B1 for a 30-40 minute ride in the direction of Campus de 
Luminy, getting off at the Luminy – PN des Calanques stop. Our hike in the Calanques National Park covered approximately 
16 km (5-6 hours including breaks). On the map below, which highlights our route, you’ll notice a small branch indicating 
the Belvédère de Sugiton viewpoint, a popular destination for many visitors. It’s quite accessible; we saw people with prams, 
but sturdy wheels are essential. The area is very rocky, so wearing good trail running or hiking shoes is crucial for safety. 
Be vigilant for trail markers, as we accidentally started climbing rocks not part of the trail a few times (the trail markers 
are not always clear, and many have been damaged). We were fortunate to have amazing weather, a beautiful sunny day in November 
with pleasant temperatures. However, we had to be mindful of the early sunset at this time of year to avoid any problems, 
since we did not have headlights&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 210407.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/Screenshot 2024-01-25 214111.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113202.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/France/Marseille/PB113217.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The replica of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grotte-cosquer.com/en/homepage/&quot;&gt;The Cosquer Cave&lt;/a&gt; in Villa Méditerranée offers an 
engaging audio guide in English for a 35-minute boat 
ride, during which visitors can explore over 400 works on the cave’s walls. Afterwards, there’s a documentary film in 
an amphitheater that chronicles the cave’s discovery by Henri Cosquer. Unfortunately, the film is in French, and English 
subtitles are provided on small TVs adjacent to the big screen, making it challenging to watch the film and read the text 
on the other screens simultaneously. Another disappointment awaited us in the next room, where short films depicted the 
step-by-step creation of the cave’s replica without any English subtitles. Additionally, a presenter explained the 
techniques used to replicate the original cave, but once again, only in French. This was similar to the rest of the 
text displayed on the gallery walls. Therefore, we felt as though we couldn’t fully experience what the museum is offering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/12/Marseille-France/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2023/12/Marseille-France/</guid>
        
        <category>France</category>
        
        <category>Marseille</category>
        
        <category>Calanques</category>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
