<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Going beyond the known</title>
    <description>A travel blog by Monika Suchoszek.</description>
    <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 21:26:14 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 21:26:14 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tips to make travelling with the baby or toddler easier</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We had to change our way of travelling and adjust to the needs of our little one. People always say that you can keep travelling
even after you became a parent. Yes, it’s true, you can … but it will not be the same! Our holidays now are less intense, we are visiting
kids-friendly places where we can have realistic chances to relax and have a break. A bored, tired or frustrated toddler will 
not allow you to do so! We are travelling on regular basis from Belgium to Poland to visit my family. The first time we went 
to Poland when our daughter was 3 months old. We also managed to go twice for holidays in Europe: to Lisbon (at 6 months 
old) and Malaga (at 14 months). Both trips were very different because of the baby’s age, but also because we have 
learned a lot during the first trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are our tips for the flight itself?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take in consideration the time of the flight and if it will fit with yours baby daily routine. E.g. we don’t book flights
with departures time before 10am or after 4pm (which limits our options considerably!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always travel with the buggy and baby carrier (we switch to the carrier while boarding the plane). Do note that
even though you are allowed to take the carrier up to the plane, you are required to get a label for it before going 
through security from the check-in desk. In theory, you are allowed
to take 1 small bag when you buy infant ticket (under age of 2) but we always had a small additional cotton bag with all the 
little one’s food and drinks, no one ever complained (in case there would be an issue, all things would comfortably
fit in our luggage). In general, the less luggage you have the better. We have standard carry-on bags when 
traveling for a week (1 small backpack per person) and it’s really enough! Once you reach your destination, it’s time to 
find your buggy. Every airport have them in a different spot, usually together with oversized luggage but never next 
to the plane. This is why having a carrier can be extremely helpful as sometimes it’s a really long walk from the plane 
to the baggage reclaim. It’s also useful to have small blanket to cover the baby while boarding the plane, sometimes it’s very 
windy, and you never know how long you’ll have to queue outside to get into the plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take enough water and snacks for your baby. According to TSA (Transportation Security Administration), there are no 
restrictions of liquids when you travel with 
kid under age of 12. Water is allowed in reasonable quantities. We usually have a 1 L bottle of water, an extra sippy cup 
already filled with water, soy milk in cardboard (250 mL), and 2-3 jars of baby food. As well some sandwiches, fruits and
veggies. This might look like a lot, but it is good to have some extras in case of emergency (unexpected delays or 
flight cancellation). Keeping the water and food in a separate cotton bag, is convenient as you’ll need to show all baby 
liquids at the security. If your baby is still on breast or formula, it’s good to give the milk during takeoff and 
landing. Apparently, babies can’t pop their ears intentionally, but we can help them by encouraging them to swallow. 
Flight attendant will provide some hot water to make your formula upon request. If you are breastfeeding, a big scarf 
and special bra will be helpful to give you some privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also helps to have a new small toy for your baby, they will have a better mood and hopefully will be occupied with the
new gift for quite some time :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are specific hints about the airports we’ve used so far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zaventem, Belgium - amazing playing area for kids next to the food corner (entrance next to the Starbucks). There is 
a microwave, high chairs, changing stations, big table for parents to sit, perfect place to wait for the flight! Going 
through securing was easy with the baby, all baby food and water was checked so better keep it in a separate bag for easy 
access.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pyrzowice, Poland - we didn’t find any playing area for toddlers, there are changing rooms. Security here is
inefficient and needlessly long. E.g. this is one of the few airports where they require shoes to be taken off and scanned. 
Expect long queues without a no priority line for families with kids.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lisbon, Portugal - there is a single special land for security checks for elderly, people in wheelchair and parents with 
babies, but be aware that it could take even longer than going by regular line as all the “slower people” will be 
in the special queue! They discourage this because there are a few steps down to get to the regular security check, 
which shouldn’t be an issue when travelling with a buggy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eindhoven, The Netherlands - it’s the best airport for parents with babies when it comes to the security checks. 
The staff ensures parents with kids can move through security swiftly, and their modern scanners allow you to keep 
most things inside your backpacks/suitcases. They just check all baby food and water afterwards in the special machine.
It is always for us very nice experience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Malaga (AGP), Spain - There was enough space to comfortably sit at the airport but the playing area we found was 
very small and closed off for unknown reasons. Going through security was a pleasant experience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the important criteria when looking for accommodation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Airbnb is our favourite platform when travelling. When we went for you first trip to Lisbon, we thought that having an 
apartment in the city center will give us flexibility.
We could come back to the apartment, it will be close to the shops and restaurants. BUT, we didn’t predict that houses in 
the old part of the city have paper thin walls. It was so laud that we couldn’t sleep and our baby had even more problems with 
sleep. It also happened few time around midnight and early morning that people were discarding glass bottles outside, waking up
everyone in the neighborhood. Next time, we checked the reviews of the apartments carefully, looking for any clues about 
the noise level. Our apartment in Benalmadena was much better! It had bigger bedroom that even with extra travel cot had enough space 
to be comfortably used. This time we also stayed in quiet area next to the park (with animals and playground), the beach and 
bus stops (this time we also relied on public transportation). Dark curtains to make the apartment dark for our baby nap, 
was another useful feature of the apartment. A small kitchen for making breakfasts and snacks is always a must for us. 
A bigger shower helped us a lot when it comes to the evening baths, especially after playing on the beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arrived at your destination? What to do next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It always makes sense to search in advance for playgrounds in the areas that you are going to visit. Sometimes they can 
be really nice, perfect for a break with a toddler. Once babies start to walk, it becomes impossible to keep them long
in their stroller, they need to run and explore :D It’s useful to have a small blanket or sport towel to use in the parks 
for a break. Even if your baby is very small, it’s good for them to have a break for tummy time or play with their toys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As public toilets with changing stations are rare, having a changing mat is a must. The waterproof layer can
also come in handy as an extra layer while sitting on grass. Keep in mind that even in some restaurants toilets can
be very small and lack a changing station, in those cases you’ll also be happy you have your own mat with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Lisbon, all tourists attractions had a separate line for families, so we didn’t have to wait much at all. Also in the shops, people 
were letting us ahead, even if we didn’t ask them for this and that was really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20220221_163710.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20220215_153807.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We travel with both a buggy and baby carrier. It gives us the flexibility needed for visiting different kind of places. 
For example, it would not be possible to visits city center of Lisbon, Moorish Castle in Portugal or Calamorro Mountain 
in Spain with the buggy. On the other hand a buggy comes handy for long walks along the see or while visiting some sites like the
Jerónimos Monastery in Lisbon (which is perfectly suited for a buggy). The easiest way to make a decision 
“buggy or carrier?” is to check the reviews on the trip advisor or on Google and look for any that describes how kids-friendly a particular tourist attraction is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dreambaby.be/e/fr/db/dreambee-essentials-poussette-canne-grey-melange-214187?utm_source=google&amp;amp;utm_medium=shopping&amp;amp;s_kwcid=AL!6321!3!!!!x!!&amp;amp;gclid=CjwKCAiAheacBhB8EiwAItVO2yQ7N_C6VWkn4sxHW_TIX8rNzywIH3wWZIyx8EqOYPPCespcWfD0HxoCK10QAvD_BwE&quot;&gt;Buggy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com.be/-/en/BABYBJ%C3%96RN-Carrier-Black-Cotton-White/dp/B07KPSS456/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2Q7TKLKF68UZ8&amp;amp;keywords=BabyBj%C3%B6rn+carrier+one&amp;amp;qid=1671045227&amp;amp;sprefix=babybj%C3%B6rn+carrier+one%2Caps%2C60&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Baby Bjorn carrier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nanabeebi.com/en/products/luiertas-rugzak&quot;&gt;Nanabeebi backpack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2022 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/12/Travelling-toddler-tips/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/12/Travelling-toddler-tips/</guid>
        
        <category>plane</category>
        
        <category>toddler</category>
        
        <category>baby</category>
        
        <category>Malaga</category>
        
        <category>Lisbon</category>
        
        <category>Portugal</category>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our top 3 half-day trips from Benalmadena </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Malaga, and Benalmadena specifically, are nice places as a home-base for doing small trips in this part of Andalusia. We had 
three days, and we decided to spend each of the afternoons exploring another destination. You can easily do everything 
in half the time, but we didn’t want to rush with the baby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mijas-village&quot;&gt;Mijas Village&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first (and the best!) destination was Mijas village. Beautiful,
small village on the slopes of the mountain, white houses decorated with flowers in blue pots. Many shops with leather 
goods, nougat, spices, honey and other delicatessen produced locally. Amazing view of the coast and the mountains!
Definitely check Parque La Muralla with church Iglesia Inmaculada Concepción and amazing views of the mountains and Alboran 
Sea. I would highly recommend to get lost in the narrow streets of this cute village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_164928.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_165256.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_162249.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_173539.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_173301.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_160725.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_162008.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_160657.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_160454.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_161834.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_152929.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-colomares-monument-butterfly-park-and-stupa&quot;&gt;The Colomares Monument, Butterfly park and Stupa&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our second destination, the Colomares Monument is a castle-style monument honoring Christopher Columbus and his discovery of the new world, America. 
This monument was built between 1987 and 1994 by Esteban Martin Martin and his two co-workers. A great place to take some interesting pictures! 
It’s not big, but it feels intense because of the number of ornaments.  It is a mix of many architectural styles and materials: brick, 
stone and cement. One part of the monument resembles of the stern from La Santa Maria, the largest of the three Spanish 
ships used by Christopher Columbus in his first voyage across the Atlantic Ocean in 1492.  You can love it or hate it. 
We had vastly different opinions, so check it yourself in what camp you’ll fall!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154146.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154729.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154519.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_154713.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_160055.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a 30-minute walk along the main road, we reached the Butterfly Park and Stupa of Enlightenment. At the entrance you will receive
a small list of different butterfly species with names and photos to see if you can spot all of them. This place looks 
like a big greenhouse, very hot and humid with a lot of plants, not unlike being in a tropical forest.
The most spectacular species we spotted were &lt;em&gt;Greta Oto&lt;/em&gt;, a butterfly with transparent wings, the bright blue 
&lt;em&gt;Morpho pheleides&lt;/em&gt; and the black &lt;em&gt;Parides iphidamas&lt;/em&gt; with its big red dots on the wings. Besides the butterflies, you 
can see their small wallaby and very colorful, rainbow finches, both native to Australia. It’s a great place for older 
kids. Young toddlers can have difficulties to spot the butterflies and if they do, you need to be careful and not let 
them damaged the fragile butterflies as some do get very close to visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_164017.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_164638.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_165254.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_170245.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_164147.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_174647.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;el-calamorro-monte&quot;&gt;El Calamorro Monte&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El Calamorro Monte, panoramic view of Benalmadena. It has several access points, but we decided to take the Benalmádena Cable Car, 
which runs along its slope from Arroyo de la Miel (next to the old Tivoli amusement park) to the very top of the mountain 
(approximately 780 metres above the see level). There are a few beautiful view points and a show featuring birds of prey at the top.
You can also start hiking from there in various directions or even cycle downhill (you can take your bike by cable car, 
though you might need to detach a wheel to get it in the cabin). We were too late for last show with birds of prey 
(3:00 pm) but we enjoyed a small tour around the peak, remember to take some extra clothes, with wind and clouds 
accumulating around the peak, it can get chilly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_151532.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_154359.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_160116.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_160633.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_163236.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_161609.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Playground, Patio de Juegos, next to Parque La Muralla in Mijas. We spend there a lot of time, this amazing playground has
attractions for each age group. Our one-year-old baby loved it and it not so easy to find a playground that suits her age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221114_164100.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.castillomonumentocolomares.com/&quot;&gt;Castillo Colomares&lt;/a&gt;  - entry 3 euro per adult, 2 euro for seniors and kids&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Butterfly Park - we bought tickets online, 8.50 euro per adult, seniors 7.50 euro. The online ticket system was a 
little strange. After paying, you should get a code via mail that can be redeemed for the tickets at the reception… We never got that mail though.
As for the tickets with PayPal fortunately the order ID was also included in the PayPal order confirmation. You need to buy tickets at 
least one hour before the visit. More on the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mariposariodebenalmadena.com/en/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Benalmadena cable car - tickets bought on spot, 16.90 euro per adult, seniors 12.90 euro&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can check how to travel by bus by reading practical info section of my related &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2022/10/Benalmadena-Spain/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;
It took us 40 min from Benalmadena to Mijas (Butterfly park was half-way to Mijas) by line 121, 126&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/11/Benalmadena-trips/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/11/Benalmadena-trips/</guid>
        
        <category>Mijas</category>
        
        <category>Benalmadena</category>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Colomares</category>
        
        <category>Monument</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Banalmadena, perfect autumn destination for a sunny holiday!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After planning all our trips to Poland for the remaining of the year, we still had approximately a week of holidays left,
so we decided to find some nice, warm place to visit in Europe. After checking all possible flight connections 
from the nearest airport, we decided to go for the warmest option, the south of Spain. Our destination, Benalmadena, had 
everything we needed: easy connection by train from the airport, beach, mountains, many shops and restaurants, 
few tourist attractions nearby and plenty of options for the nice accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This city is located approximately 20 km from Malaga where you can get easily by the same train that goes to the airport. 
We were pleasantly surprise by the weather, it was more than 20°C with no rain, and it was the beginning of November! There 
was no need to rent a car since train connection was so convenient. I had a list of places to visit prepared in 
advance, and we actually managed to see all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day we spent on exploring the city, doing some shopping and buying bus card that would allow us to travel cheaper, 
more information in the section at the end of the post. We particularly liked the marina that surprised us by very 
original shape and style of the buildings. There are plenty of shops and restaurants. In the evening the main promenade turned into small
market with (fake?) shoes, clothes or purses of well known designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221113_093340.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_172138.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_171721.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_173429.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_174142.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_173641.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parque de la Paloma, full of green parrots, rabbits, ducks, seagulls and dogs was our favourite destination in the
early mornings when our daughter was full of energy and couldn’t stay any longer in the apartment. The entrance 
to the park was just in front of our hotel. We were going to the playgrounds, the succulent garden or just watching green 
parrots, fooling around. Can you see them on the last photo? They were perfectly matching the color of the grass :)
The park was very clean and well-maintained, turning into huge picnic area during the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_091520.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_092653.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_093145.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_093201.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_092936.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_100804.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During next the days, we were checking nearby tourist attractions, going everywhere by bus. There is a separate post
describing these small trips &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2022/11/Benalmadena-trips/&quot;&gt;around Benalmadena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent last day of our holidays on wandering in Malaga; the city where Pablo Picasso was born. Our main goal was visiting Alcazaba,
Moorish fortress with city view. On the way there, we stopped by the main cathedral in the city (Catedral de la Encarnación 
de Málaga) though we didn’t check the church inside. Once we noticed soon after an ancient Roman theater, we knew it’s already Alcazaba.
Firstly, we were not sure if it’s possible to even visit this place with the buggy but there was a sign pointing to the back entrance where you can take a  lift,
so we gave it a try. Once up there, the areas you can easily access with a buggy (or for visitors in a wheelchair) are limited. 
While the stairs were not huge, and could be taken with a buggy, repeating this over and over however made 
our walk down challenging. As our pram is light, we were able to fold it and carried it down with us while our daughter was walking, 
avoiding the trip back down with the elevator, but we would not recommend visiting the castle if
your baby can’t walk unless you take a carrier instead of a buggy. While I was walking amongst narrow streets of the 
old part of Malaga during Laura’s nap, Sebastian visited the Picasso Museum. Even in November, it was crowded inside (mostly 
because of the school trips). Downtown Malaga would be nice for shopping, eating some local specialties, but didn’t make much of an impression on us. 
The city was already decorated with Christmas lights and many poinsettia, but we can’t tell how it looked at
night since we left before it got dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_104452.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_103845.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_104558.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_113539.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_113827.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_114324.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_114023.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_142240.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_143907.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221116_150056.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The airport has perfect connection with Malaga and nearby cities on the coast by train. Buying tickets was very easy,
someone from the train service told us to use one debet card and scan once for each person and then again while leaving 
the train station. Our card was charged exactly the price for signe ticket, 2.05 euro per person (20min ride). 
Train C1 Benalmádena-Arroyo de la Miel in Malaga (walking distance from to the old part of the city), 30min ride, 2.70 euro
More info about trains on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.malagaweb.com/transport/commuter-train-malaga.php&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We stayed at BenalBeach hotel, huge complex where many apartments were owned by private people and available on 
booking.com. We noticed that these apartment were renovated and had better reviews than ones still owned by the hotel.
There was a big garden in the middle part of the hotel complex and it was possible to walk through the garden to the gate 
leading directly to the beach (not accessible for the buggy). Huge amount of plants, water running in between and lights in
the evening surprised as a lot! You could feel like in the jungle, although the highest plants were really dusty.
Despite the fact that we were in the middle of the city, it was very quiet and nice area, next to the beach, many 
restaurants and most importantly, just next to the only big park in the city center, Parque de la Paloma. I can only imagine
how crowded it can get on the beach or in the city during summer since there are many huge hotels, often 10
floors high. We felt like our hotel was mostly empty and every restaurant was trying to get our attention since not so many
tourists were walking around.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_140608.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221111_175542.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Playground
 Pocoyo Parque de Juegos, next to the bus stop Rotonda García Lorca - great for toddlers 1-3 years, crowded in the afternoons&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Buses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheapest and most convenient way of travelling by bus is by buying green bus card in Tobacco shops. You will pay 1.80 euro
as card deposit (you will get the cash back while returning the card). Then you need to charge the card with the amount
of money you wish, minimum 5 euro. Remember, money left on the card will not be paid back but you can charge your card 
again. For example, it is 0.79 euro per ride to Mijas, Butterfly Park and any other closer bus stop (ticket directly from 
the driver is 1.60 euro). This card can be used by the group of people, you just need to tell the driver how many people 
enter the bus, and he will print the number of tickets accordingly (each ticket notes the amount of money left to use). 
Note that this card gives discounts only for bus tickets
(not trains). In front of our hotel, there were taxis parked with predefined prices, see photo below. We couldn’t figure 
out what was the departure time of the bus based on the information from the bus schedule on the bus stop. The QR code 
listed on the board was extremely useful, immediately redirecting you the website with departure time of all buses from
particulat bus stop, including delays in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221112_090914.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spain/Malaga/20221115_085802.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Museo Casa Natal de Picasso, more than 200 works donated by the members of Picasso’s family (including really early work).
Don’t expect the most famous works, but a nice overview of how he grew into the artist we all know.
Audio guide included in the ticket price, only listening to details on works that appeal to you, you can see everything 
in less than an hour. If you listen to more details it can take much longer. No entrance to the museum with any food or drinks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/10/Benalmadena-Spain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2022/10/Benalmadena-Spain/</guid>
        
        <category>Malaga</category>
        
        <category>Benalmadena</category>
        
        <category>Spain</category>
        
        <category>Colomares</category>
        
        <category>Monument</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Camping in the Ardennes, visiting caves and trekking around beautiful lakes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dinant, birthplace of saxophone inventor Adolphe Sax was our first destination on the way to the Ardennes. After a nice 20min walk
along the riverside from the car parking, we had reached the center of the city with the famous Citadel above our heads on the 
truly imposing rock. It is worth to walk first to the other side of the Meuse river over the Charles-de-Gaulle Bridge to have a look 
at catholic church Notre Dame de Dinant, which is located at the foot of the Citadel, from a different perspective. There are many colorful saxophones on the 
bridge, each represents different country through its unique colors and patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_115550_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_120603_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After purchasing tickets in the office
and climbing 408 stairs, we reached the top of the Citadel to enjoy beautiful view of the surroundings. There are 14 different
exposition rooms to visit but the view was the most impressive for us as we found the exhibitions not very modern and interesting.
The cable car can take you to the top within 2 minutes but walking on the stairs gives you a chance to see the view from few different
levels, each giving you unique perspective of the city and the river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_120555_edit.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_130253_edit.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_132406_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_132652_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_134553_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we left the Citadel, we passed a restaurant, graveyard and car parking where we turned right and followed hiking path, going 
all the way down to the city center, see map of our walk below. The path was mostly in the forest with one viewpoint of the city 
and river but the Citadel was almost not visible from there (photo of the city and river below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_134812_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_140313_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/Screenshot from 2021-09-05 14-22-00.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the afternoon, we planned walk starting next to Vêves Castle (9km from Dinant by car), which can be visited on weekends but as we 
were there on a Friday we couldn’t get a closer look at the castle. Our walk started in the forest but the path quickly entered yellow fields of rapeseed.
Once we reached the river Lesse, by going down a very steep path through the forest (around the 3km mark on the map below), we followed a narrow path 
running along the river banks which was the nicest part of the walk. This area was quite dark and lush with many kinds of ferns and
caves that were probably accessible for people who are familiar to caving. At one point we passed a small bar, La Flobette where
you could get from the parking car with a stroller so it’s a good ideal for a walk with kids. We discovered this car parking 
next to some small wooden hut that was office where you could buy a tickets to access the other parts of the park. The 
path we took had no entrance fee (big parking around 5km mark on the map below). There are plenty of other walking paths in this 
area (Walzin Castle further to the west) so it’s definitely a better idea to come to this parking and explore the beauty of 
Furfooz nature reserve. Unfortunately, I found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parcdefurfooz.be/index.php/en/welcome/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; with more details
about this place after our visit so take this opportunity and check all available attractions ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210528_174619.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/Screenshot from 2021-09-05 14-22-29.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the cold night, we happily left the camping in direction to Luxemburg, more precisely to the area of Lac de la Haute-Sûre.
It is the largest water reservoir in the country, built in the 1950s to meet Luxembourg’s drinking water and electricity needs.
There are so many hiking paths that it was difficult to choose one specific area! Finally we parked our car in Esch Sauer,
next to the floating bridge where we started our walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_114412.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_114231_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_122253_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We really enjoyed this walk! First along the waterside, next narrow path led us all the way up to Liefrange, small village with a lot
of campsites. Then, we kept going through the fields in direction of Kaundorf, where we started again getting closer to the 
lake. Once we passed that village, we quickly reached amazing viewpoints from where we could see far in a distance floating
bridge where we started in the morning. Path leading down from the viewpoint towards the lake was really steep so we were happy 
that we decided to do our walk in the opposite direction where uphill part was longer but not very steep. What we also liked
was the fact that there were many benches along the way so we could easily find nice place to have a rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/DSC07570.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_134450_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_141300_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/DSC07594.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_142209_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_154458_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/Screenshot from 2021-09-05 14-23-35.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we still had some time left in the afternoon, after a quick look at the map, we noticed the nearby village Esch-sur-Sûre 
is worth a visit and we were definitely right! We were lucky enough to find a parking spot along the river from where it
was not far to the castle. We just walked through narrow streets to the church and then by the stairs to the top of the hill. There
was no entrance fee (parking was also free) and we could admire from there stunning view of the river and steep hills surrounding 
this small city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_160341.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_160439.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We noticed another tower on the other side of the hill (photo below) but to get there we had to go all the way down to the village 
and then take another, much longer stairs uphill. My curiosity of the view was too strong and quickly won with fatigue after the 
whole day of activities. Luckily, it was worth it! The tower itself had few levels from where we could admire this beautiful 
region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/20210529_160800.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5291776_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5291777_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was our last day on the camping, we packed everything to the car after breakfast and headed to La Roche-en-Ardenne.
That day we had a reservation to visit Hotton cave in the early afternoon so we still had enough time to stop and visit La Roche.
It was definitely the most crowded place we visited during this longer weekend, we finally found a parking spot on the Av. 
du Hadja. To our surprise, the city was really crowded, mostly dominated by motorcyclists. We had a walk to Belvédère 
de La Roche, from where we could admire the view of the city and nearby hills. Then, we came back down to the river to check
city park and come back to the car, grabbing ice cream in the center. There is a castle and a 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.batarden.be/&quot;&gt;military museum&lt;/a&gt; in the city but we didn’t have time 
to check these out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/DSC07603_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301786_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301800_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301811_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/Screenshot from 2021-09-05 14-24-49.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our last attraction of the weekend was the visit in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grottesdehotton.be/eng/home.html&quot;&gt;Hotton Caves&lt;/a&gt;. We bought our tickets online for guided tour in English. 
The cave is well maintained but without light shows and underground boat ride, a more natural character is preserved. Probably
not as interesting for young kids, for them better option would be the &lt;a href=&quot;https://grotte-de-han.be/en&quot;&gt;Caves of Han&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lesgrottes.be/&quot;&gt;Caves of Remouchamps&lt;/a&gt;.
In general, we liked tha cave but we were hoping for more corridors open for the visitors as we feld that it was not enough 
what we saw. Maybe it’s just the matter of comparison to the big cave we visited in Georgia few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301837_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301835_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301833_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Dinant/P5301831_edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were so lucky with the weather, it was first few days with some sun after long, rainy weeks! It was definitely intense but
amazing weekend :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;De Citadel Dinant - 10 euro entrance fee, you can take a cable car or 408 steps get up to the top. Toilets on the top 
  but you have to pay 0.50 euro which is strange after paying for the entrance. There are big parking areas on the top of 
  the hill where you can buy entrance ticket so other option would be to leave the car here, visit Citadel and city (ticket 
  allows you to leave the citadel) and come back. Everyone was obligated to wear a mask in the whole area of the fortress 
  but also in the city center. More info on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.citadellededinant.be/en/&quot;&gt;official website of the Citadelle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Car parking in Dinant - we decided to park in the city center but not close to the Citadelle where it was diffucult to
  find free parking places, we parked on Rue Alexandre Daoust 46, 20 min. walking distance from the Citadelle (1.5km), many 
  spots available and most of them in the shadow of the trees what is always really helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Car parking in Luxemburg - 13 Lultzhausen, 9666 Esch-Sauer. The price was around 0.6euro/hour so very reasonable but 
  parking was not very big. We easily found a spot but it was not high season yet. There were many parkings in other parts
  of the lake that were much bigger. More information about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naturpark-sure.lu/en/&quot;&gt;this area&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We stayed at &lt;a href=&quot;https://pontbergueme.be/&quot;&gt;Camping Pont de Berguème&lt;/a&gt;, despite to be close to the highway, it was very quiet
  and nice area, next to the stream where kids could play in the water. Clean facilities, nice owners, very much recommended.
  Just keep in mind that nights in June are still pretty cold in Belgium, around 6-7 °C, take a warm sleeping bag if 
  you are camping with a tent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In La Roche-en-Ardenne, we parked the car on Av. du Hadja. Nearby parkings were completely full.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hotton Cave - entrance 10euro/adult, visiting time was about 45min, definitely worth to have sport shoes (slippery and dark inside) 
  and extra jacket if visiting in the summer because temperature in the cave is around 12°C. We bought our tickets
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grottesdehotton.be/eng/home.html&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2021/06/Belgium-Dinant/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2021/06/Belgium-Dinant/</guid>
        
        <category>Belgium</category>
        
        <category>Wallonia</category>
        
        <category>Dinant</category>
        
        <category>lake</category>
        
        <category>Luxemburg</category>
        
        <category>cave</category>
        
        <category>Hotton</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zima odnaleziona! Równica oraz Kotarz, okolica miejscowości Brenna</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Tego dnia pogoda była naprawdę wymarzona! Lekki mróz, zalegający nadal śnieg oraz bezchmurne niebo. Postanowiliśmy
tym razem wejść na Kotarz niebieskim szlakiem, który mija zalew Hołcyna a następnie udać się w przeciwnym kierunku niż 
poprzednio czyli wrócić do Brennej mijając Chatę Wuja Toma. Pomimo tego, że wchodziliśmy tą samą drogą, obecność białego 
puchu sprawiła, że widoki były zdecydowanie lepsze. Również ilość turystów i zaparkowanych wzdłuż drogi samochodów 
świadczyła o tym, że warunki tego dnia były naprawdę idealne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271503.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271507.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271520.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podejście nie sprawiło nam żadnych problemów i szybko osiągnęliśmy ponownie Halę Jaworową by od razu skierować się na sam szczyt.
Najpiękniejszym odcinkiem dzisiejszej trasy był zdecydowanie fragment szlaku czerwonego pomiędzy szczytem Kotarz a Beskidkiem 
(zaczęliśmy zejście w dół ścieżką chwilę za starym wyciagiem która prowadzi wzdłuż potoku Węgierski aby uniknąć popularnej drogi 
asfaltowej, która prowadzi do Chaty Wuja Toma). Nie spotkaliśmy tam prawie nikogo, było cicho a białe drzewa na tle niebieskiego 
nieba wyglądały bajecznie! Gdy tylko doszliśmy do drogi w dzielnicy Brenna Jurkula, ujrzeliśmy mnóstwo samochodów, które były 
zaparkowane dosłownie wszedzie i taka sytuacja miała miejsce aż do parkingów przy Karczmie Pod Skalicą. Do Brennej zjechała 
się tego dnia taka ilość ludzi, że cieżko było w to uwierzyć. Na szczęście my już kończyliśmy naszą wędrówkę podczas gdy inni dopiero 
ją zaczynali co nas bardzo zdziwiło bo do zmroku pozostało jakieś 1.5 godziny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271524.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271525.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC271536.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po kilku dniach dojadania świątecznych potraw, czuliśmy ogromną potrzebę ponownego wyjścia w góry i dlatego ruszyliśmy na Równice.
Początkowo podążalismy przez 3km wzdłuż potoku Brennica, aby następnie odbić w kierunku Leśnicy (na skrzyżowaniu stacja paliw), gdzie
wzdłuż drogi widoczne było już oznaczenie zielonego szlaku prowadzącego na szczyt. W pewnym momencie odbija on ostro w prawo i
zaczyna wznosić coraz wyżej, mijając ostatnie domy i wkraczając do lasu. Po dłuższym odcinku przechodzącym przez las, szlak
ten lączy się z niebieskim prowadzący na Równicę. Z racji tego, że już bylismy tam wcześniej a nie planowaliśmy postoju w 
schronisku, lepszą opcją wydało nam się odbicie na niebieski szlak i udanie sie w kierunku szczytu Beskidek, Orłowa i zejście 
w dół jedna ze ścieżek do ulicy Leśnica. Niestety w tym regionie śniegu było już bardzo mało, zrobiło się w wielu miejscach nawet dość
mokro przez topniejący śnieg, ale wciąż znalazłam oszronione liście, które były świetnym materiałem do zabawy z makrofotografią.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011550.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011555.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011557.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011567.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1011570.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Przed wyjazdem postanowiliśmy jeszcze spróbowac znaleźć Krzyż Zakochanych o którym dużo słyszałam i widziałam drogowskaz
w to miejsce na głownej drodze prowadzącej przez Brenna, ale nigdy nie było okazji, aby się tam wybrać. Na skrzyżowaniu z 
ulicą Osiedlową ustawiony jest drogowskaz z napisem “Szlak Wspomnień” i to właśnie tam zaczyna się ścieżka która szybko 
zamienić się w leśną ścieżkę. Prowadzi ona cały czas dość stromo pod górkę (2km długości, wzniesienie ok 300m), aby w 
końcowej części się wypłaszczyć i tam właśnie zauważamy krzyż. Jest tam również tablica informacyjna opowiadająca historię 
zakochange w zamożnej pannie, ubogiego młodzieńca i ich ostatnie wspólne chwile zanim zostali rozdzieleni. Miejsce to
osłonięte jest drzewami więc nie ma co liczyc na jakieś specjalne widoki, chyba że podejdzie się na nieco wyżej położoną 
polanę. Podążaliśmy dalej jak prowadziły nas oznaczenia aby w końcu dotrzeć do Lach Dolnych. Niestety zejście nie należało 
do przyjemnych ponieważ ścieżka została okropnie zniszczona przez wycinkę drzew, która w tym miejscu również się odbywa.
Wszędzie było mnóstwo głębokiego błota więc było bardzo ciężko tam przejść, nie topiąc sie w nim bardzo głęboko. Przykro 
patrzeć jak negatywnie na nasze lasy wpływają prowadzone obecnie wycinki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1021592.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1021593.edit.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1021594.edit.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/P1021600.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nocowaliśmy u moich rodziców, którzy wynajmują pokoje gościnne, dlatego chciałabym je polecić, gdy sytuacja epidemiologiczna 
  poprawi się na tyle, że możliwe będą weekendowe wyjazdy w góry z noclegiem &lt;a href=&quot;https://kimanko-pod-sosnami.eu/galeria/&quot;&gt;Kimanko pod sosnami&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mapki poniżej pokazują dokłandie naszą trasę, nie zawsze był to oficjalny szlak bo nie chcieliśmy kilkukrotnie iść tą samą trasą i 
  szukaliśmy szukaliśmy alternatywnych opcji.
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Kotarz-Hata Wuja Toma.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Rownica.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Krzyz_zakochanych.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2021/01/Swieta-Brenna2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2021/01/Swieta-Brenna2/</guid>
        
        <category>Polska</category>
        
        <category>Brenna</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>góry</category>
        
        <category>Kotarz</category>
        
        <category>Błatnia</category>
        
        <category>zima</category>
        
        <category>śnieg</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>W poszukiwaniu oznak zimy na szczytach Błatnia oraz Kotarz, okolica miejscowości Brenna</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;W tym roku zdecydowaliśmy się spędzić Święta u moich rodziców w Polsce. Jako, że od marca oboje pracujemy zdalnie, przed wyjazdem
odbyliśmy kwarantanne i na lotnisko pojechaliśmy własnym samochodem, aby jak najbardziej zminimalizować ryzyko zachorowania na Covid, a co
gorsza zarażenia mojej rodziny. Więc jedynie podczas przebywania na lotnisku oraz samego lotu czuliśmy się najbardziej narażeni na złapanie wirusa,
ale szczęśliwie nie zachorowaliśmy ani nikt z naszej rodziny (co było sprawdzone dwoma testami pcr w Belgii, po powrocie z Polski jak nakazują tego obecne zasady).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niestety Brenna nie przywitała nas wymarzonym białym puchem, ale mocno wierzyłam, że przez dwa tygodnie sytuacja na pewno się zmieni :D
Gdy tylko przestało padać i wiatr ustał, postanowiliśmy dłużej nie zwlekać i kolejnego dnia ruszyć w poszukiwaniu zimy w wyższe partie gór.
Udając się na Kotarz, chcieliśmy sprawdzić ścieżkę, którą kiedyś tam biegłam, zaczynającą się na ulicy Nostrożny (niedaleko karczmy Solisko). 
Podążaliśmy ulicą, która po pewnym czasie zmieniła się w ścieżkę leśną (tam gdzie kończy się asfalt znajduje się rozwidlenie i trzeba wtedy zacząć podążać po prawej stronie
strumienia). Po przejściu niewielkiego odcinka należy ponownie skręcić w prawo co widać na mapie (okolice 3 km) umieszczonej na końcu postu, w sekcji
praktyczne informacje. Niestety na tej wysokości ścieżka ta był mocno rozjechana, prawdopodobnie przez ciężkie samochody używane przy wycince drzew co niestety
zauważyliśmy rownież podczas wypadów w kolejne dni na inne okoliczne szczyty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211345.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211314.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dalej podążaliśmy cały czas tą samą ścieżką aż doszliśmy do rozwidlenia na którym skręciliśmy w lewo, podążając dalej 
na Halę Jaworową, przez którą prowadzi niebieski szlak (opis w kolejnym poście), zaczynający się przy zbiorniku wodnym Hołcyna.
Na Hali Jaworowej wiał bardzo zimny i silny wiatr a widoczność była bardzo słaba, także szybko stamtą uciekliśmy na szczyt Kotarz a następnie
odbiliśmy na czerwony szlak prowadzący na Grabową. Oszronione drzewa i krzewy oraz niewielka ilość śniegu to jedyne ślady zimy jakie tego
dnia znaleźliśmy, ale i tak było warto wybrać się na ten dłuższy spacer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211324.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211336.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC211341.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schronisko na Grabowej było otawrte, ale oferowało tylko jedzenie oraz napoje na wynos. Po minięciu Starego Gronia zrobiło się już na prawdę wiosennie,
przynajmniej ze względu na słońce i błekitne niebo bo temperatury tych wiosennych nadal nie przypomniały. Do samej Brennej podążaliśmy cały czas
zielonym szlakiem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC201308.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kilka dni poźniej w Brennej spadło niewiele śniegu, ledwo pokrywając trawę w ogrodzie ale okoliczne szczyty wyglądały już na bardziej białe
i dlatego od razu zdecydowaliśmy wybrać się na kolejny spacer, tym razem na Błatnią. Jako, że byliśmy na tym szczycie już kilka razy, szukałam
jakiegoś alternatywnego wejścia, żeby ponownie nie iść głównym zielonym szlakiem. W aplikacji MAPS.ME zauważyłam ścieżkę zaczynającą się na końcu ulicy 
Chrobaczy (bardzo niedaleko domu moich rodziców), która powinna nas zaprowadzić w okolice szczytu nad schroniskiem, przechodząc przez Bukowy Groń.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261464.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faktycznie tak było, ścieżkę znależliśmy bez problemu. Najpierw była ona dość wąska z krzewami i niskimi drzewami dookoła co sprawiało wrażenie, że 
podążaliśmy w tunelu. Ku naszej radości, już w tym miejscu bylo sporo śniegu! Biały krajobraz od razu wprowadził nas w wyśmienite nastroje :) Nieco wyżej
natrafiliśmy na kilka drewnianych domków do których prowadziła szersza ścieżka pozwalająca na dojazd terenowym samochodem, którą w pewnym momencie przecieliśmy. 
Szlak cały czas prowadził pod górkę, aż wyszliśmy na bardziej wypłaszczoną łąkę gdzie ujrzeliśmy więcej ludzi w oddali którzy podążali żółtym szlakiem z Błatniej w stronę Klimczoka lub 
Chaty Wuja Toma (trzeba w pewnym momencie odbić ze szlaku w prawo, idąc cały czas w dół kamieniską ścieżką).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261472.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261482.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261488.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po wejściu na sam szczyt góry Błatnia, udaliśmy się do Schroniska PTTK, gdzie rozgrzaliśmy się kawą i gorącą czekoladą (niestety jakość pozostawiała 
wiele do życzenia, ale ciepły napój to zawsze miły akcent wycieczki). Następnie ruszyliśmy w dół ze schroniska szlakiem zielonym, odbijając na ostatnim 
odcinku na szlak czarny prowadzący do Brennej. Oszronione krzewy, pokryte śniegiem drzewa wyglądały naprawdę cudownie i jedyne czego nam wciąż brakowało
to odrobina słońca, ale i to wkrótce się zmieniło o czym będzie kolejny post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/PC261501.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nocowaliśmy u moich rodziców, którzy wynajmują pokoje gościnne, dlatego chciałabym je polecić, gdy sytuacja epidemiologiczna 
  poprawi się na tyle, że możliwe będą weekendowe wyjazdy w góry z noclegiem &lt;a href=&quot;https://kimanko-pod-sosnami.eu/galeria/&quot;&gt;Kimanko pod sosnami&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kawa, gorąca czekolada, grzane piwo na wynos w schronisku Błatnia to koszt 8-9zł&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mapki poniżej pokazują dokłandie naszą trasę, nie zawsze był to oficjalny szlak bo nie chcieliśmy kilkukrotnie iść tą samą trasą i 
  szukaliśmy alternatywnych opcji.
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Kotarz-Stary Gron.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Poland/Brenna/Blatnia.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2021/01/Swieta-Brenna/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2021/01/Swieta-Brenna/</guid>
        
        <category>Polska</category>
        
        <category>Brenna</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>góry</category>
        
        <category>Kotarz</category>
        
        <category>Błatnia</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wycieczka do stolicy francuskojęzycznej części Belgii oraz ruin klasztoru Villers Abbey</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Średniowieczne ruiny fortecy z cegły lub kamienia i leniwie płynąca rzeka w tle lub też pozostałości XI wiecznego klasztoru…te 
inspirujące do zdjęć miejsca przewijały się w mojej głowie, gdy planowałam wyjazd na kolejny słoneczny weekend. Fotografia to
jedna z moich największych pasji (poza chodzeniem po górach, bieganiem oraz podróżami) więc zawsze mam już jakieś pomysły co do
zdjęć zanim odwiedzimy dane miejsce. Jak praktycznie zawsze, pogoda decyduje czy mam szanse na interesujące zdjęcia czy też nie. Sporo czasu
spędzam na blogach innych podróżników czy śledząc ich konta na instagramie, skąd czerpię mnóstwo inspiracji, głównie tych
górskich! :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Właśnie zorientowałam się, że tak naprawdę piszę o Belgii po raz pierwszy a mieszkamy tu już dwa lata! Wynika to z faktu, że w tym
roku nasze podróże, mocno ograniczone przez rządowe restrykcje, zostały zamienione na te bardziej lokalne, weekendowe wypady. Sytuację
ułatwił nam zakup samochodu na wiosnę tego roku, dwa tygodnie przed zamknięciem granic kraju i tzw lockdown, kiedy to oboje zaczęliśmy
pracować z domu i co to tej pory się nie zmieniło. Tak więc samochód pozwala nam na jednodniowe lub weekendowe wycieczki
w kraju lub do sąsiednich krajów (na przykład do &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/en_US/Netherlands/&quot;&gt;Holandi&lt;/a&gt;, jeśli oczywiście przepisy w danym momencie na to pozwalają.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Namur od dawna był jednym z miast w Belgii na mojej liście celów podróżniczych, po tym jak słyszałam dobre opinie o tym miejscu od kilku osób. Położone na
tyle blisko od miejsca gdzie mieszkamy, że mogliśmy bez problemu podjąć spontaniczną dycyzję o odwiedzeniu tego samego dnia.
Na pierwszym zdjęciu poniżej widać Palais des Congrès (obecnie centrum kongresowe, które kiedyś było giełdą papierów wartościowych), który
minęliśmy w drodze do historycznej cytadeli. Samo centrum miasta nie zrobiło na nas większego wrażenia, zwykłe małe miasteczko, jednak najlepsze
miejsca były dopiero przed nami :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07366.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wspinając się po wzgórzu cytadeli, w pewnym momencie zobaczyliśmy mieniącą się w słońcu rzeźbę ogromengo żółwia z siedzącym na nim jeźdźcem.
Niestety nie mogliśmy znaleźć żadnego opisu tej rzeźby i dopiero po powrocie okazało się, że jest ona stworzona przez artystę Jan Fabre i 
nazywa się “W poszukiwaniu Utopi”. Jej kopia znajduje się również w innym belgijskim mieście położonym na wybrzeżu, Nieuwpoort. Dokładnie
wypolerowana, błyszcząca w złotym kolorze, nie da się jej nie zauważyć! :) Ten sam artysta stworzył również instalację zwaną Totem na placu
Ladeuzeplein w Leuven, która jest przykładem sztuki w przestrzeni publicznej. Tej również ciężko nie zauważyć, ale w innego powodu. Przedstawia bowiem
tajskiego żuka - broszkę, nabitego na 23m wysoką igłę.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07371.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07372.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poniżej przepiękna panorama rzeki Meuse widziana w drodze na najwyższą część cytadeli, gdzie można dojechać samochodem, turystycznym tramwajem
albo po prostu na nogach. Na każdym poziomie wzgórza, mogliśmy podziwiać dolinę rzeki z zupełnie innej perspektywy. Tydzień później wybraliśmy
się na wycieczkę rowerową wzdłuż tej samej rzeki, ale niedaleko miasta Maastricht, w Holandii. Szczególnie okolice pobliskiego miasteczka Oud-Rekem
(Belgia) są świetnym miejscem wypadowym dla wielbicieli rowerów!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07376.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Château de Namur (obecnie hotel, zdjęcie poniżej), otoczony ogrodem z mnóstwem róż, które pomimo później pory roku wciąż kwitły był najdalszym miejscem przez nas 
odwiedzonym podczas spaceru po rozległej cytadeli. Nasz spacer zajął nam ponad 2h a można tam spędzić nawet więcej czasu, odwiedzając restaurację (tam kończy
swoją podróż tramwaj turystyczny) lub wybierając się na spacer z przewodnikiem tunelami fortyfikacji. W pewnym momencie minęliśmy również dawny teatr oraz 
nowoczesne centrum dla odwiedzajacych (jeszcze nie otwarte).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07384.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07385.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07389.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nasza droga powrotna prowadziła drugą stroną wzgórza, z której rozpościera się widok na starą część miasta, w której okolicy zaparkowaliśmy samochód. 
W Belgi wiele restauracji zamykanych jest w ciągu dnia, pomiędzy 14.00 a 17.00, więc musieliśmy się spieszyć z wyborem miejsca, aby nie zostać głodnym
przez resztę dnia i na szczęście dobrze trafiliśmy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07391.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07392.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07394.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Już na autostradzie prowadzącej w kierunku regionu, gdzie położone są ruiny klasztoru Villers Abbey, zauważyliśmy tablice informujące o tym wyjątkowym
miejscu. Okazało się, że jest to bardzo popularny cel wycieczek o czym przekonaliśmy się zaraz po wjeździe do wioski Villers-la-Ville, gdzie
samochody były zaparkowane po prostu wszędzie. Zdecydowaliśmy spróbować naszego szczęścia na jednym z dużych, darmowych parkingów, które wydawały się
być zapełnione po brzegi. Byliśmy niezwykle szczęśliwi, gdy przejeżdżając przez jeden z nich, zatrzymała nas starsza kobieta i oznajmiła, że właśnie
odjeżdża, więc możemy zająć jej miejsce. Bardzo szybko znaleźliśmy kasy biletowe i po okazaniu wcześniej zakupionych przez internet biletów oraz 
otrzymaniu mapki ruin, zaczęliśmy zwiedzanie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07399.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wedłu otrzymanej mapki, zdjęcie powyżej ukazuje salę jadalną w dawnym klasztorze, gdzie wszyscy mnichowie gromadzili się na wspólne posiłki.
Obecnie miejsce to jest okupowane przez kilka kóz oraz gęsi. Od razu zauważyliśmy, że rośliny zawładnęły tym miejscem dawno temu i tylko dzięki
ogromnym wysiłkom pracowników tego miejsca, główna konstrukcja budynku została zachowana a ściany nie zostały wręcz rozerwane przez silne
korzenie roślin. Piękne łuki, kolumny, niezwykłe kształty okien tworzą oryginalną scenografię do zdjęć portretowych lub modowych. Faktycznie,
widzieliśmy tam kilka modelek w pięknych sukniach z profesjonalnymi fotografami robiącymi im zdjęcia. Intensywne kolory sukni pieknie odznaczały
się na tle stonowanych kolorów kamienia lub cegły.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07405.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07406.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07409.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07412.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07434.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gdy tylko wkroczyliśmy do dawnego kościoła, ogromna nawa zrobiła na nas niesamowite wrażenie. Na zdjęciu widać jak małe są postacie ludzi (dolne, 
prawe zdjęcie) i jak wysoka jest nawa. Dość długo czekałam na moment kiedy mniej ludzi będzie przechadzało się po nawie, w tym dniu było tam na 
prawdę sporo odwiedzających. Myśleliśmy, że we wrześniu i z racji pandemii, nie będzie tam tak tłoczno. Na prawdę zależało mi na zdjęciach bez
przypadkowej głowy czy ramienia, szczególnie gdy architektura odgrywa na nich główną rolę :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07418.1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07424.1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07435.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07430.1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07455.1.1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po przejściu przez zakrystię oraz pozostałości pałacu, w końcu wkroczyliśmy do ogrodów z fontanną oraz przeróżnymi kolorowymi
kwiatami, gdzie było już widać pierwsze oznaki jesieni. Było tam dość cicho i ładnie, ale ogród nie jest zbyt duży. Od razu
zauważyliśmy szerokie schody prowadzące do kaplicy i winnicy. Fakt, że schody prowadzą pod wiaduktem kolejowym bardzo nas zaskoczył,
przejeżdżając tutaj pociagiem możemy z góry zobaczyć przez moement całe ruiny klasztoru. Ze szczytu wzniesienia rozpościera się widok
na małą winnicę i tylko niewielki fragment klasztoru bo wiekszość zasłania trakcja kolejowa oraz ogromne drzewa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07438.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07449.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07450.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07457.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Może śmiesznie to zabrzmi, ale mieliśmy problem ze znalezieniem wyjścia. Widzieliśmy tam wiele znaków wskazujących a to w prawo a
to w lewo i tak podążaliśmy za kolejnymi. Po dobrych 10min i przejściu jeszcze raz prawie całego kompleksu znaleźliśmy się bardzo
blisko wejścia i tam ukryte były schody prowadzące kładką na druga stronę ulicy i być może to nas zmyliło. Tam znajduje się łąka
z punktem widokowym na ruiny klasztoru. To nie było koniec naszej wędrówki do wyjścia, przed nami było jeszcze centrum dla odwiedzających,
kawiarnia, sklepik z pamiątkami oraz restauracja, no nie było łatwo! :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07463.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Citadelle de Namur - wejście darmowe. Na wzgórze, gdzie znajduje się restauracja i centrum dla odwiedzających (jedyne miejsce z toaletami) 
  prowadzi kilka ścieżek w tym jedna dla osób z wózkami (ścieżka A na mapie). Minęliśmy dwa parkingi samochodowe na samej górze wzniesienia, jednak 
  nie są one zbyt duże więc trzeba mieć dużo szczęścia albo zacząć zwiedzanie o poranku, żeby znaleźć tam wolne miejsce. Każdy z odwiedzających
  musi nosić na terenie całej cytadeli maskę ochronną, również w centrum miasta obowiązuje taka zasada (tak samo w Leuven czy Brukseli, całe części 
  miast są oznaczone jako takie strefy). Wszystko dokładnie wyjaśnione na tablicach informacyjnych w języku francuskim oraz angielskim, ustawionych
  na ulicach. Więcej informacji na stronie &lt;a href=&quot;https://citadelle.namur.be/en&quot;&gt;Citadelle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07380.1.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Restauracja w Namur którą z pewnością polecamy - bardzo smaczne japońskie zupy Ramen z różnymi opcjami mięsa oraz bulionu i przeróżnymi dodatkami
  takimi jak: pędy bambusa, nori, cebulka, jajka, grzyby oraz specjalnym makaronem, zwany często “chow mein noodles” &lt;a href=&quot;https://sanganamur.be/&quot;&gt;restauracja Sanga&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Miejsce parkingowe w Namur - zdecydowalismy sie zaparkować w centrum miasta, jednak nie przy samej cytadeli. Z doświadczenia wiemy, że parkując
  blisko głównych atrakcji miasta traci się więcej czasu na poszukiwania miejsca niż trwa krótki spacer z bardziej oddalonego parkingu. Zaparkowaliśmy
  na ulicy Rue des Bourgeois (10 min. spacerem od cytadeli, gdzie wzdłuż całej ulicy były wyznaczone miejsca parkingowe). Z tablicy informacyjnej
  wynikało, że strefa ta jest płatna od 9.00 do 17.00, z wyjątkiem niedzieli. Bilet można było zakupić w automacie.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bilet wstępu do Villers Abbey - 9 euro od osoby, bilety &lt;a href=&quot;https://reservation.elloha.com/?idPublication=b4abf422-9c14-4521-bc9e-069d1cdb3a5b&amp;amp;idoi=692d414a-3dbf-4ea0-b4ca-a02b2255f231&amp;amp;idPrestation=0b95964a-04fd-41a2-8894-cb17d926ec91&amp;amp;culture=en-GB&amp;amp;searchFirstAvailableDates=1&amp;amp;fbclid=IwAR0AakdxxDoEFAP7amM7lAfzsFTxRaYI6F5FvDBFuickiazBvLW6euSnAmk&quot;&gt;zakupione przez internet&lt;/a&gt;
  tego samego dnia kiedy odwiedzaliśmy to miejsce poniewaz nie mogliśmy znaleźć opcji zakupu biletu na konkretny dzień. Nie było nakazu noszenia
  maseczek w środku obiektu (tylko przy kasach biletowych), jednak wiele osób je nosiło, być może dlatego, że było tam dość tłoczno.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2020/09/Belgium-Namur/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2020/09/Belgium-Namur/</guid>
        
        <category>Belgia</category>
        
        <category>Walonia</category>
        
        <category>Namur</category>
        
        <category>rzeka</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>French-speaking part of Belgium, Namur and Villers Abbey</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The old wall of a medieval fortress made of red bricks and stone with the river slowly running in the background or maybe ruins
 of the abbey from XI century… these scenes for the unique pictures came to my mind while wondering about destination for the
 upcoming, sunny weekend. Photography is one of my biggest passions (besides hiking, running and travelling) and I always 
 have some ideas for photos in mind before actually visiting the place :D I spend quite some time checking other 
 travelling blogs and following travellers on instagram from where I get a lot of inspiration!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just realized that it’s the first time I’m writing about Belgium and we live here for 2 years already! This summer we
 are travelling more locally because of travel restriction implemented by the government to reduce the spread of the virus.
 Luckily we bought a car in the spring this year (just two weeks before the lockdown when we both started to work from home)
 so now we are using it to make one-day trips, visiting also neighbouring countries (like the &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/en_US/Netherlands/&quot;&gt;Netherlands&lt;/a&gt; if current situation allows to do it
 safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Namur was definitely one of the cities on my list to visit in Belgium after hearing about this place nice opinions. Located
close enough from the place where we live to make spontaneous decision in the morning and go the same day. On the first photo below
you can see Palais des Congrès (currently a congress center which was in the past a stock exchange), which we passed on the way to 
historical Citadel. The city center didn’t make a big impression on us but the best spots were still ahead of us :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07366.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As were walking up the hill, a rather unique sculpture appeared next to the walls of the castle. We looked for any description or at least name 
of it but we couldn’t find any. Later, I have found that artwork of artist Jan Fabre is called ‘Searching for utopia’ and the copy of it
can be found by the Belgium coast in Nieuwpoort. It’s really shiny and visible from the distance so for sure you will not miss it! 
This artist is also responsible for modern art installation called the Totem on Ladeuzeplein in Leuven. This one is also difficult
to miss but for another reason, its uniqueness, as it shows huge Thai jewel beetle stuck on a 23 m high steel needle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07371.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07372.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beautiful panoramic view of the Meuse River on the way to the top of the hill, where you can get by car, touristic tram or simply on foot.
As we were getting higher up the hill, we could admire the whole panorama of the river valley from another perspective. A week later we were 
cycling along the same river but in the region of Maastricht, the Netherlands. Btw, the area of Oud-Rekem is just paradise for cyclist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07376.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Château de Namur (nowadays a hotel), which is surrounded by a nice garden, was the furthest point we reached during our walk (photo below). 
The whole area of Citadel is quite big, it took a few hours to explore it. There are some tunnels to walk by and we noticed it is 
possible to visit some underground corridors with the guide but I think now their offers are not available. There is also an old theater and 
the visitor center in the same building as the restaurant (it’s the final stop of the tram).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07384.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07385.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07389.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way back we stayed on the other side of the hill, overlooking the old part of the city where we parked our car. It was already 
past lunch time so high time to look for a restaurant. In Belgium many restaurants close between 2 pm and 5 pm, so we had to
hurry up to make sure we found something to eat before that afternoon break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07391.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07392.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07394.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already on the highway leading to the area where Villers Abbey is located, we notice the signs advertising this place. It turned
out to be very popular based on amount of people we found there! As soon as we got to the village Villers-la-Ville, we were
shocked by the amount of cars parked just everywhere. We decided to first try and go to one of big, free parking but they all 
seemed to be fully packed. We were really lucky when a women walking through parking, offered her spot as she were leaving.
We found the entrance pretty quickly and after showing our tickets on the phone, we could start exploring the ruins with the small map
we got at the entrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07399.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the map, the photo above shows the refectory; the dining are were monks used to eat together but now there place is occupied
by few goats and geese. You can clearly see that plants began taking over this abandoned abbey long time ago and only
thanks to relentless efforts, plants didn’t completely destroy the construction of this place. Beautiful arched, columns, unusual
shapes of windows, make an interesting setting for portrait or fashion photography. Indeed, there were a few models
in a beautiful dresses with professional photographers taking their photos. Dresses in the vibrant colors look stunning against the 
muted tones in the background of stone and rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07405.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07406.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07409.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07412.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07434.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we entered the ruins of the church, the huge nave (the central part) made a big impression on us. Just, look how small the people are 
in the photo. I did have to patiently wait for a moment with fewer people, don’t be misled by what you see on my photos …
it was really crowded that day. But I really hate to have a random leg or head on the photos where architecture plays the 
major role :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07418.1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07424.1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07435.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07430.1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07455.1.1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We passed the sacristy and abbey’s palace to finally end up in the gardens with fountains and colorful plants, although we could clearly
notice the first signs of autumn. Pretty and quiet place but now very big. We immediately noticed big stairs leading to chapel and 
vineyard. What surprised us … there was a railway track just above the stairs so when you are traveling by train, you can catch a glimpse of
the abbey. From the top of the hill we could see the ruins of the abbey from a distance, but only a small fragment was visible as the rest
was covered by trees and passing trains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07438.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07449.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07450.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07457.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As funny as it sounds, we couldn’t find the exit. There were many signs pointing left/right in different places of the complex but we felt 
like we are going from one to another without any known direction, after good 10 minutes of following the directions, we finally ended up in 
front of the stairs leading to the fields located on the other site of the street from where we could see the abbey from a distance. We had
to pass visitors center, cafe, souvenir shop and another restaurant to get outside, really not easy! :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07463.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Citadelle de Namur - free entrance, few different ways to get up to the top, including one for people with strollers (entrance A),
  all of them leading to the restaurant and visitor center (with toilets inside). There are two parking areas on the top of the hill but with very
  limited number of spots so you need to be lucky to find a free one. Everyone was obligated to wear a mask in the whole area of the
  fortress but also in the city center. The signs explaining the rules applying in the city were visible very often on the streets, we
  notice them immediately after we started to walk towards city center. More info on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://citadelle.namur.be/en&quot;&gt;official website of the Citadelle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Belgium/Namur/DSC07380.1.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A restaurant in Namur that we can certainly recommend - very tasty Japanese Ramen Noodle soup including meat, bamboo shoot, nori, spring onions,
   broth of choice, egg, mushrooms and wheat noodles, which are also sometimes called chow mein noodles. &lt;a href=&quot;https://sanganamur.be/&quot;&gt;Ramen restaurant Sanga&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Car parking in Namur - we decided to park in the city center but not close to the Citadelle where it was diffucult to
  find free parking places, we parked on Rue des Bourgeois, 10 min. walking distance from the Citadelle, many spots available.
  It is paid parking zones from 9am until 5pm everyday of the week, except on Sundays and as were were there on Sunday, we didn’t have
  to purchase a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Entrance to Villers Abbey - 9 euro per person, tickets &lt;a href=&quot;https://reservation.elloha.com/?idPublication=b4abf422-9c14-4521-bc9e-069d1cdb3a5b&amp;amp;idoi=692d414a-3dbf-4ea0-b4ca-a02b2255f231&amp;amp;idPrestation=0b95964a-04fd-41a2-8894-cb17d926ec91&amp;amp;culture=en-GB&amp;amp;searchFirstAvailableDates=1&amp;amp;fbclid=IwAR0AakdxxDoEFAP7amM7lAfzsFTxRaYI6F5FvDBFuickiazBvLW6euSnAmk&quot;&gt;bought online&lt;/a&gt;
  on the day of the visit as we haven’t see the option to buy them the day before. It is not obligatory to wear a mask inside but many people 
  have them anyway, maybe because it was quite crowded.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2020/09/Belgium-Namur/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2020/09/Belgium-Namur/</guid>
        
        <category>Belgium</category>
        
        <category>Wallonia</category>
        
        <category>Namur</category>
        
        <category>river</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kolejny dzień w Zeeland, spacer plażą do Cadzand-Bad, przy granicy z Belgią</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Bezchmurne niebo przywitało nas również kolejnego dnia, było dość chłodno, ale perspektywna słonecznego dnia sprawiła, że
całkiem szybko byliśmy gotowi na całodzienną, pieszą wycieczkę do miasta położonego dokładnie na granicy z Belgią, Cadzand-Bad.
Postanowiliśmy całą drogę przejść po plaży, zaczynając przy rezerwacie przyrody zwanym Zwarte Polder. Jest on miejscem 
uwielbianym przez ptactwo, zwłaszcza mewy oraz otoczonym zielonymi polami, na których przechadzają się owce. Świetne miejsce
dla miłośników ptaków i tylko przy pomocy długiego obiektywu udało mi się zrobić zdjęcia mew, które latały jak szalone nad 
naszymi głowami. Przez środek tego małego rezerwatu prowadzi drewniana kładka, którą dojdziemy na plażę, po drodze mijając małe 
stawy i szuwary czyli idelane miejsca lęgowe różnych gatunków ptaków (jak wyjaśniają tablice informacyjne).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07169.edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Zwarte Polder nature reserve&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/P7200440.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07178.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07175.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07184.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07189.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07191.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spacer po plaży okazał się bardzo przyjemny, ponieważ jeszcze mokry i twardy piasek po odpływie powodował, że nasze
stopy nie zapadały się głęboko. Dość mocno wiało i takie warunki przyciągnęły ponownie wielbicieli sportów wodnych.
Zbliżając się do Cadzand-Bad, zauważyliśmy wysokie hotele oraz nowe budynki z mieszkaniami na sprzedaż zaraz przy plaży. Od razu skojarzyło
mi się to miejsce z Oostende, pierwszym odwiedzonym przeze mnie miastem na belgijskim wybrzeżu. Oczywiście wiąże się to z
większą ilością osób w mieście oraz na plaży, co zdecydowanie zauważyliśmy. W innych przez nas odwiedzonych częściach Holandii
nie było takiego trendu w budownickwie co bardziej nam się podoba. Leżenie na plaży z widokiem na hotele nie jest już
tak relaksujące. Wyobrażam sobie, że zachód słońca z wyższych pięter tych budynków musi być niesamowity, ale nie jest już to samo, gdy
przy plaży nie ma pasma pięknych wydm, które niejako ukrywają plażowiczów i chronią wnętrze lądu przed działaniem morza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07225.edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;walk towards Cadzand-Bad&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07216.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07233.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po opuszczeniu plaży udaliśmy się do niewielkiego portu, aby następnie podążać wzdłuż ścieżki rowerowej prowadzącej do dość dużego
rezerwatu przyrody zwanego “Het Zwin”. Jest to depresyjny teren nadmorski otoczony wydmami. Aby dowiedzić ten rezerwat przyrody, który znany 
jest jako miejsce  występowania wielu gatunków
ptaków, trzeba zakupić bilet online na określoną godzinę. Z racji tego, że wejście do parku znajduje się po drugiej stronie niż ta z 
której my przyszliśmy, nie udało nam się wejść do środka (dodatkowe kilka km marszu w jedną stronę). Doszliśmy za to do punktu widokowego, 
gdzie przebiega granica między oba krajami i widać z oddali cały obszar rezerwatu przyrody. Nie jest możliwe dojście tam plażą co skróciłoby 
drastycznie dystans, ponieważ dwa razy dziennie podczas przypływów woda z morza wpływa na teren rezerwatu. Zdecydowaliśmy się
poleżeć na plaży niedaleko tego punktu widokowego (mniej zatłoczona), z ładnym widokiem na rezerwat przyrody oraz mnóstwem latawców unoszących 
się w powietrzu, a następnie udać się w długą drogę powrotną na nasze pole namiotowe :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07236.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Z racji tego, że był to nasz ostatni dzień z szansą na zachód słońca, pomimo przebytych już wielu kilometrów, postanowiliśmy 
ponownie udać się wieczorem na plażę. Tego dnia niebo było nieco zachmurzone w ciągu dnia, ale wieczorem, jakby specjalnie dla nas wszystkie
chmury zniknęły i był to naprawdę piękny zachód słońca. Nie spotkaliśmy wielu ludzi na plaży, ale za to lokalna szkoła jeździectwa postanowiła 
wybrać się na przejażdżkę konną a wiadomo, konie na tle zachodzącego słońca wyglądają magicznie!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07244.edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunset in Nieuwvliet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07255.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ostatniego dnia chcieliśmy jedynie poleżeć na plaży i wygrzać się na słońcu, zanim ruszymy w drogę powrotną. Podczas mojego wieczornego
biegu pierwszego dnia, przebiegałam obok sporego parkingu zaraz przy rezerwacie Waterdunen i pomyślałam, że możemy właśnie tam podjechać 
ostatniego dnia. Oczywiście z moim szczęściem wylądowaliśmy na samym środku plaży dla naturystów :D Podczas naszej ostatniej wycieczki
również natknęliśmy się na plaże oznaczoną “nudistenstrand” i to słowo już zapamiętałam a tu nagle kolejne oznaczające również ten 
sam typ plaży - “naaktstrand”. Świetny przykład na to, że podróże kształcą a mnie dodatkowo uczą holenderskiego :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Po wejściu na plaże, skręciliśmy w prawo do miejsca, gdzie plaża kończy się i zaczyna rezerwat przyrody, także dalszy spacer plażą nie jest
już możliwy. Rezerwat ten jest kolejnym miejsce dla wielbicieli ptaków, cały jego teren to mokradła, uwielbiane przez wiele 
gatunków ptaków. Po południu, już mieliśmy wychodzić z plaży, kiedy zauważyłam małą grupkę ludzi wypatrujących czegoś w morzu. Okazało się, że foka
podpłynęła naprawdę blisko i w pewnym momencie nawet wyskoczyła na niski, betonowy falochron, aby po chwili zniknąć spowrotem w wodzie.
Używając długiego obiektywu mogłam uchwycić ją naprawdę z bliska, jednak była dość szybka i znikała często pod wodą wiec trzeba było
wykazać się refleksem. Także była to nasza ostatnia, niespodziewana atrakcja podczas tego wyjazdu!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07281.edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Beach close to Nieuwvliet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07287.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07292.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informacje praktyczne:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zatrzymaliśmy się na polu namiotowym: &lt;a href=&quot;https://minicampingdecatshoek.nl/&quot;&gt;Camping De Catshoek&lt;/a&gt;, które z pewnością możemy polecić!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nasz spacer do Cadzend to około 24,5km (mapa poniżej pokazuje mniej kilometrów ponieważ naszkicowałam ją już po powrocie,
  dystans w lini prostej co nie uwzględnia więc szczegółowo naszej trasy oraz dodatkowego spaceru w mieście Cadzand).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/Screenshot from 2020-08-30 15-13-18.png&quot; alt=&quot;Walk to Cadzand-Bad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parking samochodowy - 4.0 euro za dzień (1 euro/h), Parkeerplaats Walendijk, wejście na plaże prowadzi do baru “Van Houten” oraz
niespodziewanie również na plażę dla naturystów (ważne słowo do zapamiętania po holendersku - “naaktstrand”). Ta wyznaczona 
tablicami informacyjnymi część plaży rozciąga się może jakieś 200m, więc nie trzeba daleko iść, aby leżec poza tą strefą.
Można również iść ścieżką rowerową do kolejnego wejścia na plażę (skręcając w prawo, stojąc w kierunku morza na parkingu), aby ominąć przechodzenie 
przez plażę dla naturystów.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2020/08/Zeeland-Cadzand/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/pl/podroze/2020/08/Zeeland-Cadzand/</guid>
        
        <category>Holandia</category>
        
        <category>plaza</category>
        
        <category>morze</category>
        
        <category>wydmy</category>
        
        <category>Cadzand-Bad</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zeeland again! Walk by the beach to Cadzand-Bad</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The weather was again amazing, the air a bit chilly, but no rain predicted and that was crucial. Our plan for today was to 
visit the city located on the border with Belgium, Cadzand-Bad… on foot! First, we had to walk straight 
to the beach where we ended up just if front of the Zwarte Polder nature reserve, surrounded by green fields with many sheep walking
idly in the sun. Great place to observe seagulls, they were flying just above our heads. Only after taking out my long camera lens, 
I was able to snap a couple of good, sharp pictures of them. Very quiet area with high grass and hidden small ponds which are nesting places for many 
bird species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07169.edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Zwarte Polder nature reserve&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/P7200440.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07178.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07175.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07184.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07189.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07191.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very easy to walk along the water where the sand was still wet and quite hard. As we got closer to the Cadzand-Bad, 
big hotels and apartment buildings started to appear on the horizon. In the Netherlands this is rare, but the Belgian 
coastline is packed with buildings like that. I remember being in Oostende, a city in Belgium with even higher hotels what results 
in many people visiting that cities and indeed, also here we noticed that it was more crowded on the beach but also in the city. 
As these hotels were located along the beach, laying on the sand was not that relaxing anymore. I agree, the view from the higher 
floors during the sunset must be amazing but the character of the beach and dunes … it’s not the same anymore with these
tall buildings near the coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07225.edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;walk towards Cadzand-Bad&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07216.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07233.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We passed small harbour and followed cycling line in the direction of Het Zwin Nature Park to finally reach viewpoint where we could 
see in the distance place of residence for many bird species. You need to book a ticket to visit this park but the entrance is 
located on the other side on the enclosure from where we came from, actually it’s already Belgium. The border between the countries 
runs just through the nature reserve, actually the viewpoint we reached had a small concrete post indicating the border with Belgium.
We decided to rest on the beach nearby the viewpoint as it looked less crowded than close to the city center what you can see on the photo below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07236.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In was our last evening on the camping and last chance to see the sunset. Despite the many kilometers we already walked that day,
going to the beach again was a must. This evening the sky was almost completely clear and as most people already packed their things and headed home 
we didn’t meet many people on the beach. The local riding school took their horses on the beach, which looked so amazing with the sunset in the background! :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07244.edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunset in Nieuwvliet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07255.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day we just wanted to rest on the beach and catch some sun before heading back home. While running during the first evening,
I spotted big parking and a nice beach, just before the Waterdunen nature reserve and we decided that it should be a good spot to check out.
Imagine, my surprise when we ended up in the middle of naturist beach! During our previous trip the same thing happened and I have learned to 
look out for beaches marked as “nudistenstrand” … but apparently the is another term which is didn’t recognize “naaktstrand”. Well, 
there is still a long way ahead of me to really know this language :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We walked in the direction of nature reserve where the beach ends. The nature reserve consists of wetlands which are connected with the sea and it’s not possible to walk
along the coast there, you need to go around. After few hours on the beach, we decided to leave and when we were about to go back to the car we saw a small group
of people next to the water, taking a photos of something in the water. As I got closer with my camera, a seal put her head above the water
and cheerfully played with the water. That was very nice and unexpected attraction!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07281.edit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Beach close to Nieuwvliet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07287.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/DSC07292.edit.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We stayed at the camping site: &lt;a href=&quot;https://minicampingdecatshoek.nl/&quot;&gt;Camping De Catshoek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our walk to Cadzend was in total 24,5km (the map is showing less but I just draw it afterwards so it doesn’t take into
  account some extra walking in Cadzane).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Netherlands/Nieuwvliet/Screenshot from 2020-08-30 15-13-18.png&quot; alt=&quot;Walk to Cadzand-Bad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Car parking- 4.0 euro per day (1euro/h), Parkeerplaats Walendijk, the entrance leading to the beach bar “Van Houten” and
  naturist beach “naaktstrand”, important word to remember if you want to avoid it :p This part of the beach around
  Van Houten bar is marked with the board but you can just walk maybe 200m and you are you of the zone what we did as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2020/08/Zeeland-Cadzand/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu/en/travel/2020/08/Zeeland-Cadzand/</guid>
        
        <category>Netherlands</category>
        
        <category>beach</category>
        
        <category>sea</category>
        
        <category>dunes</category>
        
        <category>Cadzand-Bad</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
