<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Going beyond the known</title>
    <description>A travel blog by Monika Suchoszek.</description>
    <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 21:52:21 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 21:52:21 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cities in the area of Como Lake</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During 10 days spent in Italy, we visited quite a few cities (Como, Lecco, Milan, Morbegro, Sondrio), discovered amazing mountains, managed to rest one day on the shore of 
Como Lake (Colico) and tried countless times Italian ice cream, which by the way are for me the best in the world :) I will try to briefly highlight the possibilities each 
city offer tourists and give you also some practical tips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;como&quot;&gt;Como&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Como was our first stop, we spend there one intense day and I think it was enough to discover this city. We found a room located very close to the 
city gate tower (Porta Torre), a few minutes walking distance to the heart of the city, Piazza del Duomo with the impressive Cathedral of Como. To visit this cathedral 
you need to purchase a ticket (1 euro) which will be a donation to support the renovation of the church. It’s very low price for visiting such a stunning cathedral. I know 
literally anything about different architectural styles, italian painters but I was impressed with the sculptures, paintings and overall unique atmosphere. I like how the 
cathedral looks outside, with its white marble facade and splendid dome overlooking the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06520.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Como cathedra&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06537.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Como cathedra&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06508.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Como cathedra&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06531.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Como cathedra&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The cathedral in Como surprised us with its inside beauty!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06491.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Como cathedra&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Interesting monument in the shape of enormous hands in the park in front of the train station immediately caught our attention&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06556.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Volta Temple&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After walking through the narrow streets of the old part of the city, we finally reached the lake! That was a stunning view :) We walked on the pier to see the city from an other perspective.
Then we just started to walk along the shore, enjoying the impressive combination of water and mountains :) We quickly reached the park with the building looking like a greek
temple. It was a museum dedicated to scientist and inventor, Aleksandro Volta who was born in Como in XVIII century. His tools, equipment and experiments, which led to the invention of the electrical battery, can be 
seen here. The museum is relatively small and during our visit the exhibition on the first floor was closed. For those with
a keen interest in the history of science this is a good place to visit, others might want to skip this one (4euro entrance fee).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06565.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We walked along the shore of Como Lake until we reached Villa Olmo with small garden in front of it where we had a break in the shadow of the trees.
There was a bar and tiny, rocky beach nearby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While walking in Como, we noticed a cable car going up the hill. According to my map it was Brunate, which turned out to be a wonderful village on the mountainside above the lake.
My first obvious idea was to walk uphill instead of taking a cable car. Indeed, MAPS.ME had a path marked, leading to the top. We decided to try it out. On the wy there we found 
amazing view point just on one of the streets (Salita Peltrera), see next two photos below :) It wasn’t difficult to find a starting point of the path but it got worse really fast.
The path was full of rocks, narrow and with the weird smell, along some old fence. After a while we decided to come back since we were actually suspicious if we can ever get to 
the top this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06573.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;View of the city here was just amazing! You can clearly see Como's cathedral overlooking the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06576.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;You can see on the lake long pier with many boats tied to it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/small_DSC06582.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funicolare, the small cable car takes tourists to the peak of the hill from where you can admire a view of Como Lake and the city. However, for 
us the view was not spectacular, maybe we just didn’t find a right viewpoint. On the way back to funicolare we notice posters advertising a shuttle bus to the lighthouse with
 “the best view”, maybe that was the place to go. You can find there few cafes, souvenirs shops and small church so I think it’s still worth to go. 
 We had to wait like 30min in the queue to get down and it was horribly crowded and warm inside the cable car, yeah still high travel season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;morbegno---caspano---cadeipicco---dazio---morbegno&quot;&gt;Morbegno - Caspano - Cadeipicco - Dazio - Morbegno&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my boyfriend needed a rest day without hiking, taking a bus to the highest village nearby and walking all the way down back through vineyards sounded reasonable
enough that he agreed :) We took a bus from the bus station in Morbegno (next to the train station) to Caspano village. Bus ticket was 2.60 euro per person and we
bought it in the information office, just next to the bus station. The plan was to hike down through the villages but obviously not along the road which was extremely narrow 
and without any sidewalk. There was some path marked on MAPS.ME but we were really not sure how it looks in reality. We got out of the minivan close to the church San Bartolomeo in Caspano and started to walk through the village which was pretty nice with its narrow streets and old houses. 
It was so incredibly quiet and the view of the mountains put us in a good mood :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06876.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;We highly reccomend to check the view from the terrace in the back of the church, looks stunning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06883.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first walked on the road until the next village, Cadeipicco where we found a path leading to Dazio through the forest. It was marked with truly beautiful 
 wooden plate decorated with flowers :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06892.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06885.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dazio is much bigger and in front of the church we found a map with explanation of hiking trail in this area. It confirmed our belief that we should be able to hike all
 the way down without being on the dangerous road. Now we started to follow small metal plates with red and white stripes what you can see on the photo below. We are actually not sure
 what Colmen Trail means but it followed the path we took, almost until Morbegno. It wasn’t difficult to find a path, it crossed few times the main road and we didn’t meet any other
 tourists. Not demanding, very pleasant and relaxing walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/IMG_20190918_141604747.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/Screenshot from 2020-01-19 19-59-48.png&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Map shows the hiking trail we took, passing few villages and many fields with grapes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06898.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; The vineyards looked really nice since the grapes were almost ready to collect, it was late September so the time of harvest was coming soon :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06902.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/IMG_20190918_150743573.jpg&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06905.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06915.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ponte di Ganda, impresive bridge leading to the center of Morbegno&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sondrio&quot;&gt;Sondrio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather forecasts in the mountains were pretty bad and we had to look for another destination for the last day of our stay, before heading back to Milan.
We decided to check Sondrio, the capital city of the province. I noticed two castles on the map so we just decided to be spontaneous and check them out! The first one, 
Castle Grumello is located around 3km from the train station but last part, just couple hundreds meters through the vineyards was really steep (200m up!). First we
noticed closed gate and got really scared that we can’t enter. But we walked around and there was another entrance with the box where they kindly ask to put entrance fee
for renovation of the castle. Actually, there are only ruins of the castle but I think it’s really pretty place where you can sit on the bench and enjoy the surrounding
mountains and the view of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06930.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06933.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06940.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06952.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; From castle Grumello we walked to the second castle in the city, Masegra Castle, passing again many vineyards like everywhere in this region :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06968.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the view from castle Masegra in the centre of Sondrio and it was the only positive thing we can say about this castle ;) It didn’t resemble the castle at all,
just big building under repair so we quickly decided to head back to the city for well deserved pizza and ice cream  :D It’s very easy to visit the cities along the railway 
line, you can just relocate from one to another quite quickly and in fair price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;milan&quot;&gt;Milan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our knowledge of Milan was limited to two basic facts: it’s full of shops with luxury designer brands and its impressive cathedral attracts huge amount of tourists all year round!
To be honest, shopping is not my thing, especially with so many expensive shops around so I have no tips for you regarding shopping in Milan, sorry! :) We definitely wanted 
to visit famous cathedral and Sforza Castle, these were actually our only ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/G0789160.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Galery of Vittorio Emanuele II, full of designers shops like Versace, Louis Vitton, Dolce&amp;amp;Gabbana, Gucci, Armani. It's the oldest shopping mall in Italy, looks very elegant with
  glass roof and many paintings and sculptures on the walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06991.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Cathedral in Milan is one of the biggest in Italy, indeed really impressive! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC06999.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC07030.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/G0819182.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The rooftop of the cathedral was really amazing with enormous number of sculpture and adornments but we would enjoy it even more if the half of it would
 not be in the scaffold. As you can see great spot for selfies :D &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC07021.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;View from the rooftop of cathedral, monument Vittoro Emanuele II visible in the middle of the square &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC07060.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Columns of nave are really high! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC07052.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ray of light coming through the stained glass window looks always very special inside every church &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Como/DSC07084.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Sforza Castle (XVth century)visible from Sempione Park, just behind the castle. Nice place to relax from the hustle of the city :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not really sure what to think about this city. The cathedral is definitely really impressive and worth to visit but the overall style of the city didn’t attract out attention.
Maybe we should visit the museum in the castle but we are not big history enthusiasts, more like a plants/animals/nature enthusiast (Monika) and technology/robots/space (Sebastian) enthusiast :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Entrance fee to cathedral and rooftop by stairs (DUOMO PASS STAIRS) - 13 euro per person but if you want to use elevator then higher fee applies.
  Tickets can be bought in the office next to the Cathedral&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Train from Colico to Milan - 7.30 per person&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since we had very early flight connection next day, we spend the night in &lt;strong&gt;Gallarate&lt;/strong&gt; assuming that it would be easier to get from there to the airport. 
The train is only around 25min from Gallarate to the Airport but it runs unfortunately only unce per hour (modern and comfortable train, 6euro per person).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/10/Como-Morbegno-Sondrio/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/10/Como-Morbegno-Sondrio/</guid>
        
        <category>italy</category>
        
        <category>Como</category>
        
        <category>Sondrio</category>
        
        <category>Morbegno</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Another destination from Lecco, Monte Coltignone</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After hiking to &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2019/09/Monte-Resegone/&quot;&gt;Monte Resegone&lt;/a&gt;, a day trip around the Como lake by 
ferry, it was finally time for another hike, this time to Monte Coltignone. It was supposed to be 
tough and it certainly was. Three kilometers and 1000m altitude gain, this can’t be good :) 
First we took a bus to Laorca (more details in the section practical info) where we started the hike. 
You can reach the peak by two trails: one passing Medale and one, easier but longer route, which is 
also the most popular. We don’t like to walk the same way up and down the peak and obviously I wanted to 
scramble a bit more and that was guaranteed by choosing the first option, Santiero G.E.R trail (number 59).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06621.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Lecco, for me the city itself was not particularly special but the surrounding mountains added a lot 
of beauty to this place. Como has its beautiful cathedral, Varenna its castle with a spectacular view, 
Bellagio its expensive shops and Lecco has spectacular mountains but you need to put in more effort (and 
get more sweaty :p) to enjoy them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06623.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/IMG_105527361.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06831.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole way up was really steep! Except the first couple hundreds meters when we passed a few houses before entering the forest. As we made our way up the mountain, the path didn’t get flatter even for a moment and our calves were still really sore after the previous hike. So we were walking slowly but steady to finally reach the wooden sign indicating route number 57 to Monte San Martino and route nr 59 to Monte Coltignone (Santiero G.E.R). We took a short break there, looking at the peak Corno Medale, which was really close to us (we think there is no touristic path to this peak). Now we were on more exposed terrain, with rocks to climb, chains to hold. At one point we passed a tiny cavern with a Madonna statue, right before the most difficult part of the hike :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06833.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06836.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06838.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06841.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite it being a very nice, sunny day, the visibility was not great. We couldn’t clearly see the lake and distant peaks. When we reached the top of the mountain we were quite surprised to see a big forest on the other side, after this whole steep part. So basically you have a nice view but only on one side of the mountain, the one we have chosen to get to the peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06845.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06850.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06847.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06851.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monte Coltignone looks totally different from the other side which can be reached by wide, easy path from the shelter S.E.L Rocca-Locatelli in Piani Resinelli (you can park your car there). Between the peak and the shelter we could admired a stunning peaks of Grigna massif in a distance (first photo below). On the way back we passed Casa Museo di Villa Gerosa, Rifugio S.E.L Rocca-Locatelli in Piani Resinelli which was unfortunatley closed. Next, we followed the stream Torrente Calolden where the path got steeper and really rocky until we finally reached Laorca village again. The path we took to go down from Monte Coltignone was much easier, of course steep and exhausting but not dangerous (no exposed terrain or chains).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06854.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06855.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/DSC06862.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final sprint to catch the next bus and we were back on our way to Lecco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We came to Lecco from Como S.Giovanni by train (4.80 euro per person) which was the main means of transportation used by us to travel between the cities in Italy. It’s easy to find a schedule on the websites, usually we bought our ticket in the ticket machines, at the counter at the train station (Trenitalia) or in the newspaper shops (Trenord). The shops have a sticker from Trenord in the shop window if they sell them. You can’t buy them in the machines from Trenitalia. Check both links &lt;a href=&quot;http://m.trenord.it/site-lite/index.html&quot;&gt;Trenord&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trenitalia.com/en.html&quot;&gt;Trenitalia&lt;/a&gt;. In Lecco you can buy a 12 rides bus ticket for 13 euro (single ride is 2 euro) and use it for more then one person at the same time (just need to validate it more times). The ticket is valid for 90min and within this time you can make changes so it’s pretty good deal. Schedule of the buses you can find here &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lineelecco.it/tpl/orari-invernali/&quot;&gt;Busses in Lecco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started the hike in Laorca where we got by bus number 7 (bus number 1 also goes there, we used on the way back bacause unfortunately the connections are really infrequent so better check it before). The bus stop was called Laorca Asilo on &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.me/&quot;&gt;MAPS.ME&lt;/a&gt;, we decided to track our position to press STOP button on the bus in the right moment. It worked really well and when we got out there, first we followed the street Via Giuseppe Baruffaldi (on the corner of this street was a bus stop in the oposite direction) until we reached the church, then Via alla Grigna until the parking where we found an information board, pointing to the begining of the path to Monte Coltignone. See the whole hike on the map below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/Screenshot 21-46-31.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also very nice and easy hike to Monte Barro. One evening I did a run on the slopes of the mountain. The view of the lake and the city was really nice and should be even better from the peak. After you cross the bridge, Ponte Azzone Visconti, just walk to the other side of the street and there will be a tiny street a little bit to the left, Via San Michele, with the sign indicated the time needed to reach the peak (around 2h). Very nice for running because the rocks are not loosy so I felt pretty comfortable running there. There is also running/cycling path along the lake which I checked on the way back (see the map below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/MonteColtignone/Screenshot 19-13-51.1.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Coltignone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2019 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/09/Monte-Coltignone/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/09/Monte-Coltignone/</guid>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>italy</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Varenna-Bellagio-Lierna by ferry</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One lazy day designated for sightseeing between two days of demanding hiking was the perfect idea! Ok … this day ultimately was not so lazy with 16km of walking ;-)
Varenna was our first destination that day, one of the top rated towns on the shores of Lake Como. Immediately after arriving we noticed a really long queue in front of the ferry.
The first thing we did was buying tickets and actually getting some information about the ferry schedule which was very difficult to find online (scan of the ferry schedule
in practical info section on the bottom of the post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t know exactly what we should see in this town. I just noticed on &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.me/&quot;&gt;MAPS.ME&lt;/a&gt; (our favorite app with offline maps) a castle above the town and thought
there was going to be a nice view from there. I was right ! Just look at the pictures below. You have to buy a ticket to enter the castle which is in ruins now but nicely maintained with 
“ghost” sculptures scattered around the place and few birds of prey sitting in the small olive garden where you can have a rest in the refreshing shadow. The best spot for a great
view is the tower of the castle but unfortunately there were some very annoying insects attacking people so we could really barely enjoy the view and take photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06732.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06738.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06756.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06758.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06764.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06769.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06772.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colorful houses, narrow streets, lots of flowers, a breathtaking view from the castle…the beauty of this town charmed us! :) However there was still a lot of sightseeing waiting
for us in the next village. Before lunch we took a ferry to Bellagio, a must to visit while travelling in this region of Italy. The ferry took us there in around 15 min and it was really charming to see 
Varenna disappearing in the distance.  The first thing you’ll see while getting close to the shore are Bellagio’s nice, big hotels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06804.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06807.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06814.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This small city is always really crowded, full of expensive shops and art galleries, shopping lovers will definitely feel satisfied there! ;)  We had a really italian lunch, carbonara
and of course mandatory ice cream :) Next, we just walked through the park and along the shore of Como lake where we stumbled upon an exhibition with old motorcycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06785.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06797.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06799.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06817.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06820.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06782.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06818.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06821.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06823.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got quite tired in the afternoon and decided to head back to Lierna where the plan was to lay dawn on the beach and chill until sunset and then take a train back to Lecco.
The ferry left from Bellagio on time, however, it was really tricky to find a right spot to wait. There are a lot of people waiting and the screens show only the most popular connections, which left
many people confused (our connection was served by a boat, not a ferry). The beach in Lierna was not very nice, really rocky and narrow. A few days later we discovered much better one in another 
village, Collico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06825.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.castellodivezio.it/EN/home-en.html&quot;&gt;Castello di Vezio&lt;/a&gt;  - entrance fee 4 euro per person, check their website for opening hours.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ferry ticket from Varenna to Lierna with a change in Bellagio - 4,60 euro per person&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/DSC06776.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ferry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/IMG_20200112_schedule1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Schedule1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Ferry/IMG_20200112_schedule2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Schedule2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Train tickets:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Lecco - Varenna 2,90 euro per person. We made a mistake here and bought tickets on the train which cost us extra 4 euro 
per person! Note that this fee doesn’t apply when statring from a station without a ticket machine, for example Lierna&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Lierna - Lecco 2,50 euro per person&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2019 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/09/Ferry/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/09/Ferry/</guid>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        <category>sightseeing</category>
        
        <category>italy</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Trekking na szczyt Monte Resegone</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lecco, miasto w  którym zatrzymaliśmy się na kilka dni, okazało się być wspaniałą baza wypadową dla miłośników pieszych wędrówek. Położenie miasta nad samym jeziorem Como
(południowy kraniec jeziora) zapewnia niesamowite połączenie gór i błękitu wody widocznej w oddali. Moglibyśmy tam zostać dłużej, miasto oferuje możliwość wielu jednodniowych 
wycieczek w pobliskie góry. Nasza gospodyni w Lecco wiedziała dużo o pobliskich górach i zasugerowała nam dwa, najbardziej wymagające 
szlaki w okolicy a my z radością zaakceptowaliśmy jej sugestie :D Z racje tego, że prognoza pogody na kolejny dzień była wspaniała, postanowiliśmy nie czekać i kolejnego dnia wyruszyć
na szlak prowadzący do Monte Resegone (1875m). To nie dystans nas przerażał, ale różnica wysokości do pokonania, około 1500m mozolnego podchodzenia pod górę :O Nasz trekking
zaczęliśmy w dzielicy miasta zwanej Acquate i po dotarciu do &lt;strong&gt;szlaku nr 1&lt;/strong&gt;, podążaliśmy nim aż do samego szczytu ze schroniskiem Luigi Azzoni w pobliżu. Szlak ten zaczyna się w 
dzielicy Versasio u podnóża kolejki linowej (więcej o niej w sekcji praktyczne informacje), najpierw prowadzi przyjemną szeroką, skalistą ścieżką przez las. Potem naszym oczom 
ukazał się pierwszy widok na miasto Lecco i jezioro w oddali (przy niewielkiej grupie domów Frazione Costa) a po chwili doszliśmy do schroniska Rifugio Antonio Stoppani, które jeszcze
było zamknięte. Ścieżka jest cały czas dobrze oznaczony (patrz praktyczne informacje), jednak przecina ją wiele innych szlaków, w tym rowerowych MTB oraz prowadzących na via ferraty,
więc trzeba uważnie patrzeć, aby nie skręcić w złą ścieżkę, co nam sie również przytrafiło.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06629.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nie mogłam się doczekać, aż wyjdziemy powyżej linii lasu na bardziej skaliste tereny :) Oczywiście bardzo ucieszyłam się na widok łańcuchów, bo to zapowiadało bardziej interesującą dla mnie
część szlaku, z ekspozycją i pięknymi formacjami skalnymi i nie zawiodłam się! Chmury, które były widoczne poniżej nas dopełniały ten niesamowity widok. W wielu miejscach używaliśmy rąk,
aby pokonać odcinki skalne (łańcuchy często nie były zbyt przydatne, ponieważ skała była sucha, pogoda bardzo dobra ale w deszczowych warunkach na pewno będą niezbędne!). Z pewnością
nie każdy będzie czuł się na tym odcinku komfortowo, część turystów poruszała się bardzo niepewnie, ale ze względu na to, że przez 7lat wspinaczka była bardzo ważną częścią mojego życia,
czuje się wspaniale w skalnym terenie. Slyszeliśmy od naszej gospodyni, że podczas załamania pogody dosłownie dwa tygodnie przed naszym przyjazdem, ekipy ratunkowe z użyciem
helikoptera musiały kilkukrotnie interweniować w okolicach tego szlaku.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06646.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06663.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06682.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06677.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06692.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06699.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Widok na samym szczycie był naprawdę cudowny, zwłaszcza kiedy chmury rozeszły się i zobaczyliśmy jezioro Como oraz bardziej odległe szczyty
w oddali. Na szczycie znajduje się kilkumetrowej wysokości metalowy krzyż oraz tablice pomagające zidentifikować szczyty widoczne na horyzoncie
wraz z ich wysokościami. A szczytów widocznych jest naprawdę mnóstwo, ponad 30, więc zajęło mi chwilę aby przeczytać wszystkie nazwy :p W
schronisku można kupić kanapki, napoje a nawet proste dania makaronowe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_121345847.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-45&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W drodze powrotnej zdecydowaliśmy się wypróbować inny szlak prowadzący do Piani d’Erna, &lt;strong&gt;nr 10&lt;/strong&gt;, który prowadzi niedaleko innych szczytów takich
jak Punta Stoppani, Manzoni oraz Dente. Okazało się, że jest on dużo mniej popularną opcją. Spotkaliśmy na nim niewiele osób, nagle cała okolica znalazła
się w gęstej mgle i widoczność była bardzo niewielka. Mnóstwo dużych, luźnych kamieni bardzo nas spowolniło, do tego łańcuchy i po jakimś czasie czuliśmy 
zmęczenie a właściwie flustrację, że ta uciążliwa kamienista ścieżka nie ma końca! :) Jeśli nie lubicie chodzić tymi samymi szlakami w obie strony to być może
lepiej będzie wejść szlakiem nr 10 a zejść szlakiem nr 1, który ma zdecydowanie mniej luźnych kamieni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_134055691.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06705.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_134052323.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06703.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Praktyczne informacje:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeśli obawiasz się, że być może taka wędrówka będzie zbyt wymagająca, ale wciąż jesteś ciekaw niesamowitych widoków, dobrym pomysłem będzie 
wjechanie kolejką linową do Piani d’Erna i rozpoczęcie trekkingu z tego miejsca. To zdecydowanie zmniejszy dystans i różnice wysokości jaką 
mamy do pokonanie, teraz będzie to ok 550m w górę na szczyt Monte Resegone (ale będzie to najbardziej spektakularny odcinek!). Na mapie poniżej
zaznaczona jest trasa naszej wędrówki i wysokości jakie pokonaliśmy. Wejście na szczyt zajęło nam prawie 4h i prawie tyle samo potrzebowaliśmy aby zejść w dół 
(więcej krótkich postojów). Nie śpieszyliśmy się, wyjście wcześnie rano zawsze gwarantuje zapas czasu, który można wykorzystać na podziwianie
piękna gór :) Jak zwykle, aplikacja MAPS.ME była bardzo przydatna, aby sprawdzić naszą lokalizację oraz, co najważniejsze, znaleźć krótsze dojście do
szlaku z naszego pokoju w Lecco. Aplikacja o tyle użyteczna, że można po prostu pobrać mapę danego regionu w który się wybieramy i używać mapy offline
(ponad 100 krajów z mapami w ofercie!). Ta aplikacja pomogła nam bardzo podczas 10 dniowego trekingu w Górach Atlas w Maroku, gdzie oznaczenia szlaków
praktycznie nie istnieją. Zdecydowanie polecamy aplikację, gdy podróżujecie zarówno w górach jak i w miastach. &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/maps-me-offline-map-nav/id510623322&quot;&gt;MAPS.ME app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/Screenshot 21-47-52.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Szlak oznaczony był bardzo wyraźnie czerwono-biało-żółtymi paskami z numerem 1 umiejscowionym po środku. Nie ma obaw, że się zgubimy, wystarczy zwracać uwagę
na oznaczenia znajdujące się głównie na kamieniach, czasem drzewach. Na szlaku spotkaliśmy dosyć dużo ludzi, w znacznej większości Włochów, albo jest to popularna
okolica wśród mieszkańców tego kraju albo fakt, że była to sobota i pogoda była cudowna, przyciągnął tłumy wędrowców :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podczas tej wędrówki używaliści naszym górskich butów biegowych (Sebastian- Salomon Speedcross 
4 oraz Monika- Salomon SENSE RIDE) ale wysokie buty górskie zdecydowanie są tutaj rekomendowane, mnóstwo miejsc wyeksponowanych, ostrych kamieni. Jesteśmy przyzwyczajeni
do trekkingu w lżejszym obuwiu a poza tym takie obuwie używaliśmy podczas całego wyjazdu, zwiedzając miasta co w ciężkich butach górskich byłoby niemożliwe.
Jadąc na dłuższy trekking, gdzie nosimy ciężkie plecami i śpiwmy w namiocie czy schroniskach, bierzemy wyższe skórzane buty. Najlepiej wybrać się w sprawdzonych butach,
to nie miejsce na eksperymenty ;-) Podczas deszczowej pogody może tam być bardzo niebezpiecznie, mnóstwo odcinków skalnych z ekspozycją, także obuwie musi wtedy
być dostosowane do panujących warunków.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_090851298.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Byliśmy zaskoczeni jak wiele imprez miało miejsce w ten weekend w Lecco. Oprócz kilkudniowego spotkanie na temat zmian klimatycznych, któremu towarzyszyły
liczne prelekcje oraz warsztaty (niestety po włosku), odbył się również w mieście bieg z przeszkodami. Wracając z Monte Resegone zauważyliśmy uczestników pokonujących 
przeszkody takie jak: rzut młodkiem do celu, przeskok przez wysoką ścianę oraz bardziej wspinaczkowe zadanie z linami. Sami uczestniczyliśmy w kilku takich biegach w 
Niemczech (Tough Mudder) oraz Belgii (Iron Viking, 42km i ponad 100 przeszkód!) i z pewnością uważamy to za niesamowitą przygodę, szczególnie, gdy startujemy z grupą 
przyjaciół :) Sprawdź szczegóły biegu tutaj &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scigamatt.com/site/index.php/&quot;&gt;Scigamatt in Lecco&lt;/a&gt;, być może będzie to powód, aby wybrać się na wakacje w te rejony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06718.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//pl/podroze/2019/09/Trekking-na-szczyt-Monte-Resegone/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//pl/podroze/2019/09/Trekking-na-szczyt-Monte-Resegone/</guid>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>wlochy</category>
        
        
        <category>podroze</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A day hike to Monte Resegone</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lecco, a small city located on the southern tip of Lake Como turned out to be a fantastic base for hiking lovers. 
We could have actually stayed here longer than we did as we still had plenty of ideas for day hikes or just regular 
sightseeing. More about the city itself in the next post :) Our host in Lecco knew a lot about the mountains 
surrounding this region and suggested us two of the most demanding hikes and we enthousiastically followed her 
ideas :D The weather predictions were really good so we decided not to wait long and do the most demanding hike to 
Monte Resegone (1875m) the next day. It was not the distance which made this hike challenging but the altitude 
gain of around 1500m. We started the hike from the place where we stayed in Lecco (Acquate district) and we made 
our way up to hiking path number 1 which we followed to rifugio Luigi Azzoni near the peak of Monte Resegone. This 
path starts at the bottom of the cable car in Versasio and it first leads through the forest on a nice, wide,rocky 
path. Then it passes a small group of houses (Frazione Costa) and a shelter Rifugio Antonio Stoppani. From there we 
could already admire the stunning view of Como lake and Lecco city. The path was clearly marked with red-white-yellow stripes with number one written in the middle. Marks were placed on the rocks or trees, so no worries to get lost (of course you need to pay attendion on the crossings with other paths e.g. with MTB trails or paths leading to via ferratas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06629.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was eager to reach the higher parts of the trail, above the tree-line and enjoy the impressive rock formations. I got super excited when I saw the first chains, that meant the path was about to get more interesting! :D In many places it was necessary to use hands, it was more like a scrambling than normal hike but these parts I just loved. Not everyone would be so excited (including my boyfriend) but I was climbing for 7 years so that part of me will always love the feeling of rocks and being in the exposed terrain. We had amazing weather but be aware that this path is difficult and many accidents happens there when it’s icy or rainy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06646.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06663.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06682.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06677.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06692.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06699.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view from the peak was really cool, mountains all around, when clouds moved out of the way we could see distant peaks and of course Como lake which, all together, create a spectacular experience! We stood there for a while admiring the mountain peaks. With over 30 peaks on the horizon, I found it really useful to look at the metal plate with points to all off them indicating their names and heights. There is a shelter next to the peak so you can grab some snacks, sandwich or even a simple hot meal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_121345847.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-45&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to try another hiking path and go back to Piani d’Erna by trail number 10 (passing a few peaks, Punta Stoppani, Manzoni &amp;amp; Dente) which is less popular and unfortunately had way more loose rocks which actually makes it quite difficult to walk down as there was a high probability of falling down. Our muscles were constantly tense and got really tired after the first difficult part with some chains and falling rocks. Also, it got very foggy, the visibility was really low as shown on the photos below. If you really don’t like to do twice the same path then I would recommend to go up to the peak by the route number 10 and go down with number 1 which is still difficult but has less loosy rocks which are especially annoying while going down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_134055691.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06705.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_134052323.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06703.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are afraid that this is gonna be too much for you but you still want to enjoy the spectacular views, then taking cable car to Piani d’Erna is a good idea. It will shorten the hike meaningfully, then it’s “only” about 550m of altitude gain to Monte Resegone. On the map below you can see our hike and the distance. It took us almost 4h to get there and almost the same (including breaks) to get back. We were not rushing, just enjoying the day. As always, navigation app MAPS.ME was very useful to double check our position and to find a shortcut to our room in Lecco. You can just simply download maps of the region where you stay for an offline use (maps of more than 100 countries in the world ready to download!). It worked even in Marocco when we did 10 days hike in Atlas Mountains where the paths were not really marked and difficult to find. We hightly reccomend this app for hiking but also for sightseeing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/maps-me-offline-map-nav/id510623322&quot;&gt;MAPS.ME app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/Screenshot 21-47-52.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path was clearly marked with red-white-yellow colors and number one written in the middle. No worries to get lost, just look carefully for the marks on the rocks or trees. It is a popular destination for Italians and we met many of them on the hiking trail (or maybe it was crowded because it was Saturday). We did the hike in our trail running shoes (Salomon Speedcross 4 and Salomon SENSE RIDE) but high-cut hiking boots would be definitely recommended here. We are used to hike with lighter types of shoes and it works for us. Use gear you are comfortable with, this is not the place for experimentation ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/IMG_090851298.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many activities happening in Lecco that weekend, besides the climate change meeting, there was an obstacle run which took place the day we went to Monte Resegone. On the way back we saw the participants struggeling to cross a big wall and climbing an obstacle with many ropes. We participated a few times in obstacle runs in Germany and Belgium and we highly recommend this kind of activity as a great adventure :) Check this link &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scigamatt.com/site/index.php/&quot;&gt;Scigamatt in Lecco&lt;/a&gt; in case you want to try something unusual during your next holidays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Italy/Monte_Resegone/DSC06718.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Monte Resegone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/09/Monte-Resegone/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/09/Monte-Resegone/</guid>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>italy</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A trip to Little Switzerland</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Visiting Berdorf in Luxemburg? Why not! We couldn’t miss our chance to finally check one of the options for a weekend trip when you live in Belgium. The initial idea was to do the whole Mullerthal trail route 2 which is around 37km. However, life is unpredictable and we had to modify our plans a little bit. Since we left Leuven on Saturday morning and arrived to Berdorf (the starting point of a trek) at 10.30 am there was not enough time to do the complete route so on the way we decided to skip one loop and took a shortcut to the next village. The first part (around 6km) from Berdorf to Mullerthal led along big rocky walls, the further we got from the car parking, the quieter it got with less and less hikers on the way. The large, high rocks situated close to each other started to create narrow passages, darker and colder inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05267.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;The part from Berdorf to Mullerthal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05277.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;The part from Berdorf to Mullerthal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05278.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-50&quot; alt=&quot;Narrow passage between big rocks&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mullerthal village offers a camping site, some places to buy drinks and fast food. We passed the village quite fast, constantly following wooden poles with the name of the route (and distance to the next village). After some time we saw Schiessentümpel Cascade, famous waterfalls atracting many tourists but I need to admit, after having seen waterfalls in Iceland and Laos, they are rather small ;) The shape and style of the wooden bridge above made a bigger impression on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05295.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;The part from Berdorf to Mullerthal2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit further, close to the viewpoint Burgkapp, we had a chance to shorten our hike and go straight ahead to the village Consdorf, skipping the loop to the south and cutting off a few km. We passed Burgkapp, La Pineda camping site, Consdorf (there is a bakery close to the church) to finally reach Scheidgen where we picked up Mullerthal trail route 2 again. The part from here to Echternach was a bit borring. Beautiful, old forest but less groups of rocks which you can explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05317.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Berdorf viewpoint&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05316.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-45&quot; alt=&quot;Berdorf viewpoint&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view of village Echternach where we had a dinner and ice cream :) Visiting this touristic place required us to walk down a steep path to the village and come back the same way what means steep uphill parts as well but it was worth it. On the photo below you can clearly see St. Willibrord Basilica, which dominates the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05325.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Village Echternal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day we explored the area nearby our camping in Berdorf. Amazing viewpoints where you can admire the hills sourrounding the area are a great spot for many tourists to relax. Numerous narrow passages between the rocks attract children with head lights, exploring them without any fear. We really got lost amongst narrow corridors, it feels like being in a labyrinth! Good shoes are highly recommended since the rocks and steps can be quite slippery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05378.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Berdorf viewpoint&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05389.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Berdorf viewpoint&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05396.JPG&quot; class=&quot;column-45&quot; alt=&quot;Narrow passage between big rocks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area has a lot to offer not only for hikers, runners or cyclists but also for sport climbers! Around 1km from the camping Martbusch you can find this little but very interesting area with sandstone rock. Most of the climbing routes are rated between 5 and 6. The beautiful forest surrounding this spot makes it colder, something every climber appreciates during the hot summer :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05414.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Climbing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mullerthal trail route 2 - 31km, we skipped around 7km part in south, taking a shortcut from Consdorfer Millen parking to Scheidgen where we again started to follow Mullerthal trail 2 until Berdorf, see the map below for details&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/Map from runkeeper 2019-08-06.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stayed at the Camping Belle-Vue 2000 (around 8euro/person, steel fire bowl and portion of wood - 12 euro) in Berdorf. There are many camping sites in the area of Mullerthal trail route 2 so it is definitely possible to split the whole track into a few parts and explore the area a bit more. There are really plenty of places to check, beautiful rock formations, view points and caves which are difficult to really explore if you do the whole trek in one day like we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Luxembourg/DSC05353.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Village Echternal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.campingbelle-vue2000.com/&quot;&gt;Camping Belle-Vue in Berdorf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/08/luxembourg/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2019/08/luxembourg/</guid>
        
        <category>hiking</category>
        
        <category>luxembourg</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lao New Year's Celebrations</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Pi Mai Lao, celebration of the New Year in Laos during the hottest part of the year was an 
unexpected event we gladly joined  :D Officially it is a 3-day celebration but in some cities 
like Vientian or Luang Prabang it can last over a week. During the New Year celebrations the entrance 
to all temples is free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That day we decided to visit Pha That Luang, a large gold-covered stupa; a national monument and the 
symbol of Vientian. We again used the public transportation to get to this part of the city (bus nr 
10 from the crossing near the central bus station, we found the correct bus stop based on the map 
with information on the central bus station).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03309.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Buddhist temple nearby the stupa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03284.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enormous statue of reclining Buddha&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03302.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Large gold-covered stupa, the symbol of Vientian&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In front of each temple, Buddha statues are placed in easy accessible places so devotes can pour 
scented water with flower petals over the statues. It symbolizes washing last-year’s sins away since 
the first day of celebrations is the last day of the old year. Everyone wants to enter the New Year 
without any sins. Then, they collect the water which runs over the Buddha and take it home to pour over 
other members of the family as a blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03298.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;In the front of the main entrance the table with many small Buddha statues is prepared for devotes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03306.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Everyone was dressed in a very special way, floral shirts for men and beautiful long dresses for women&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03324.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;As you can see, the jade Buddha statues wear various robes for different seasons of the year (covering the statue at the different levels)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03204.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;On every street you could buy offerings for this special days composed of banana leaves and flowers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03196.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;According to the tradition people buy gift baskets with food or cosmetics for the elderly members of their families&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03326.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Some people sell birds in the bamboo cages, intended to be set them free as a symbol of a prosperity and good luck (we have seen a banners trying to discourage tourists from taking part in it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03316.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Beautiful, long dresses are a very important aspect of the celebrations :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/DSC03329.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Since it was the hottest part of the year, people were pouring the whole buckets of water on each other, perfect way to cool down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already around a lunchtime people started to pour water on each other and few hours later all the streets 
turned to a giant battle field. Pickup trucks, full of people and buckets of water were appearing more 
and more often on the street so it was a time to switch from a normal camera to our waterproof GoPro :) 
We noticed in front of most houses inflatable swimming pools to cool down and owners waiting with hoses, 
water pistols and buckets to pour water over the pedestrians. No one could stay dry that day :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/GOPR8182.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The owners of our guesthouse prepared delicious food, beers, lao-lao (Laotian rice whisky), loud music and a lot of water to make sure no-one who passed by  remained dry :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/GOPR8206.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Along the promenade there were few stages where we could listen a Laotian music, dance in a foam or underneath the sprinklers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/NewYear/GOPR8233.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Laotian techno party which turned into Laotian pop concert a bit later. Probably some well-known group since everyone was singing along with the band :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day of the celebrations is a day to relax, the one between the last day of an old year 
and the first day of a New Year (third day of the celebrations). We noticed that the owners of the 
guesthouse where we stayed were “very tired” in the morning :D We took the bus to Vang Vieng, this wasn’t 
easy since only one company was operating during a holiday (the price was also somewhat higher than normal).
It was difficult to stay dry during the next days, there were always many kids along the road, waiting 
to pour water on passers. Better get a good waterproof bag* for all your documents, electronics and money! 
You can buy them actually on the every corner of the street. Walking from the bus station to our 
guesthouse,  which was about one kilometer, was a very tricky task as we didn’t want to get wet. We had 
to basically look around each corner of the street and check if it was safe to go there. Being in a tuk-tuk 
was not helpful either, since whenever the tuk-tuks with tourists stopped, there were some kids with water 
running towards them to get everyone inside soaking wet :O&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, to survive the Laotian new Year celebration, get a waterproof bag, and feel again like a 
child and enjoy pouring water on the others! :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical info:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bus ticket to Pha That Luang (bus number 10) - 4k per person, one way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bus ticket to Vang Vieng (minivan) - 60k Kip per person&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a waterproof bag ! It wil come in handy quite often if you are there in the wet season.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2018/11/Lao-New_Year/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2018/11/Lao-New_Year/</guid>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
        <category>laos</category>
        
        <category>festival</category>
        
        <category>urban</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Buddha Park in Vientian</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Buddha Park, located 26km from the city center, was our main destination for that day. We decided to use 
the public transportation to get there and it turned out to be an easy and cheap solution.  First you need 
to go to the central bus station which is divided into two parts: CBS1 and CBS2. You can easily find an 
information boards about bus routes and prices with the description in English. It was necessary to get 
bus number 14 from the CBS2 part of the bus station and after around 40 min of a bus ride we arrived to 
Buddha Park. All tourists on the bus were going there and the women selling tickets on the bus very loudly 
shouted the name of the stop and took care that all tourists are out :D The bus also passes the immigration 
office next to the Friendship Bridge on the border with Thailand. Our visit in Buddha Park took around 
1,5 hour and we caught the bus back on the other side of the street where we got off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buddha Park is a sculpture park with more than 200 religious statues made of concrete. A huge dome-shaped 
sculpture consist of three levels: the lowest showing hell, then middle one is an earth and heaven on the 
top with nice view over the whole park. Huge demon’s mouth are the entrance to this scary place. It is 
really narrow inside and probably always very crowded. For me it was bizarre place, especially after 
visiting hell :) The park was created by monk who studied both Buddhism and Hinduism. That’d why this place 
is full of Buddha images, Hindu gods, demons and animals common in both beliefs. You can easily buy there a 
snack or chill out in cafe nearby the Mekong river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/DSC03214.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Enormous reclining Buddha (40 meters long) is one of the biggest attractions of the park&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/DSC03228.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/DSC03211.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/DSC03239.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/DSC03210.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/IMG_20180413_110811403.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/IMG_20180413_111236224_LL.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The way to the view terrace was through a dark hell :O&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/DSC03249.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Panoramic view of the Buddha Park&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After nice lunch in the city center we walked to check Patuxai, a war monument, victory gate surrounded
by a nice green park with fountain. It is possible to walk to the top of the monument and admire the 
view of the city. That’s exactly what we did :) On the way to the top you can buy souvenirs and clothes 
from the local vendors. The monument inside is not well maintained, many bird nests destroyed the 
paintings on the ceiling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/DSC03264.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/BuddhaPark/DSC03266.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical information:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bus ticket to Buddha Park - 6 000 Kip per person, one way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Entrance ticket to Buddha Park - 15 000 Kip per person&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Entrance to Patuxai - 3 000 Kip per person&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2018 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2018/10/Buddha-Park/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2018/10/Buddha-Park/</guid>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
        <category>laos</category>
        
        <category>urban</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vientian, capital with an endless number of temples</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;First something about how we got here. In a nutshell, after a short boat ride from Don Det to Nakasong, 
we took a bus to Pakse where we were supposed to have a lunch break. Instead of this, the bus stopped 
on the side of the road and we had to change to another bus. Six of us ended up this way on a local bus 
without anyone speaking English. For the next 7h we were stuck on the bus without any breaks. During the 
bus ride a group of women entered the bus a few times with chicken, fish and meat skewers sold as a snack. 
We arrived to Thathek late in the evening and decided to buy immediately something to eat since we were 
really hungry after the whole day without almost any food (we were not brave enough to buy sth on the bus). 
Around the bus station were many hostels but it was already dark so we just wanted to find something 
closeby and go to sleep. Luckily after checking few options, we found a guesthouse with a clean room and a 
good price :) In the morning we took a VIP bus at 9:15 which was really comfortable! This time we had a few 
breaks to use a toilette and to buy some food. After 6.5 hour we arrived at Southern Bus Station in Vientian, 
12km from the city center. It was necessary again to take a tuk-tuk, drivers inside the bus station where asking 
60 000 Kip for the ride, we managed to knock the price down to 30 000 Kip negotiating with drivers waiting just 
outside the bus station. We decided to stay in Vientian next 3 days to celebrate the Lao New Year in the capital 
of the country :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vientian has a great variety of Buddhist temples and we spend the first day wandering around a downtown in 
search of our favourite one. There is no entrance fee to the most of them, with the exception of Phra Keo 
and Wat Sisaket. Interior of the first temple is now a small museum with Lao religious art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03165.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03172.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Phra Keo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second one on the contrary was quite unique, characterized by walls full of tiny Buddha statues (thousands 
of them!). Along the wall surrounding the main temple, there was also a long line of seated big Buddhas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03187.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Wat Sisaket&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03182.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Buddha gallery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We noticed that almost all temples were decorated with snake like creatures which are called naga and are believed 
to protect the city and live in Mekong river. All temples were very clean and decorated with colorful bands and 
flags for upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;/en/travel/2018/11/Lao-New_Year/&quot;&gt;New Year celebrations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03261.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Naga guarding the entrance to the temple&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03135.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03142.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Inside one of a temple. You are usually welcome to enter and have a look, though taking of your shoes 
is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03176.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;More gold statues of Buddha next to the temple&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a late lunch and a break to cool down we headed off to &lt;a href=&quot;http://copelaos.org/&quot;&gt;COPE center&lt;/a&gt;. Laos, 
similar to Cambodia has his own dark period in the history which still has an influence on people’s lives. During 
9 years of the Vietnam War (1964 - 73), more than 270 million cluster bombs were dropped all over the country. 
Up to 30% of them did not detonated and many villages are still threatened with unexploded bombs. Despite the 
effort of  bomb clearance every year many people (around 100) dies and almost half of the victims are children. 
The bombs usually explode  when people are farming, cooking on fire or when children unawares of the danger 
play with small bomblets (which are about the size of a tennis ball) :( COPE offers rehabilitation and provides 
artificial limbs, walking aids and wheelchairs for victims. More importantly, it gives them a hope for a normal 
life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03191.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Sculpture made by using covering of the cluster bombs in front of COPE information center&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/DSC03192.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Each of the cluster bomb contains around 600 to 700 small bomblets...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/IMG_20180423_105414542_HDR.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The region of Nong Khiaw in the north of Laos is still in a great danger&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/IMG_20180423_105431405_HDR.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It is recommended to not walk off the path&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we explored the area of Mekong promenade. We noticed really nice looking place for a night market (apparently 
opened in 2018) with new, wooden stands, however half of the were empty and most of the vendors were still selling 
on the street. The night market stretched from the sunset view point to the Chao Anouvong statue. This area of the 
city was really crowded in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/IMG_20180412_191904124.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Night market glowing in a distance...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/Vientian/IMG_20180412_191659775.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Since the food on the market didn't have any English descriptions, we opted to play it safe and go 
to a local restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical information:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bus ticket to Thakhet (from Don Det) - 110 000 Kip / per person&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bus ticket to Vientian (from Thakhet) - 80 000 Kip / per person&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tuk-tuk from the southern bus station to the center of Vientian - 30 000 Kip&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Entrance fee to Wat Sisaket, Phrat Keo - 10 000 Kip per person&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 09:43:59 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2018/10/Vientian/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2018/10/Vientian/</guid>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
        <category>laos</category>
        
        <category>urban</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Don Det, a gateway to Laos</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Crossing the borders by land is always more complicated than by plane but we like challenges. Actually, the ride 
from Siem Reap to Don Det in Laos was smoother than we were expecting :) Maybe due to the right choice of bus 
company (&lt;a href=&quot;http://asiavantransfer.com/&quot;&gt;Asia Van Transfer&lt;/a&gt;) or just pure luck. Since the journey 
isn’t easy and requires a few changes from bus to van to boat, it was very useful when the employee of the 
company showed us a folder with pictures detailing how the transfer would go. The morning of our departure they 
explained us again in details the whole procedure so we felt quite confident. However the driver who took us 
to Stung Treng (first stop where we had a 1 hour break for a lunch) was driving in a very dangerous way, speeding 
70-90km/h through a villages full of people cycling and kids playing on the side of the road. That was the longest 
part of a journey, 5 hours by minivan. After a lunch (2-5$) another minivan drove us to the border where we had a 
chance to exchange American dollars to Lao kip (exchange rate 1$ = 8200 Lao kip, on Don Det it was 8100) and fill 
the entry card for the Lao visa. However, first we had to leave officially Cambodia what means getting a stamp for 
2$. Then we were free to walk with our luggage to arrivals of immigration office on Lao site where we all could get 
visas. Visa rates change depends on country of your origin, but there is a chart to see your country rate, for 
Polish citizens it is 30$, Sebastian (Belgian) had to pay few dollars more. On the top of that we paid an additional 
1$ (per person) because we were crossing the border during the weekend and 2$ (per person) for the “activation” of 
the visa. It is basically a state-condoned bribe, but they’ll hold onto your passports until you pay up. So arguing 
about those extra fees will just extend the whole procedure and the driver will not wait for someone who is late. 
After all got their visas we started the last drive to Nakasong where we had to change for a boat to Don Det (north 
pier). During less than 20 minutes boat ride we knew this gonna be an amazing place! And indeed, we stayed there 
longer than we planned :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mekong river runs through China, Myanmar, Laos, Thailand, Cambodia, and Vietnam. Big differences in the water 
level and many rapids create a perfect conditions for spectacular waterfalls and we were going to look for them. 
This region of Mekong delta consist of lots of tiny islands between each people travel by small boats. Most of 
them are uninhabited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no ATM on the island so be sure to have enough cash with you! It is also not necessary to book a room 
in advance since there were plenty of options to choose from. There are two main roads on Don Det, on the sunrise 
and sunset site of the island, where you can find a wide variety of bungalows. Get one with a balcony and a hammock, 
this island is just perfect to lay back, relax and do nothing :) We booked a (rather expensive in hindsight) hotel 
room for the first night and were welcomed by two cockroaches (which Sebastian had to deal with before I could 
sleep), as we decided to stay longer we got a bungalow on the sunrise side of the island. The advantage of the 
situation was that we could check the cleanliness, the condition of the mosquito net and the comfort of the 
hammock before taking the room :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We again decided to rent a bikes (10000 kip per bike) and explore the island where we stayed, Don Det and 
Don Khon. Both islands are connected by the historical French bridge with a beautiful view on Mekong Delta 
backwater. We started to cycle from the north pier of Don Det, following the dirt path on the sunrise site of 
the island. Then we crossed the bridge and again started to cycle along the east shore what is indicated on the 
map by increasing number of kilometers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/Map-of-DonDet.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;As indicated on the map, we cycled around 20km on both Don Det and Don Khon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC02989.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Even cows were running away in a hurry when they saw Sebastian's tiny red bike with a pink basket&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC02996.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The combination of blooming trees, blue sky and water looked incredible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC03020.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The only church on Don Khon, as always beautifully painted and well-maintained&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC03003.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The shore of the Don Khon visible in a distance, our next destination&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/most.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Getting closer to the bridge connecting two islands, Don Det and Don Khon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After around 8-9 km of cycling, already on Don Khon, we noticed sign pointing to the waterfalls and decided to 
check them. We left our bikes close to the restaurant, crossed an unstable wooden bridge and started to look for 
the best view on waterfalls. The waterfalls are a bit hidden so you need to carefully walk between high bushes 
(we turned left after crossing the bridge). There was also a box to donate some money for a maintenance of the 
bridge by locals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC03033.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Wobbly bridge remained me of these from Nepal :O&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC03029.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Small, hidden cascades...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our idea was to cycle further to the south of the island, however at one point we were forced to stop because the 
bridge collapsed. With no way to get across we had to backtrack a few kilometers and take another path. It was 
getting awfully hot already … perfect time for a lunch and a cold drink with a view over the Mekong Delta. We 
left the main attraction of the island, Li Phi Waterfalls for the afternoon. On the way there we noticed rusty 
locomotive, legacy of the time when there was a railway connecting both islands (7 km long). It was closed in the
middle of 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/IMG_20180408_125016225.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC03054.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Watermill close to the waterfalls&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC03070.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Water buffaloes cooling down in a pond&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC03074.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Water accumulates furiously below the edge...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/IMG_20180408_134204158.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I found a place where time passes slowly :D I could sit on this bench all day long...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/IMG_20180408_140729160.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Chilling out in the shadow of the bar, next to the beach&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC03103.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It is common to have a pig on a rope instead of a dog in front of a house. As you can see, 
they adapted to strong sun by darker color of the skin and hard soil by having a massive snout&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/DSC03089.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The sunset view from our guesthouse, truly amazing! :D This region is well-known from the best 
sunsets in SE Asia. What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Laos/DonDet/IMG_20180409_184526029.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Here I discovered the best beer in SE Asia :) Perfect to drink while admiring a sunset!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We really like the character of this place and relaxed atmosphere so it was difficult to leave this place. We 
experienced many power cuts in the evenings, owners of the restaurants were ready for such a possibility and 
immediately put a candle on the table what made an atmosphere ever better :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next destination was Vientian, the capital of Laos but how to ride almost 850km? :O If you want to make it in 
one go, be ready for a boat ride, 2h bus to Pakse, then night bus (12h) to Vientian. It didn’t sound appealing to 
my boyfriend who is tall and always has difficulty to be comfortable on the bus. In one of the offices we bought 
a bus ticket to Thakhek, where we decided to spend one night and split into two parts this long distance to Vientian. If you want to know about problems we encountered during the journey, check upcoming post :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical information:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Entrance fee to Li Phi/Tad Somphamit Waterfalls - 35000 kip per person&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renting a bike - 10000 kip per person&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bungalow - 40,000 Kip (5$)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Room in a guesthouse 13$&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bus ticket to Thakhek - 70000 KIP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other possible activities we did not try:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Kayaking tour - 170,000 KIP - 220,000 KIP depending on agent (half day)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tubing - 10,000 KIP&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Both required attention since there are many places with the rapidly increasing current which turns into rapids!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 10:43:59 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2018/10/DonDet/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beyond-the-known.eu//en/travel/2018/10/DonDet/</guid>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
        <category>laos</category>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
